<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>chloethekayakingchihuahua.com</title>
   
   <link>http://chloethekayakingchihuahua.com</link>
   <description>One small dog discovering the beauty of Vancouver Island.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Debra Lynn</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Devil’s Bath: A Great Place to Find an Old Flame (and Examine a Few Skeletons)</title>
	  <link>//devils-bath</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2021-06-06T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//devils-bath</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>August 6, 2017</b></p>

<p>James and I joined his son, Dakota, and Dakota’s girlfriend, Cassandra, at Link River for a family get-together. It had been a really hot summer and Link River has lots of trees to keep us cool. I was also hoping to check out the driftwood graveyard that we saw on our very first official kayaking trip, so I could take pictures with a better camera than the flip phone I had at the time. It was also a good place to do some low-key family kayaking, because Dakota and Cassandra had a toddler, Gabby, and because my 26-year-old son and the computer brain behind this blog, Ramzi, was coming too.</p>

<p>Because James had just bought a new truck, a four-wheel drive Nissan Titan, we ended up with three vehicles. Rather than trade in my Tacoma, we decided to give it to Ramzi. We used the opportunity to bribe him to come kayaking with us. I also had in mind the possibility to check out the Eternal Fountain and Devil’s Bath. I have been a property taxpayer in Port Alice since 2010 and hadn’t yet seen Port Alice’s trademark tourist attractions. Devil’s Bath had a little surprise for me that would send me back 40 years in time, causing me to have some serious reflections about my life and veering it onto an unexpected course.</p>

<p>James joined Dakota, Cassandra and Gabby at Link River on Thursday. I stayed back so I could get some canning out of the way and then drive down to Nanaimo to meet Ramzi at the ferry on Saturday. </p>

<p>When I finally got to Nanaimo—two hours late which Ramzi noted with emphasis because he is all about doing things fast (he was even two weeks ahead of schedule when he was born)—I met him at the mall that is just up from the terminal.  As he was coming to meet me, I tried to put a bow on the windshield. It refused to stick to the truck and stayed on my fingers instead. We hugged and proceeded to ICBC to change the ownership title.  </p>

<p>We were acting like a couple of goof balls, forgetting things and almost losing important papers! The lady at the insurance office sent us to the bank to get a sheet for payments but halfway there we realized it was Saturday and that banks would be closed! On top of that, Ramzi wanted to pay cash anyway! It looks like our giddiness even affected the staff at the licensing office! When we came back, I saw that I left my ownership papers on one of the desks! The paperwork seemed to take all day and we had a heck of time getting the old plate off the truck. After raising Ramzi as a struggling single parent, it felt great to give him something expensive for once. Finally, all was done and just in the nick of time. If we hadn’t gotten it all done before closing, he wouldn’t have been able to take the truck home that weekend. </p>

<p>Since we were way behind schedule anyway, we decided to kill even more time and have a sit-down dinner in at Montanas. By the time we crept into Link River, it was around midnight. James was shocked to see us venture on wilderness roads so late. Travelling in the bush in the middle of the night is not something I would normally do, but the route to Link River is short and clearly marked.  </p>

<p><b>August 6, 2017</b></p>

<p>James and I joined his son, Dakota, and Dakota’s girlfriend, Cassandra, at Link River for a family get-together. It had been a really hot summer and Link River has lots of trees to keep us cool. I was also hoping to check out the driftwood graveyard that we saw on our very first official kayaking trip, so I could take pictures with a better camera than the flip phone I had at the time. It was also a good place to do some low-key family kayaking, because Dakota and Cassandra had a toddler, Gabby, and because my 26-year-old son and the computer brain behind this blog, Ramzi, was coming too.</p>

<p>Because James had just bought a new truck, a four-wheel drive Nissan Titan, we ended up with three vehicles. Rather than trade in my Tacoma, we decided to give it to Ramzi. We used the opportunity to bribe him to come kayaking with us. I also had in mind the possibility to check out the Eternal Fountain and Devil’s Bath. I have been a property taxpayer in Port Alice since 2010 and hadn’t yet seen Port Alice’s trademark tourist attractions. Devil’s Bath had a little surprise for me that would send me back 40 years in time, causing me to have some serious reflections about my life and veering it onto an unexpected course.</p>

<p>James joined Dakota, Cassandra and Gabby at Link River on Thursday. I stayed back so I could get some canning out of the way and then drive down to Nanaimo to meet Ramzi at the ferry on Saturday. </p>

<p>When I finally got to Nanaimo—two hours late which Ramzi noted with emphasis because he is all about doing things fast (he was even two weeks ahead of schedule when he was born)—I met him at the mall that is just up from the terminal.  As he was coming to meet me, I tried to put a bow on the windshield. It refused to stick to the truck and stayed on my fingers instead. We hugged and proceeded to ICBC to change the ownership title.  </p>

<p>We were acting like a couple of goof balls, forgetting things and almost losing important papers! The lady at the insurance office sent us to the bank to get a sheet for payments but halfway there we realized it was Saturday and that banks would be closed! On top of that, Ramzi wanted to pay cash anyway! It looks like our giddiness even affected the staff at the licensing office! When we came back, I saw that I left my ownership papers on one of the desks! The paperwork seemed to take all day and we had a heck of time getting the old plate off the truck. After raising Ramzi as a struggling single parent, it felt great to give him something expensive for once. Finally, all was done and just in the nick of time. If we hadn’t gotten it all done before closing, he wouldn’t have been able to take the truck home that weekend. </p>

<p>Since we were way behind schedule anyway, we decided to kill even more time and have a sit-down dinner in at Montanas. By the time we crept into Link River, it was around midnight. James was shocked to see us venture on wilderness roads so late. Travelling in the bush in the middle of the night is not something I would normally do, but the route to Link River is short and clearly marked.  </p>

<p><b>August 7, 2017</b></p>

<p>We had the typical type of family outing, with kayaking, swimming and sun-bathing. I got to be grandmother to little Gabby, just following her around and helping her to explore things. Ramzi and I paddled out to the driftwood graveyard that James and I had visited on our very first kayaking trip, but the driftwood somehow looked flattened and less interesting. I guess we’ve had a great many adventures since then! Ramzi had to do a few goofy things: shoot water all around with the bilge pump and sit at a submerged picnic table looking like he’s waiting for a server. He’s a comedian! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/the_whole_fam_damily.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>The whole fam damily!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/geeks_can_paddle.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Geeks can paddle</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/ramzi_up_a_stump.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Ramzi up a stump</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/waiter_over_here_please.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Waiter! Over here please!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/the_somewhat_flattened_driftwood_graveyard.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>A somewhat flattened driftwood graveyard</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/a_tangled_root.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>A tangled root</em></p>

<p><b>August 8, 2017</b></p>

<p>The next day, after our offspring departed to their respective homes, James and I drove out to the Eternal Fountain. Surprisingly, there were quite a few people in this remote spot in the bush. It felt like a slightly busy street in the middle of nowhere! </p>

<p>The Eternal Fountain is essentially an underground stream in a karst formation that makes a brief appearance at the surface. A karst formation is a network of caves, underwater rivers and depressions created by gradual weather effects and erosion. The Huson Caves that we visited in 2016 (check out the post “Huson Caves and Little Huson Lake: Stuck in a Labyrinth with Shifting Walls”) was another manifestation of a karst formation. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/the_eternal_fountain.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>The Eternal Fountain</em></p>

<p>Later, we drove to Devil’s Bath. Devil’s Bath is a “cenote,” which is a flooded sinkhole. It is apparently the largest in Canada measuring 359 metres around and 44 metres deep caused by the collapse of an underground cavern. It was a little creepy because of the strait steep banks that seemed to be leading to the “underworld,” hence, probably why the name, “Devil’s Bath.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/devils_bath.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Devil’s Bath</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/northwest_bank_of_devils_bath.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Northwest bank of Devil’s Bath *</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/guardians_of_the_cenote.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Guardians of the cenote</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/james_and_his_truck.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>James and his new truck</em></p>

<p>The cenote is connected to the Benson River through cave passages that are 80 metres below the water table. The river itself is a like a canyon, with high eroded banks. The water at this time of year was a series of semi-still pools, but it probably really roars with spring runoff. </p>

<p>As we drove up to Devil’s Bath, shortly after another vehicle drove up and out stepped this older guy with white hair. He walked toward me and started talking to me like he knew me. We shared some work-related experiences and talked about the University of Alberta in the 1980s. Finally, as he got into his vehicle to leave, I asked him his name. I had recognized the name right away and I really knew only one person in my life who had that name. For some reason, I had not made the connection in my brain until he had driven off. We more than worked together! We were “a thing”! I think it was partly because he looked so different from the time that I knew him—which was nearly 40 years ago! I couldn’t quickly link up the images of his younger and present-day selves.</p>

<p>James and I headed through the bushes just northeast of the Devil’s Bath and down the bank full of trees, fallen logs and rocks to the Benson River. I certainly wouldn’t call it a “well hewn” trail. If anything, it requires a little imagination to discern. On the way down, James was playing “Twenty Questions.” I told him of a brief relationship I had with a guy with that name, but I couldn’t quite believe that it was him. James said I had to admit that there aren’t many guys around with a name like his. Then, the disparate parts of my brain fused together, and I finally realized who he was…even though I already knew who he was!  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/a_well_hewn_trail_to_benson_river.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>A “well-hewn” trail to Benson River</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/dont_forget_to_duck.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Don’t forget to duck!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/goin_down.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Goin’ down!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/and_down.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>…and down</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/and_down_some_more.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>…and down some more!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/you_coming.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>You coming?</em></p>

<p>James later said he thought I had made quite an impression on him. I answered that “Well, I was a pretty crazy in those days.” As James and I talked about the situation throughout the day, he would sarcastically refer to him as “your boyfriend.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/water_is_a_little_low_this_time_of_year.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>The river is a little dry this time of year!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/still_pools.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Still pools</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/inunkshuk_made_by_a_previous_visitor.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Inukshuk made by a previous visitor</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/the_benson_river.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>The Benson River</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/james_contemplating_a_swim.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>James contemplating a swim</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/james_taking_a_dip.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>James taking a dip</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/where_daddy_go.JPG" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>“Where Daddy go?”</em></p>

<p>Before I realized the connection between us, the old flame had said something interesting. I don’t remember his exact words, but he said something like, “you forest fire lookout types are not much into relationships.” I thought it seemed like an odd thing to say with James right there beside me. </p>

<p>Although what he said was something I had always believed in my bones, hearing it come directly from someone else’s mouth gave me a bit of a shock. So many people in my life would shake their head at my choice of occupation and suggest, in various ways, that I find a job where I could have more of a social life and maybe meet a nice guy. I would usually rebuff the idea as so “plebian.” I tended to see myself as a woman who was tough, extremely independent and happily solitary. I didn’t consider myself a “relationship-type” of girl. I thought, for once, someone gets what I’m really about! </p>

<p>Then I wondered why I thought of myself that way! After ruminating on it for a good long while, I realized that there was a more insidious reason why. </p>

<p>My father had a serious anger management problem. He would get into these explosive rants where he would call me the most horribly insulting names he could think of, which included some very ugly gender-based slurs. He then would almost always top it off with the same dictum: “no decent guy will ever want you, and even if he does, sooner or later, he’ll smell you out!” </p>

<p>This was not a couple of isolated events, but a regular occurrence from my early elementary school years to my early twenties. When he was in a better mood, however, he didn’t become a “nice father” and say nice things and apologize for his vile behaviour. He just ignored me like I was a ghost. </p>

<p>Maybe my dad’s rants would not have had so much of an effect if not for the fact that no one else around me said anything different. Compliments, affirmations and endearments were not a thing in my family, to put it mildly. I was an only child for the first six years of my life, and we lived in somewhat isolated conditions—on a farm in northern Alberta. I didn’t have much contact with other kids, or people for that matter, until I went to school, and, even then, my social contacts remained quite limited. The only time I remember someone complimenting me on my looks (or anything) was when an unfamiliar woman came to our house for coffee and said I was pretty. Because that was the only time that I had heard anything of the sort, I assumed she was nuts. </p>

<p>I grew up thinking that I was not quite a “real girl,” technically female without the looks, charm, allure, “feminine wiles” or skills to attract a guy that other girls seemed to have. Because I had broad shoulders and muscular arms, I thought I virtually looked like a man. And, of course, I was “too fat,” though, when my son sees photos of me when I was young, he calls me “a stick.” I considered myself to be “androgynous” or “asexual” or “genderless” or “one of the boys.” I thought I could be a great friend to a guy, but nothing more than that. I considered myself more as an observer of human relationships, rather than a participant in them. If a guy seemed interested in me, instead of thinking of him as a potential prospect or even simply a boost to the ego, I saw the situation as a weird, convoluted and unsettling threat. Situations that would have made other girls feel “enthralled” or “alive,” tended to give me a feeling of overwhelming unease. I had no mental construct in my mind for being “the apple of someone’s eye” or an “object of desire.” Whatever men were looking for in a woman, I thought I didn’t have it; I believed I had a “neutral” effect on men. I was an artist and, as far as I was concerned, the only love of my life was art!   </p>

<p>Because being female seemed like such a bad thing, I tried to act as much like a boy as possible. I had very tomboyish interests and shunned any activity that smacked of femininity, such as wearing dresses, doing my hair or wearing make-up. To get my father’s attention—which all children are compelled to do—I would show off to him how I could lift heavy things or effectively wield a hammer. I supposed it worked in a way, because he found it quite amusing….and he certainly enjoyed the extra help on the farm!</p>

<p>As a teen I was severely shy. I often walked around with my head bowed and trying to hide my face with my hair. Whenever I would hang out with my girl friends and we would meet a cute bunch of guys, I would retreat to the back of the group so the “real girls” could do their thing. When I was older, I would rebuff guys left, right and centre, then constantly bemoan that I didn’t have what it takes to get a boyfriend! If I met a guy that I found interesting, I simply assumed I didn’t have a chance with him. If a guy was really “gaga” over me, I thought there had to be something seriously wrong with him, or that he was just pulling my leg. It’s amazing what lengths we will go to prove our parents right! </p>

<p>Now I realize that I was probably just as attractive and feminine as any girl my age; plus, I could be very vivacious, bubbly and energetic…which might have even made me come across as “sexy” sometimes (probably made worse by the fact that I had no idea I was!). No-one who is young could be considered unattractive: youth is the very definition of beauty, and I may have even been more attractive than some! It explains why my interactions with men would always turn out so “weird,” even explosive sometimes. I was trapped in my own existential reality, and terribly out of touch with what was <i>really<i/> going on around me. I was in a psychological prison created by my father’s venomous rants and it led to a lot of confusing situations and dangerous misunderstandings. </p>

<p>Back in 1978-79, when I was 19, I was in a long-distance love triangle with an American who I so badly wanted to be with. Although he said that he would have preferred to be with me than the other woman, I felt so unworthy next to her that I just quietly slipped out of his life without a fight. I really “knew my place.” I was effectively held back by the idea that I wasn’t “good enough”; I had a profound sense of “non-entitlement.” Not a day in my life has passed by since then that I haven’t thought of him! </p>

<p>A year later, when I was travelling near where he lived, I had another opportunity to try to win him over. My travel companions and I were having a party in our hotel room and, after I mentioned him, I had a major meltdown. They tried their hardest to console me and convinced me that I should try to contact him. They didn’t suggest any other action than that, perhaps believing I would “instinctively” know how to take it from there. I contacted him. We spent some time together, then I left again. I didn’t bother to mention to him that I was having a hard time living without him. I didn’t think I’d be taken seriously if I did. </p>

<p>I only went to see him as my friends ordered me to. They neglected to mention that I should try work things in my favour as well, which is what one might normally do in that situation. I now realize that he must have been totally confused by my sudden appearance and subsequent disappearance! </p>

<p>Talk about long lasting invisible bruises! He had even broken up with the other woman at that time and I still didn’t feel entitled to try to win him over…and all because I thought he was “too good”! I told this story to a friend of mine in the eighties, and she scolded me for not fighting for him. It was a strange concept to me at the time. Now, only after decades have passed, has the idea only <i>started<i/> to make sense to me. It’s hard to sell yourself when you are taught by your father that you are fundamentally horrible, disgusting and despicable! </p>

<p>My dad’s rageful attacks was gaslighting of astronomical proportions, putting me totally out of synch with my own life. I was being made to feel unattractive <i>because of <i/> my attractiveness! If I had been less so, I probably would have been able to circumvent his wrath and develop a more positive sexual identity. </p>

<p>I realize there were other situations that I gravely misinterpreted because of my low self worth that I remember, and there were probably plenty more that didn’t even register. I tended to have plenty of “guy friends,” not boyfriends, just guys who were friends (or so I thought). Now, I realize, some of them (except the gay ones) might have been contemplating becoming more than just friends. </p>

<p>When I was an undergraduate, a guy hung out with me for nearly a year. My friends and acquaintances would, rather sarcastically, bug me to take things to “the next level” with him (instead of all the derision, a long sincere heart-to-heart talk about the situation would have been more effective). I found the idea demeaning and thought that it would “ruin a good friendship.” My companion disappeared for a time and then turned up again married to his childhood sweetheart. Needless to say, he wasn’t interested in hanging out with me as a friend anymore (which actually surprised me at first!). If I had been told growing up that “any decent guy would be lucky to have you” that situation probably would have turned out very differently. </p>

<p>When I was working in the restaurant and hotel business not long after becoming a single parent, I was becoming acutely aware of how having a partner was almost necessary. There was a guy who I worked with who very enthusiastically asked me out. Shortly after, when I was having a coffee break with the rest of the staff, including one of my supervisors, we discussed my upcoming date with this guy (which I now realize, I should have kept a secret). My supervisor quickly proclaimed that he was “desperate,” and, not realizing that she might have been jealous, or spiteful, or simply a vehicle for evil in the world, I took her words for hard fact. I guess after hearing what I had always heard growing up, it was something I could not handle. I met him for coffee but ruled out any more dates in the future. Not long after, one of my co-workers informed me that he had quit his job (at a time when jobs were quite hard to come by). I was totally in shock, not because I realized that I had missed an opportunity to go out with someone who was quite enthralled with me and who probably would have treated me well, but because I couldn’t understand why he would have such a strong reaction over “someone like me.” </p>

<p>My father’s indoctrinations went deep, laid down early in my life as the foundation for my self-concept. I couldn’t see the flaws in my way of thinking because my reality was created out of those flaws.  </p>

<p>The guy I met at Devil’s Bath and I were involved briefly, but I was more interested than he was at first (probably because he seemed unavailable and not a risk to my solitary status quo). After we were apart for a while, he suddenly showed an interest in me one day “out of the blue.” Strangely, I abruptly gave him the brush off as I have done with so many guys. Whenever a guy comes across as “too interested” I always make a run for it; then, once he’s well out of reach, I beat myself up for running! It would be nice if I could see these situations coming in advance and prepare myself, but they always seem to catch me unawares and I panic and run. I did panic with James, but I had the opportunity to back-track. </p>

<p>Although this pattern causes me much grief and guilt and I’d like nothing more than to be able to make it go away, I realize it is simply an extension of my hiding behind my girlfriends when we ran into a cute bunch of guys when I was a teenager. Also, because my dad was always such a menacing figure, I would always “make myself invisible” when the man of the house was around. I never had the chance to learn pro-social behaviours with my opposite-sex parent. You also tend to think there is something really fishy is going on if guys are acting like they are attracted to you when you’ve been repeatedly told that you shouldn’t be appealing to anyone worthwhile! </p>

<p>I did consider my “unattractiveness” a weird sort of freedom. It meant I didn’t have to get my heart broken like so many other people did and that I could “hang out” with guys and approach guys (like I was “one of them”), confidently assuming they would never get the wrong idea. Methinks I may have been erroneous about that assumption more times than I’d care to consider! I realize that I probably came across as confident because I had no real expectations, which lead to a lot of strange “unexpected entanglements.” </p>

<p>Later on, I had moments when I got half the inkling that I might have qualified for the “relationship game”—but without coming to the realization that I could have been considered attractive or desirable. When things wouldn’t work out, I wasn’t that disappointed because I didn’t expect much in the first place (which was probably a factor in why they didn’t). Whenever a guy broke up with me, I would just shrug my shoulders and say, “OK.” I would then erase my expectation as a rogue thought that didn’t really belong in my life. In fact, I was often relieved because I felt too much “out of my element.” </p>

<p>It rarely got to that point though because I would usually break up with him first—even before the relationship had a chance to get off the ground! Between my parents’ fighting and my dad’s dictums, I couldn’t envision that proverbial “happily ever after.”  </p>

<p>Lately, I’ve been painfully coming to terms with the fact that, with a better attitude and a little conscious effort, I probably could have had practically any guy I wanted—which could have happened shortly after graduating from high school! I just needed to conceive of the idea as a genuine possibility. It would have happened “naturally” if I had had a father with a positive attitude toward me. Looking back, I am amazed to see how I had plenty of opportunities to have a partner! There was a weird algorithm in my brain that cancelled them all out! If not for my father’s indoctrination, instead of being the “lifelong bachelor” that I have been, I probably would have been one of the first girls to hop on the permanent relationship bandwagon! </p>

<p>Since this epiphany, I started trying to boost my self esteem by starting small. I started taking care of something innocuous and “non-threatening” like my elbows, which later led to using face cream, taking luxurious skin softening baths, giving myself facials and so on. I never used to spend that much time on my appearance before and I am finding that it’s quite fun! I used to balk at the idea of doing anything for “vanity” before. If I had engaged in such activities when I was young, my father’s attacks probably would have intensified. Maybe these little bits of self-care don’t make a big difference in themselves, but they seem to be giving me a bit of an overall glow just because I’m taking care of myself (I used to be a very much a “wash and wear” girl, or guy, or that something in between). This has led to a general overall improvement in my appearance and demeanor, probably because I developed a new perspective. I even lost some weight for some unknown reason! At nearly sixty years of age, I finally discovered I was a girl! </p>

<p>All my life I complained to my friends about my painful lack of “feminine wiles,” as if hoping that, somehow, they would teach me something. I now know that feminine wiles are not some long, complicated list of tactical manoeuvres, but rather, the simple notion that one could be attractive to <i>someone<i/>. It’s not something you can easily learn if your father has been saying the most utterly horrible things possible about you all throughout your developmental years! </p>

<p>Over the course of my life, I sometimes had friends who tried to “straighten me out.” Some tried to give me make-overs to boost my self-esteem; others would out and out scold me like a schoolmarm for not being flirtatious or friendly with guys. What really needed fixing and that they could not see was my damaged internalized self-image, created by years and years of stomach-turning insults. </p>

<p>I was sent out into the world totally without a compass for navigating the often-treacherous complexities of human sexuality and, consequently, that which makes the world go round! I was deprived of knowing “the things all women know.” In this society where women are still so much at a disadvantage, I wasn’t even allowed to survive using “women’s oldest ways.” It’s amazing I survived at all! Because this aspect of life was in such a huge blind spot for me, it left me incorrigibly naïve about society in general! When I eventually tried to insert myself into dating life, I did so with a very over-simplified juvenile understanding. Things that some girls learn at age 6, I was struggling to make sense of in my 30s and 40s. A lifetime of social knowledge suddenly fell into my brain shortly after the meeting at Devil’s Bath. </p>

<p>Because of the lack of a critical piece of information, it feels like I’ve been an imposter in my own life! I feel I need to erase it like a whiteboard and start all over again! Lately, I have been looking at old photos of myself with this new perspective and I find I am constantly shaking my head. It’s amazing how my father has been “pulling the strings” in my life …even in death! </p>

<p>This delay in my awareness is probably due to the isolation of lookout work: it kept me in suspended animation as I contentedly fed my “solitude addiction” (solitude was relief from all the chaos) for a good portion of my life. Sometimes I’m torn up inside myself that I’m not a lookout anymore (I should have never quit to take over the management of my father’s estate that turned out disastrously anyway); however, I am strangely grateful that I finally reached this realization. I guess it helps to have a troubling mystery solved. Many strange encounters I have had with the opposite sex now suddenly make sense. I now know why all those crazy situations in my past were so crazy! I simply could not read or interpret “the signs.” Guys were probably seeing me as “all woman”—possibly attributing all kinds of (very confusing) clever motives and devices to my behaviour—and I saw myself as a female eunuch! </p>

<p>This is a fine example of how parents should be careful what they say to their kids. They may be listening better than they think! Kids are like clay. They can be moulded into anything, including perpetual victims or dangerous monsters! This is why I am a believer in mandatory parent training: anybody about to have a child should take a rudimentary course in child development and behavioral management (based on widely accepted research of the last approximately 100 years that teachers and child-care workers have to study) just like drivers have to study driving before being able to drive. Maybe my father would not have been influenced by a course he was obliged to take, but I have seen even well-educated and well-intentioned parents say and do very damaging things to their kids that could lead to a lifetime of low self-esteem and grief. Sometimes, in “traditional parenting,” a child’s low self-esteem can be viewed by a parent as a “tactical advantage,” which, I believe, creates more long-term disadvantages than they may realize. There are other parents, afraid of being “abusive,” who will resist setting boundaries and standing their ground with their child…which can be just about as bad! People should be provided some basic useful information before embarking on the very difficult and complicated job of being a parent! </p>

<p>Ironically, in his heart of hearts, my father wanted nothing more than for me to get married and have a family. I think, whenever I would return home from my adventures in the Alberta wilderness or around the world still very much unattached, it was a serious source of anxiety for him. It’s as if he thought I would greedily usurp that which he told me I could not have! Unfortunately, I was one of those kids who listened much too well. </p>

<p>I take delight in the fact, but for a brief catastrophic marriage in my early thirties that was one of those “unexpected entanglements” (on steroids), my father knew me as a single woman right up until the day he died. James has been the only “real” boyfriend I’ve had for any length of time, and he arrived seven years after my dad passed away. </p>

<p><b>********</b></p>

<p>My ruminations after the Devil’s Bath encounter might have had an affect on my relationship with James, as I was back in Port Alice on my own three months later. Even though we had been together for three years, our relationship had always been tentative. I think we only lasted as long as we did because we both tended to be accommodating and good at avoiding conflict. We were “getting along,” even though there were some major unresolved issues hanging in the air that were not getting any closer to being resolved.  After the Devil’s Bath encounter, what “little bit of glue” that held us together just totally disintegrated. After walking away from a guy I wanted so badly a long time ago and just now realizing that it didn’t necessarily have to turn out that way, it has turned my world view completely upside-down! I came to the realization that I need to start living my life on completely different terms…and what those terms are exactly I’m not quite sure yet! </p>

<p>My relationship with James was good for me in a way though. I had a boyfriend who was especially good at doing all those dutiful boyfriend things (dinners out, flowers on Valentine’s Day, not calling me horrible names, etc.) and it helped to contradict some of those gruesome lessons my father taught me. Things that I once would have considered “a miracle” I now have come to expect at a minimum. A “real relationship” can be a good learning experience; too bad it happened for me “the first time” (at least the first time with conscious intent) when I was in my fifties! </p>

<p>You can add to that that James and I had some terrific kayaking adventures together in some spectacular, largely undiscovered places! James was a great kayaking partner! His methodicalness in planning for our trips and timing the tides was critical in keeping us safe; yet, at the same time, he had just enough of a sense of adventure to make them interesting. He was also very fit, especially for a guy in his fifties, and he could handle those long marathon trips. The blog certainly won’t be the same without him. </p>

<p>I left Mackenzie to return to my house in Port Alice on December 4, 2017, when James was at work. I also “stole” Chloe, which was uncharacteristically brazen of me (a tendency that seems to have emerged lately). Because she has breathing problems and sometimes goes into convulsions, she needs regular exercise to keep her weight down and her air passages open. She wasn’t tolerating the cold and the snow in Mackenzie and was refusing to go for walks, while frequently using the carpet in the basement for a bathroom. I used to put booties on her and carry her to the end of her walk and then let her scramble home across the snow and ice. It was something, but hardly enough. Add to that the fact that James worked 10 hours a day or more and he would have had a hard time finding a dog sitter for an uncooperative sickly dog who hates snow. It also would have increased her chances of having a convulsion without anyone around to give her Benadryl to help her breathe. If I left her in Mackenzie, I worried she wouldn’t survive much longer. I figured her chances were much better on Vancouver Island. </p>

<p>In the end, James conceded it was for the best. In the spring, he came to Port Alice so we could exchange some of our belongings and he left me Chloe’s papers (by then he already had another girlfriend!). He even gave me the Manitou, which was greatly appreciated!  </p>

<p>Interestingly, after I left James, Dakota and Cassandra also broke up and “the whole fam damily” was scattered like pinballs across the country. I haven’t seen Gabby since, but I do occasionally see her on my Facebook feed. She sure is growing into a lovely young girl! For sure, when she grows up, she is going to be a real bombshell! I hope she knows that!</p>

<p>It’s ironic that, because of this incredible realization that I wasn’t the ugly undesirable charmless ogre that my father always taught me that I was, that I have ended up a solitary woman again, and probably for the rest of my life! It would be just like me to figure something like this out in my twilight years! Although my perspective has dramatically changed, it’s hard to change a lifetime of behavioral patterns and attitudes at age 60….especially when I didn’t get to “practice” in those critical early years. At least now, after this epiphany, I am feeling very “settled” and comfortable in my skin. It is like someone has removed a “veil of ugliness” that I had been wearing all these years! Even so, I will undoubtably be spending a lot of time reviewing past events with new eyes and mourning the loss of what could have been.</p>

<p>It’s a good thing I can enjoy my own company, as 18 seasons of lookout work can attest to. I’ve got so many projects on the go that it makes my head spin! If I’m lonely, I don’t have time to think about it. If I turn out to be female in my next life, however, I will have to make sure that no one takes it away from me! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post17-devils-bath/me_at_age_16.jpg" alt="Devil&#39;s Bath"><em>Me at age 16; Photo credit: Robert Tannas</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Side Bay: Port Alice's Best Kept Secret</title>
	  <link>//side-bay</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2021-02-27T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//side-bay</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>July 30, 2017</b></p>

<p>Side Bay, the fantastic bay with the oddly innocuous name, is Port Alice’s best kept secret. Since I’ve lived in Port Alice, I’ve listened to people talk about Side Bay like it was some kind of precious gem or a magical haven. This really means something in a place like Vancouver Island that has stunning views just about everywhere you look! </p>

<p>Before going to Side Bay, I talked to my cat sitter, Leah, about it. She enthusiastically told me that I’m going to love it. I asked her what is so special about it. She mused and then, struggling for an answer, said that it is “like Hawaii.” </p>

<p>Well, yes, I guess it is a lot like Hawaii. It is a large bay with islands and black lava rock protrusions with the background sound of a gentle surf hitting the beach. It just has pine and fir trees instead of palm trees. It also does have an air of a warmer place, which, I realized, might be because it is right beside Brooks Bay Peninsula. Brooks Bay Peninsula was just missed by the big ice cap in the last ice age and still has vegetation from another era. I think some seeds might have blown over to Side Bay. I did notice some odd-looking plants there. While preparing this post I realized that it has the most photos of all other of my posts. This goes to show you that Side Bay has plenty of “visual interest.”</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/odd_plants_1.jpg" alt="Side Bay"><em>Strange looking plants 1.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/odd_plants_2.jpg" alt="Side Bay"><em>Strange looking plants 2.</em></p>

<p>James bought a new truck, a four-wheel drive, just in time for our trip to Vancouver Island. We also had a new fancy dancy kayak carrier, a new kitchen centre and a couple of camping chairs with their own little table on the side and cup holder. We were stylin’ kayakers!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stylin.jpg" alt="Side Bay"><em>We were stylin&#39; kayakers.</em></p>

<p>Since we had taken this road to the Wild West Coast before, we thought that we knew where we were going. Once we got into the belly of the forest, uncertainty set in. We relived our fear of taking the wrong turn and getting lost or ending up on top of a mountain cut-block with no room to turn around. We scrambled around the truck for our <i>BC Coast Explorer</i> and the <i>Backwoods Map Book</i>, trying to figure out this route like it was the first time we’d taken it. We bemoaned that I did not bring a printed out copy of my post for Gooding Cove of 2016, that I laboriously edited and re-edited, to use as a guide. There is such a labyrinth of logging roads in the area, it is just too easy to get lost. </p>

<p>Things were a little easier this time though, as, with Port Alice’s new tourism promotion initiative, we found nice new professionally done guide signs that replaced the home-made ones from the year before. In keeping with the tendency of BC backwoods signage, however, there weren’t many signs at the beginning of the route. </p>

<p>To get to Side Bay, take Marine Drive from Port Alice around the inlet. Follow it until it “becomes” Teeta Main (there’s no turn or dividing marker)—it is just Marine Drive in one part, and Teeta Main the next part. When you get to that hairpin turn 25 km from Port Alice, there is no guess work at all. There is a lovely sign pointing the way to Teeta 500 (or K 500) and other mains that come after. After Teeta 500, you take K main, then I main. Somewhere around I main, the signage for Side Bay and Gooding Cove starts, and that’s all you need to know. </p>

<p>May I once again remind you to avoid travelling on the logging roads between 6 am and 6 pm on the weekdays when the loggers are at work. In a lot of places, the roads are very narrow and only allow passage for one vehicle. This means if you come face to face with a logging truck you could be toast! They will stop if they can, but sometimes they can’t because of their heavy loads and could plough right into you! If this happens, they are not liable either. If you do come up on a logging truck that can’t stop for you, head straight for the ditch or the bush. </p>

<p>There is another complication to this scenario. Though most loggers maintain banker’s hours, some contract-based logging companies don’t always—so you must always be wary. I talked to someone in the forestry industry and he says that that’s quite rare for the North Island. It tends to happen more on the Central Island. To travel the backwoods of Vancouver Island you need to have a thick skin…but a lot of people do it. In my post for Gooding Cove, I wrote about how James and I came across a logging truck and survived. It appeared the truck was expecting us. A Western Forest Products pick-up had driven by earlier and they likely informed the logging truck via the 2-way radio that there were a couple of yahoos with kayaks on the road. </p>

<p>Also, when you venture into the back country, make sure to tell someone where you’re going and when you plan to be back, so it doesn’t take days or weeks before someone realizes you’re missing. </p>

<p>Interestingly, the trip to Side Bay only took two hours. When we went to Gooding Cove last year—because we got side-tracked to Cayeuse Main and had to back track, and then ended up stuck on a mountain top (with a stunning view of Quatsino Sound)—the same journey took us 5 hours! </p>

<p>Arriving at Side Bay, we spent a few moments in stunned silence taking in the scene before us. There were people around, but the vastness and the beauty of the huge bay made them seem quite insignificant. </p>

<h4><i>Side Bay Beach Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-0.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-3.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-4.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-5.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-6.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-7.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-8.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-9.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/sidebay/sidebay-10.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p>We set up camp right away and headed out onto the water. There was a good surf hitting the beach, but the water in the middle of the bay looked <i>flatish</i>. After struggling to figure out a way to get on the water without getting Chloe and ourselves all wet, we decided to go in nose first. It worked! </p>

<p>Once we were on the water, we discovered that we were riding some pretty big rollers. The water wasn’t “flatish” at all! It felt a little like being on an elevator going up and down without stopping. If this were my first time on a kayak, I would have been having a serious panic attack!</p>

<p>We paddled by the rocky north shore, trying to take pictures while also saying “wee wee” as we went up and down the ocean roller coaster. We ended up at Mayday Island, on the sandy beach at the northeast corner, to have our snack. </p>

<h4><i> Riding Swells </i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/swells-0.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/swells-1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/swells-2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/swells-3.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p><b>July 31, 2017</b></p>

<p>That first sojourn we thought we had seen all there was to see and wondered what we’d have to explore the next couple of days. As it turns out, there would be a lot to discover just by checking out all the nooks and crannies of the bay. </p>

<p>The next day, we planned to get up “bright and early” so we could maybe kayak out to Lawn point, a stretch of land that looks to be covered by a primed lawn from the air, which is actually very tall grasses hiding rough boulders. We were even fantasizing about going on to Restless Bite by passing the turbulent Kwaikiutl Point.</p>

<p>We had the best intentions. Even though we did get up fairly early, by the time we got cleaned and fed and had our coffee, we didn’t get onto the water until around noon. It turned out to be a good thing. The water wasn’t as turbulent as the day before. The rollers on the bay were much smaller than yesterday, but, as we headed toward the open ocean, they became enormous! </p>

<p>James said we could turn back if I wanted to. I paddled ahead a little more, then accepted the offer. We later realized we should only be out here with skirts and not with a Chihuahua. We realized, once our kayaks filled with water out there, our gooses would be quite cooked! We saw a few kayakers paddle out to that area, but they were likely not kayaking with a Chihuahua and probably had skirts, tons of experience and plenty of bravado!</p>

<p>The situation then got a little more interesting. After deciding to head to the far east side of the bay (the other end of the bay from our campsite) the wind picked up. The ride got rough and rocky. We kept getting splashed. We realized, if this wind had suddenly come along on the open ocean, it would not have been fun to say the least! If we had gone out there in the morning when the water was calmer, we might have gone too far afield, possibly even going on a hike. When it would have been time to go back—after a little daytime heating—we probably would have had to fight the winds and maybe even a few breakers on the open ocean. </p>

<p>Hitting that wind, we made a sharp left turn and headed in the direction of our campsite. This is where I came to understand the term “crosswinds.” The waves were going from west to east, and the wind was coming from the north to south. The smooth undulating waves developed choppy points that knocked us all over the place!</p>

<p>Having cut our kayaking trip short, we were quite disappointed. Nevertheless, we took our kayaking snack at the far west end of the beach in the shade of the stones. We checked out a huge cave from afar that was only visible at low tide. We did some sunbathing and even some swimming. James went in the icy cold water (in this way, Side Bay is not like Hawaii!). As usual, James was the braver one, swimming a lap or two. I got wet up to my waist and dunked my hair in the water. Later I noticed that my hair was quite soft and silky, which probably explains why so many products from the sea are used in personal care products.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/cave_visible.jpg" alt="Side Bay"><em>Cave visible at low tide.</em></p>

<p>As evening approached, we went out for a short kayak ride to explore the shore just north of the beach. We saw a driftwood beach, then came upon a wall of stones. At that moment the wind seriously picked up again and I wanted to go back, but Mr. Adventure just went around the stones. It was a good thing too. What we discovered was a photographer’s delight!</p>

<p>On the other side of the wall of stones we found volumetric shadows, high contrasts with blue and black and water making interesting patterns pouring through crevices. I call this place the “Side Bay Stonehenge.” I took too many pictures, and it was a lucky thing too. I still had a lot to learn about photographing shadows using metering. If I focused on the rocks, the camera would overexpose them and take away the strong shadows. I had to focus the metering on the water to make the rocks looks like the dark and powerful monoliths that they were. </p>

<h4><i>Side Bay Stonehenge Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-0.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-3.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-4.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-5.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-6.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-7.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/stonehendge/stonehendge-8.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p><b>August 1, 2017</b></p>

<p>For day three, we were out of ideas; but still ended up having an adventure anyway. The winds from the north were fierce. We “settled” for a return to Mayday Island. Since we were passing by the north side of the island. I saw a monolith of a rock that would have made a good picture, so I decided to turn the kayak around and get a shot. As I was doing this, James, ahead of me and already around the island, noticed I was nowhere to be seen! </p>

<p>After I took my shot, I had to fight with all my might to turn back around in the wind and waves and follow the course. James wasn’t too happy about my risking life and limb for art. He gave me quite a scolding when he finally found me. The whole thing was kind of for naught anyway, as the photo wasn’t very sharp or well-framed.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/risky.jpg" alt="Side Bay"><em>The risky photo.</em>*</p>

<p>Landing at Mayday Island for a break, the creativity gods compensated me for not getting a good shot of the monolith. As I came sliding onto the beach, I saw these little seaweed plants twisting and turning in the clear water. With the added enhancement of ripples, the seaweed struck me as expressionistic art. I took a gazillion pictures! Here are just a few of them. </p>

<h4><i>Seaweed Art Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-0.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-3.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-4.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-5.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-6.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-7.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-8.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/seaweed/seaweed-9.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p>We originally wanted to paddle up the creek just east of the island, but it had to be ruled out because of the low tide. It probably could have been an interesting adventure. Paddling around the east side of Mayday Island, we found a beautiful hidden beach for some all-over sun tanning, skinny dipping and rock picture taking. It had a smooth sandy white beach surrounded by black lava boulders and a view of black lava islands in the distance. It felt like it was just us and the Pacific Ocean! The water was great for swimming: it was nice and shallow with clear water revealing a sandy bottom. I spent more time in the water than James this time. It took me a while and a few dunks to get adapted to the icy water, but I even swam around a bit. </p>

<h4><i>Secluded Beach Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/secluded/secluded-0.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/secluded/secluded-1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/secluded/secluded-2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/secluded/secluded-3.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/secluded/secluded-4.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p>When we got back, we were treated to a ride up the mountain in quads by a couple of our camping neighbours. They took us up to a lookout point where we were able to get some great aerial shots of the Rugged Islands and Brooks Bay Peninsula. The sky was tinged with a little bit of brown—a sign of the many forest fires raging that summer—that turned the whole scene a dusty pink as the sun went down. </p>

<h4><i>Lookout Point Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/lookout/lookout1.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/lookout/lookout2.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/lookout/lookout3.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/lookout/lookout4.jpg" alt="Side Bay">
<img src="/assets/images/post16-sidebay/lookout/lookout5.jpg" alt="Side Bay"></p>

<p>Our guides, who had been camping at Side Bay every summer for years and years, acted like they were showing us around their personal back yard. They told us stories of people they had met here. They told us about a Japanese lady who came straight from Japan, with no previous kayaking experience. She landed in Canada, bought a kayak and proceeded to kayak around Vancouver Island all alone with no radio and apparently very little food. She had even somehow managed to paddle around the potentially violent waters of Cape Scott and survive! When I was talking to one of the fishermen at the marina in Port Alice once, he told me that a buoy that was located at Cape Scott once recorded waves 100 feet high before it disconnected and went out of commission! It was quite possible the waves got even higher after that! </p>

<p>When the Japanese lady showed up at Side Bay, with only a bag of rice left in her kayak, the campers fed her a nice big meal. They gave her a lure and taught her how to use it so she could feed on fish. She took off the next day before everyone was up, leaving the lure behind. The next hurdle on her destination was the tip of Brooks Bay Peninsula, which can be almost as bad as Cape Scott. Not far past the tip, the ocean floor takes an abrupt and steep drop, which can make for some wicked turbulence. We all wondered if she survived. Even so, it’s amazing how far she managed to get on her romantic, poorly informed ideas about kayaking in Canada. </p>

<p>The couple also told us the historical story about a plane carrying payroll cash that crashed at Lawn Point. We were told two guys had survived the crash; one was severely injured. The more able-bodied person decided he would hike out to get help. Oddly, he also decided he should take the payroll money with him. The guy who was left had died and the guy who hiked out was never found. He might have been attacked by wild animals, but the cynic in me contemplated that with all that money, he might have seen fit to hitch or hijack a ride on a boat and leave the country. </p>

<p>I looked into the story a little more at home. It was a US Navy plane with six crew members that didn’t return from a navigation exercise in 1943. The plane did indeed have payroll on it. While searching for the Port Hardy Air Force Base, the pilot saw a break in the clouds and what looked like a carefully manicured lawn. It was the tall grasses hiding the abundance of rocks of Lawn Point! When the wreckage was found in 1944, with a rudimentary camp and the remains of five men, one man and one payroll, as well as watches, guns and other valuables were missing. </p>

<p>After telling their tales, our guides then asked me about my blog that I had mentioned a couple of times before. As soon as I told them the title of this entry will be “Side Bay, Port Alice’s Best Kept Secret” I gulped, wishing I could take my words back. Their expressions suddenly changed. Their chattiness ended abruptly. They quickly took us back down the mountain and gave us the cold shoulder for the remainder the weekend. They had been keeping Side Bay as their personal private getaway and didn’t want the outside world to know about it! </p>

<p>As I was looking at the map of Side Bay while writing up this post, I realized that Klaskino Inlet is very accessible from there. To get there by road you have to go over a rough mountain road, which, until not long ago, was impassable. I recently ran into some very experienced kayakers who made it there by the overland route. I had taken their number for writing an article about them for the North Island Gazette, but ended up losing it when my One Note app malfunctioned. They said it was passable because of some active logging going at the time, but who knows if it still is? I have long thought of Klaskino Inlet as a possible “Kayakers’ Shangri la.” It cuts into the mountains for quite a distance so it should have a very “canyon-like” and remote feel to it. From Side Bay it would probably amount to a two-day excursion there and back going at a steady pace. </p>

<p>John Kimantas talks a bit about it in his <i>BC Coast Explorer </i>. There was a lot of active logging going on there at the time, so it sounded like an industrial zone. It might have reverted to it’s more or less natural state by now. He also mentions that there are not a lot of good places to launch. Anchorage Island might be a good place to set up camp for the night—if it’s anything like Mayday Island—but don’t quote me on that. It could very well be nothing but rocks and trees right up to the water! There must be some beaches to land on around it where the waves from the open ocean hit and smooth out the shoreline into nice sandy beaches. It’s something worth checking out for the adventurous. </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Schoen Lake: Cathedral in the Sky</title>
	  <link>//schoen-lake</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2020-10-26T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//schoen-lake</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>As the mill in Port Alice closed down and people moved away for work, James and I eventually ended up joining the exodus in September of 2016. He went to a mill maintenance shut down in Mackenzie, then was offered a job there. I kept my place in Port Alice and we planned to come back for holidays to kayak and continue the blog. In the summer of 2017, I came back to Port Alice earlier with Chloe and the cats to do some work on my house. When James arrived for his two-week holiday, we crammed in three monumental (and as it turned out) life-altering kayaking trips into those two weeks.</p>

<p>Mackenzie is way up in northern BC, a couple of hours past Prince George. Like Port Alice, Mackenzie is a pulp mill town that has had its ups and downs. The mill closed for a while, then reopened again. Before I bought my place in Port Alice, I was actually looking at some dirt-cheap houses in Mackenzie during the time that the mill was closed.</p>

<p>Mackenzie reminded me very much of my hometown, Athabasca, in Alberta, except it has a lot more snow! Athabasca is quite dry for the most part. It can be cold, but there is usually only foot or two of snow most years. Mackenzie is at roughly the same latitude, but the town is nestled in mountains—so there is <i>incredible amount</i> of snow! Sometimes it gets so bad that people have to shovel the snow off their roofs to keep them from caving in. A fond (or not-so-fond) memory I have of Mackenzie is looking out into our back yard in the middle of winter and seeing our patio furniture almost buried.</p>

<p>We took quite a few kayak trips around Mackenzie in the spring, to Morfee Lake, Tudya Lake, Azouzetta Lake and Dina Lakes. Morfee Lake is right in the municipality of Mackenzie. You can’t see any trace of the town when you’re there, so it feels like you are deep in the wilderness. Tudya Lake is a quiet and quite secluded-feeling lake 25 minutes south of Mackenzie, just off of highway 97. Azouzetta Lake is nestled in the mountains near the famous Powder King ski resort on the road to Dawson Creek. Dina Lakes was unique. Near the sprawling Williston Lake, it is a cluster of lakes with portage routes of varying lengths. We took a shorter portage and ended up encountering a moose and a brown bear quite close up. The north certainly merits its own blog, but I will only include a few photos for the sake of comparison. One thing about kayaking in the north—though we saw some beautiful pristine sites—there was something about the lack of tides that was disappointing. I guess the changing tides add an extra element of challenge and adventure to a kayaking trip.</p>

<h4><i>Morfee Lake</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/morfee_10.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<h4><i>Tudya Lake</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/tudya_68.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/tudya_107.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/tudya_205.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/tudya_250.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<h4><i>Azouzetta Lake</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/azuouzetta_235.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/azouzetta_278.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/azouzetta_295.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<h4><i>Dina Lakes</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_1.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_2.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_3.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_4.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_5.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_6.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_7.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_8.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_9.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/dina_10.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<p><b>July 23, 2017</b></p>

<p>Back on Vancouver Island, we ended up going to Schoen Lake as an afterthought. Our big plans were for Side Bay this trip but, when we arrived in Port Alice, we needed to do some kayaking right away. Schoen Lake seemed to be the only thing we could fit into that time slot. James lived in Campbell River most of his life and hadn’t seen it before, though he knew people who had. He assumed that it was just another overrun public campsite, but it would be a good excuse to get paddling. It turned out to be more than an excuse. It didn’t feel “public” at all. It was more like a remote spiritual retreat. </p>

<p>To get there we turned west off Highway 19 and followed the Mt. Cain road. There are signs at both sides of the turnoff for Schoen Lake and Mt. Cain, plus one at the turnoff. It’s hard to miss. There are probably a couple of branches you can take before the main turnoff that could get you on the same track. We took one of those branches, but still saw lots of signage that lead us to the road to Schoen Lake. Once you get past a certain point, there is really only one road so it’s hard to get lost. It’s not a place with an endless maze of logging roads like it is on the way to Gooding Cove and Side Bay.</p>

<p>The road is still for die-hards. If you take an 80-foot camper on that road it’ll probably end up in a thousand little pieces by the end! Chloe wasn’t too pleased about the rough, bumpy ride. She kept giving James and me that “can you make it stop” look. It was only a 14 km route: but being so rough and tightly encased with trees, we had that “going to the ends of the Earth” feeling again. When we were beginning to doubt there actually was a campsite at the end of it, we finally saw the park sign and several campers. In fact, the sites were nearly full. We still managed to get a lovely one close to the water.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/canada_flag.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Canada flag on Schoen Lake</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/praise_peaks.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Praise to the peaks!</em></p>

<p>Schoen Lake is surrounded by mountains that encase it like tall cathedral walls. The mountains were so big and close, I could barely fit them into the frame of my camera. Unfortunately, inexperienced with my new recently acquired digital camera and equipment, I did not realize that I had a wide-angle lens in my camera pouch that could have captured everything in a single frame. It wouldn’t have captured the closed in feeling though. </p>

<h4><i>Mountain Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_0.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_1.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_2.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_3.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_4.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mountain_6.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<p>As we paddled the evening of our arrival, we kept hearing waterfalls. James had to get off the kayak and go into the forest looking for the source of the sound. He found only a couple of small cascades. He kept feeling that if he would only go in a little farther, he would find a REALLY BIG waterfall…which probably would have been the case…maybe halfway up the mountain! The next day we would discover that Schoen Lake has many waterfalls! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/waterfall_james.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>A waterfall that James tried to chase</em></p>

<p>We made it past the point where the lake bends when we were hit by a blast of wind. We wanted to go to the end of the lake, but, being that the sun would be setting soon and we were tired, we decided to save our energy for the next day.</p>

<p><b>July 24, 2017</b></p>

<p>We started out early in bright sunshine. We were grateful the wind was at our backs, but knew we’d pay for it later. On the way to the end of the lake, the many waterfalls produced a pleasant background noise. We couldn’t see half as many as we could hear.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/mini_waterfalls.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Mini waterfalls</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/watching_waterfalls.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Watching waterfalls</em></p>

<p>The real waterfall bonus came when we reached the end of the lake and looked up to the ice fields on top of Mt. Schoen with its series of very high up branching waterfalls. It was stunning from far away, so it had to be magnificent up close! If I didn’t have such bad knees, we could have hiked up there. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/waterfall_schoenpeak.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Waterfalls on Schoen Peak</em></p>

<p>When we landed at the end of the lake, we found ourselves in a dark, spirited old growth forest. I went around snapping the better part of my standard minimum 400 shots for a daily kayak outing. A lot of them ended up overexposed because I didn’t know how to adjust my camera for dark places. I did manage to get a few that captured the magic of the forest. </p>

<h4><i>Rainforest Gallery</i></h4>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_0.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_1.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_2.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_3.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_4.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_5.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_6.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_7.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_9.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_11.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_12.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_13.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_15.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake">
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/rf_8.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"></p>

<p>We followed a trail going in the opposite direction of the ice fields, on the hunt for waterfalls. By trail I don’t mean a wide path with lots of signage, I mean a wormy little skinny trail half hidden by shrubs and marked by tiny and very short strips of florescent tape. It only went so far, but it did at least bring us to a small waterfall. James, always wanting to explore, climbed behind it to investigate. I sat on the rocks, enjoying the waterfall and practicing getting the flowing water effect with my camera. It wasn’t hard, being that the light was so limited. It gave me no option but to use the required slower shutter speed. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/flowing_waterfall.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Waterfall with flowing water effect</em></p>

<p>When we walked back to the boats, James checked out the trail up the mountain that went toward the ice field waterfalls. He thought it would lead to a plateau where one can get a better view. James seemed to have nominated himself caretaker of the waterfall route, clearing some of it and making big plans to return some day to complete the trail. </p>

<p>James was gone for a while, leaving Chloe and me to wonder and wait for him in the dark and spooky forest. Finally, I called for him and he came back shortly after. Before getting on the boats, we went toward the creek and perused an elk graveyard. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/snack_time_rainforest.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Snack time in the rainforest</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/elk_bones.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Elk bones</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/elk_skull.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Elk skull</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/chloe_spooked.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Chloe spooked!</em></p>

<p>We paddled as far as the bend in the middle of the lake, then stopped for a snack. It was also time to give Chloe a dunking to cool her off. I took photos of wildflowers. We walked to the creek and finished the remainder of our snack by the bubbling rocky stream reflecting little stars of evening sunlight. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/cooling_off.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Cooling Chloe off</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/blue_wildflower.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Blue wildflower</em></p>

<p>On the final leg of the journey, I must have been fighting a flu bug. I suddenly lost all the energy in my arms! I moved very slowly, making the paddle move from sheer willpower rather than strength. I was amazed I could get anywhere at all, especially going against the wind. As arduous as it was, we were sad when it was over.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/kayakers.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>I do hope these kayakers know what they are doing!</em></p>

<p>We ended up going back on the water at dusk. We paddled around near the campsite; then, floating side by side on our kayaks, we gazed at the gradually fading twilight pastel hues on Mt. Schoen. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post15-schoenlake/twilight_on_shoen.jpg" alt="Schoen Lake"><em>Twilight on Mt. Schoen</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Drake Island and Quatsino: Ghosts of the Sound</title>
	  <link>//drake-island-quatsino</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2020-05-12T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//drake-island-quatsino</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><i>I’d like to give a special thanks to three people for helping me with this post: Gwen Hansen of the Quatsino Museum and Archives for providing historical information on Ed Frigon; Jane Hutton of the Port Hardy Museum and Archives for allowing me to photograph images of Ed Frigon and his hotel; and, my friend and friendly neighbour, Evelyn Hartford, for providing me with a  photograph of Frigon’s hotel, articles and for being a general all round valuable resource for historical information on the North Island.</i></p>

<p><b>July 19, 2016</b></p>

<p>We wanted to go out on Neroutsos Inlet to Drake Island where the notorious Ed Frigon had his hotel and trading post between 1895 and 1917. We had been talking about the idea for a while. It took some convincing to get James on side for it: he thought our kayaks wouldn’t be big enough to carry all the stuff we needed. We finally concluded it shouldn’t be that hard, since many have paddled all the way around the Island with just their kayaks for carrying supplies…for a good stretch anyway. As it turned out, after paring down a few items, there was plenty of room for what we needed. Sea kayaks are big kayaks.  </p>

<p>Ed Frigon is one of Port Alice’s favourite historical “characters.” The very picturesque islands on Neroutsos Inlet are named after him. Frigon was an entrepreneur, an adventurer and a man with a mind of his own. He also had several wives, though not all at the same time. </p>

<p>Ed or “Ned” Frigon was born in Maurice, Quebec. At the age of 21 he left his family to find riches in the California Gold Rush of 1848-55. He took a boat to Panama, then crossed the isthmus by foot through mud, swamps, tropical heat by day and swarms of mosquitos by night. Making it to the Pacific coast in a little over a week, he took passage on a schooner to San Francisco. Although he managed to find gold, it was never enough to overcome the overinflated living costs in the area. He left the mines in disgust. He worked for a time in the San Francisco Bay area; then, not happy with the warm climate, he headed further up the coast. He eventually landed in Victoria, BC. In 1857, after accumulating a tidy savings, he headed to Hope Island on the north end of Vancouver Island to be a fur-trader.</p>

<p>Frigon was one of the first few white men to live among the local Indigenous population. He appeared to get along well with them; but, from time to time, a few “cultural disparities” would emerge. </p>

<p>The material goods in his store could incite envy in people who knew nothing but living off the land. A small group of unscrupulous men once plotted to kill him and divide his goods among themselves. Forewarned by his Indigenous wife at the time, the night of the planned attack he locked all the doors and windows and slept with several loaded weapons by his bed. It turned out that the locked door was enough to thwart the plan. </p>

<p>The next day Frigon opened his store and behaved as if nothing had happened, but had a message sent to the authorities in Victoria. A few weeks later a gunboat appeared, heading in the direction of Hope Island. Upon landing, the commander of the vessel warned the First Nations community that they would be punished should anything ever happen to Ed Frigon. After seeing many Indigenous communities decimated by the colonists, they considered this a serious threat. Thereafter, Frigon was accompanied by an entourage of Indigenous bodyguards wherever he went, to the point it became a serious encumbrance to him. </p>

<p>Of Ed Frigon’s many wives, most of them were Indigenous. He outlived some, was deserted by others and had to send at least one back to her people. Although Frigon was believed to be monogamous, he had a certain charm with women. One of his wives, who was the jealous type, tried to stab him with a butcher knife while he was in his bed. As she raised the knife to deliver the fatal blow, Frigon grabbed her wrist and said, “Not tonight Marie!” He removed the knife from her hand and threw her out of the house. It was with some regret, as he thought she was a very good housekeeper and “une dame belle.” </p>

<p>Frigon carried on trading on Hope Island until 1889, then built a second trading post at Korprino Harbour. In 1895 he moved to Quiet Cove, (Pamphlet Cove) on Limestone Island (now Drake Island) where he built a store, hospital, steamship stop and hotel with a saloon that had the ‘longest bar north of San Francisco.’ When rumours of prohibition were about, Frigon sold his hotel to the mill in 1917. He retreated to a large property north of Port Alice to live with his last common law wife, Lucy Moon. Lucy Moon had the title of “The Last of the Long Heads”: she was the last member of a group of Indigenous people who bound the heads of their children to elongate them. The hotel was floated down to Port Alice where it became a boarding house for mill workers, called “Jones’ Hotel.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20and%20general%20store.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s hotel and general store</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Young%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em><center>Young Ed Frigon</center></em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Middle-aged%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em><center>Middle-aged Ed Frigon</center></em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Elderly%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em><center>Elderly Ed Frigon</center></em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20getting%20floated%20to%20the%20mill.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s hotel getting floated to the mill</em></p>

<p>To get to Drake Island we ended up launching from Atkin’s Cove, a place we had been to before. To get there you take Neroutsos Main north of Port Alice on the east side of Neroutsos Inlet. Keep going on Neroutsos Main for 12 kilometres. Make sure to keep a careful eye on your odometer—it might be the only way you’ll be able to find the proper turn. About halfway there you will see a fork in the road with a branch that goes up the mountain. Don’t take it. That’s Quarry Main. It won’t take you to Atkin’s Cove, but it will take you up the mountain for an incredible view! Go up too far and you will definitely be needing a four-wheel drive and a strong stomach for driving on high mountain roads! Once you pass a side road on Nertoutsos Main with a wire across it, go a few metres further and turn left along a little “goat trail” that’s just wide enough for a vehicle to pass. Sometimes it is overgrown with shrubs, but sometimes it’s brushed. Drive for about a half a kilometre to a pull-out where you can park. In total, you shouldn’t go over 13 km from Port Alice. Any more than that and you’re lost! Let me remind you that if you go out into the bush, make sure to inform someone where you’re going and when you plan to be back so you don’t have to wait for days or even weeks before someone realizes you are missing. </p>

<p>If you look hard enough, on the south west side of the pull-out, you will see an opening in the shrubs which should be marked with florescent ribbon. That is the trail head. If you walk into the woods to the west, you will start to see water. If you read about our first adventure to Atkin’s Cove from years back, you will see how we got terribly lost! Check out my post, “Atkin’s Cove: Lost and Lost Again!” and have a laugh!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Entrance%20to%20the%20trail%20to%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Entrance to the trail to Atkin’s Cove</em></p>

<p>James and I were originally going to launch at Kokwina Cove (which is a little portage to the east of the goat trail) that is at the edge of the Quatsino Narrows with all its nasty currents. We were going to time the tides to go out just before slack tide. I was apprehensive about the idea but didn’t say anything. Then, out of the blue, James voiced misgivings. I told him that if he’s uncertain, then I’m scared you-know-what-less! We talked about it some more, then concluded there were too many unknowns. We decided to take Atkin’s Cove to Drake Island instead. I said I would be willing to try Kokwina some day, but not with Chloe.</p>

<p>You could also get to Drake Island by launching from Port Alice, but it would be a minimum two-day trip. If you are a strong paddler, you may be able to make it to Drake Island in one day. If not, you could spend the night at Atkin’s Cove. Make sure to time the tides, so they are carrying you in the direction you want to go. Leave early in the morning before daytime heating makes the water on Neroutsos Inlet too choppy. </p>

<p>We dragged our supplies and kayaks down the hill to our launch point. Chloe was excited about getting into a kayak. As soon as I put a couple of blankets in her cockpit, she hopped in and wouldn’t leave!</p>

<p>The camera box only fits comfortably in the tandem Manitou; but, because I was due for surgery and James is so noble, he felt he had to paddle the heavier loaded down kayak. It ended up that I only had James’ phone—that doesn’t have a neck strap—for taking photos. I didn’t have much trouble paddling the larger kayak, but he insisted. It would turn out to be something he would woefully regret!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20hopped%20in%20the%20kayak%20and%20wouldn&#x27;t%20leave.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe hopped in the kayak and wouldn’t leave!</em></p>

<p>After leaving the tranquil calm waters of the cove, we met the rougher waters of Neroutsos Inlet—which were especially rough around the point! We made it around somehow, riding waves that made our kayaks feel like bucking broncos! </p>

<p>As soon as we came around the point to calmer waters, we met a community of Harbour seals—one with a baby—playing peek-a-boo with us. </p>

<p>When we crossed the inlet to the east side of Drake Island, our stomachs started complaining. It was 3 o’clock and we had only had breakfast. We landed briefly for a snack. Although we were on Drake Island, we still had a considerable paddle to get to Pamphlet Cove. As we paddled around the large island, we were getting impatient. We kept saying, “are we there yet?” It took a while, but we finally got there!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Kayaks%20landed%20at%20east%20side%20of%20Drake%20Island.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kayaks landed on the east side of Drake Island</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20inspecting%20the%20cuddy.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe inspecting the cuddy</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/paddling%20in%20the%20kelp.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Paddling in the kelp</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Kayaking%20Chloe%20with%20kelp.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kayaking Chloe with kelp</em></p>

<p>Coming up on the entrance of Pamphlet Cove, we entered a serene, windless, warmer, almost stagnant zone of the Sound. The water was calm, with bits of flotsam and foam floating on top. At the entrance of the cove were a couple of rock protrusions with bonsai-like trees on top. It made me think of a water-bound Japanese garden. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Me%20with%20bonsai-like%20trees.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Me with bonsai-like tree</em></p>

<p>We came across a sign surrounded by foxgloves. It informed us that the foxgloves marked the location of Ed Frigon’s hotel! That was the only sign of the previous human habitation, as the area had been almost completely reclaimed by the forest. </p>

<p>Before landing, we decided to explore the cove in our kayaks. The tide was ebbing out, but there was still enough water left for us to go in quite far. We saw lots of little fish. The cove is apparently a haven from the big fish of the sound. All the racing and roaring of the ocean was blocked out. Our voices and splashes echoed against the trees. James was well ahead of me, looking around and lost in wonderment. Unfortunately, that wonderment would be short-lived…</p>

<p>As I passed the shallow channel between the two sections of the hourglass shaped cove, I found a beautiful arrangement of three large starfish sitting together on some large rocks just below the surface of the rushing water. I snapped pictures like crazy! I was obsessed! I don’t know what it is with me a starfish, but they make me go bonkers! I envisioned making some serious money from the shot! </p>

<p>The current was strong and made it hard to stay still long enough to snap the photos. I kept putting James’ cell phone on my lap as I paddled frenetically. I took tons of pictures but kept wanting that one extra picture! When I started to put the camera away after that last extra, <i>extra</i> shot, as I transferred it from one hand to another, it did a sudden flip—as if someone or something had tried to reach out and grab it—then, plop!, into the water it went! </p>

<p>I screamed! I almost went in headfirst trying to reach for it. I tried to stay at the spot where it fell, so maybe we could somehow find it. I kept calling for James, but he wasn’t coming. I called again a couple of times. He finally showed up.</p>

<p>“What’s up?” he asked. 
I told him I dropped his phone in the water. 
He said, “you’re joking, right?” 
I shook my head in the negative. 
Again, he said, “You are joking?” 
I shook my head again. </p>

<p>We repeated that little interchange a couple of times more until he started to make the paradigm shift and acquire a very startled look. </p>

<p>I told him I was over the spot where it fell. In a frenzy, he got out of his boat in the shallow water, rolled up his shorts up to his hips and walked onto the rocks, frenetically searching and reaching in the water for his phone. </p>

<p>Feeling what we feel, Chloe, in the Manitou, was whining desperately. It took some time, but James finally found the camera. It was standing upright in a space between two rocks—which was why it was so hard to find.</p>

<p>With the phone retrieved, we paddled mournfully to our camping spot. I was slouched in the Eskia, paddling a good distance behind and giving James plenty of space. Needles to say, when we landed, he didn’t help me out of my kayak as he usually does.</p>

<p>After about an hour, James was back to his old self and being very poetic about the whole thing. He said it was bound to happen sooner or later. The very nature of cell phones is that they easily get damaged and lost, simply because they are not wired to a wall.</p>

<p>We landed in the area were Ed Frigon’s old floating wharf used to be. All that was left was a construction of poles covered with barnacles embedded in a very mucky shoreline. Half hidden in the trees was an upside-down boat, weathered, worn, with a couple of gaping holes in the bottom—definitely no longer sea-worthy!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20old%20floating%20warf%20(2).JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s old floating wharf</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Barnacle%20encrusted%20relic.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Barnacle encrusted relic</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/No%20longer%20sea%20worthy.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>No longer seaworthy</em></p>

<p>We walked around the forest looking for places to camp. We found the “Green Throne” built by BC Marine Trails. We prided ourselves in being one of the first few people to use it! We found some flat places with nice soft moss among the trees, which was in the area of the foundation of Frigon’s hotel. We didn’t think it was a good place to have a campfire. There were too many “forest fuels” around. We admired the holly and foxgloves—plants not native to the BC wilderness—that have been growing here for over a century. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20foxgloves.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s foxgloves</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20site%20of%20Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20today.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The site of Frigon’s hotel today</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Ferns.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Ferns</em></p>

<p>Finally, we went back out to our landing point and noticed a mound protruding out of the water. There was a small spot just big enough for our tent. There were also some rocks arranged in a circle, which was probably previously a campfire. We added a few more and it made a good fire ring. There was virtually no danger of starting a forest fire here!</p>

<p>We later found the hidden cache from BC Marine Trails that advised us to avoid having a campfire. We were going to keep our fire a secret, but I am going to go out on a limb and confess to it. The spot where we had it is probably the only safe spot to have one on the whole island. Having a fire anywhere else could surely lead to disaster. We felt, by leaving a fire ring on the rise, it will deter people from having one in a riskier place.</p>

<p>We set up camp and then took a walk in the forest, taking pictures of the foxgloves and trees and picking huckleberries. We didn’t do much for the rest of the evening except eat, roast marshmallows, drink tea and try to dry out James’ phone. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Harmony%20in%20green.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Harmony in green</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Old%20man&#x27;s%20hairs.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Old man’s hairs</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Unusual%20coniferous%20trees.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Unusual coniferous trees</em></p>

<p>We watched the tide creep up slowly over the course of the evening. We kept trying to figure out if our tent would end up submerged. It was to be an especially high tide: 11ft. We were getting anxious, staying up as late as possible to figure out how close it would get. </p>

<p>I was very tired, because I hadn’t slept much the night before, and James was just tired. We weren’t willing to wait around until 2 am for the high tide point. It turned out we had miscalculated the tide readings and it would not be as bad as originally expected. We didn’t think it would reach the grass—because grass can’t grow under sea water—but we weren’t sure. We thought it might only go to the sea asparagus, in which case our tent, only on grass, should be fine, though it would have been very close.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Sea%20asparagus%20growing%20up-side-down..JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Sea asparagus growing upside-down</em></p>

<p>We ended up working ourselves into a tizzy. We decided to move the tent to a higher point just to put the issue to rest. It was too bad because the other spot was so nice and soft and grassy. At the higher spot, we had to sleep on rocks and roots! When we got up in the night, James concluded that we probably would’ve been OK down below.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20tent%20on%20nice%20soft%20grass.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our tent on nice soft grass</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20tend%20on%20rocks%20and%20roots.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our tent on rocks and roots</em></p>

<p><b>July 20, 2016</b></p>

<p>The next morning, we were thinking of cancelling our trip to Quatsino. We were late for the flooding tide (this sounds a lot like catching a subway). We decided instead to paddle the last leg of the trip against the ebbing tide at a leisurely pace. We were bound to get there sooner or later. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y8Ywi0dfbP8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/It&#x27;s%20a%20kayaking%20dog&#x27;s%20life.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>It’s a kayaking dog’s life</em></p>

<p>We crossed the sound diagonally, seeing many passing speed boats. We saw a shoreline of houses, many of which were boarded up. Quatsino has seen better days and, I think, will see them again in the future once people discover what a paradise this is. </p>

<p>We cut around an island and a small peninsula. Finally, we came up to a lighthouse and then noticed a cove with a wharf, boats and a concentration of houses. We had finally arrived at Quatsino. We saw St. Olaf’s church and wondered if it was the church in Emily Carr’s painting, <i>The Indian Church</i>. It turned out not to be. When she was painting here in 1930, the church was a school. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20Quatsino%20Lighthouse.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The Quatsino Lighthouse</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/View%20of%20St.%20Olaf&#x27;s%20from%20the%20water.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>View of St. Olaf’s Church seen from the water</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/indian_church.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em><center>Emily Carr’s painting  <i>The Indian Church</i>, 1929</center></em></p>

<p>We paddled under the wharf, and, after landing, found ourselves in the company of a community of snakes zipping about hither and thither. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Driftwood%20root%20lodged%20under%20the%20dock.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Driftwood root lodged under the dock</em></p>

<p>Since I had been living in Port Alice, I had never seen Quatsino, but heard of many heard stories about it. I envisioned it as a place with aging hippies, huge gardens and peacocks running about freely. One of the residents there who has peacocks brought a huge bouquet of peacock feathers to the Legion one day. I ended up getting a few of them from the bartender I babysat for. </p>

<p>Until then, I didn’t have a boat to get to Quatsino and check it out myself. When I finally arrived, it didn’t quite live up to my perhaps over-idealized image of it. I was surprised that it looked a little dreary. This may have been because of the cloudy day. A major tragedy did happen there in 2002, where a father murdered his six children and then set his house on fire. Even further back, there was a domestic murder suicide. Perhaps the causes and effects of such events leave subtle signs and suggestions on the face of a village, the same way a person who has suffered a great loss has a permanent look of sadness in their eyes. In spite of that, I see that, one day, maybe 50 or so years from now, Quatsino will be a colourful little village (maybe even with the peacocks roaming freely) that will attract many visitors from around the world. It already does to some extent. Perhaps the Quatsino I was seeing in my mind before was a Quatsino of the future.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/A%20dreary%20day%20in%20otherwise%20quaint%20Quatsino.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>A dreary day in otherwise quaint Quatsino</em></p>

<p>Quatsino is a very different way of life. To get anywhere, you need a boat. The community once had an opportunity to install a road, but they voted against it. Although I tend to think of Port Alice as remote, residents leave Quatsino for Port Alice to do their shopping and have a bit of social life and “culture.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Backwoods%20GPS.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em><center>Backwoods GPS</center></em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Been%20parked%20here%20a%20while.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Been parked here a while</em></p>

<p>We went straight to the Museum, which looked like the only thing open.  We met the curator, Gwen Hansen. I asked her about Ed Frigon, and she led me to a filing cabinet. I read stuff while she and James conversed. Finally, feeling overwhelmed, I asked if I could get copies of the files. </p>

<p>A bunch of people came in who looked very Scandinavian. A very tall guy with a Scandinavian accent pointed to something on the wall and asked what it was. Gwen said it was a sasquatch comb and everybody laughed. Gwen later told me it was a herring comb, but I was still confused. I had to ask James to enlighten me. As it turns out you sweep the comb in the water, catching herring and then throwing them into your boat.</p>

<p>Chloe suddenly started whining hard. James and Chloe took leave of the museum. It turned out Chloe needed to take a really big poop! We were thankful that she didn’t take a dump in the museum! From then on, we resolved to always listen to Chloe, as she usually whines for a good reason (except when she wants extra treats).</p>

<p>We checked out St. Olaf’s church. James was just going to peek in the windows to see what’s inside. I had a more novel idea: I opened the door! It is amazing that there are still places on this planet that don’t have to be under tight security! We went inside, signed the register and took a few pictures of this tiny simple church that was originally the colony’s first school.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/St.%20Olaf&#x27;s%20Church.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>St. Olaf’s Church</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Inside%20the%20church.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Inside the church</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20in%20the%20church.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe in the church</em></p>

<p>Back at our launch point, we sat and had a snack and took pictures and videos of the snakes. It is amazing that snakes can be so beautiful! And fast! In a place where time moves so slowly, it was odd to see something move like it was late for a very important meeting!</p>

<iframe width="1620" height="1080" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RCpW9Ayq-HE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20eager%20to%20get%20in%20a%20kayak.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe eager to get in a kayak</em></p>

<p>For the trip back to Atkin’s Cove, I was back in Tigger and James in Eeyore. We paddled over the sound surprisingly fast. We took only 15 minutes to cross it. The snakes must have given us some of their energy.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/kelp%20bed%20by%20Quatsino.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kelp bed by Quatsino</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Going%20from%20Quatsino%20to%20Atkin&#x27;s.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Going from Quatsino to Atkin’s</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20point%20before%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The point before Atkin’s Cove</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Sea%20onions%20at%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Sea Onions at Atkin’s Cove</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20well%20marked%20trail%20to%20the%20truck.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our “well marked” trail to the truck</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Dreamland.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Dreamland</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/truck%20with%20kayaks.edited.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Truck with kayaks</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20way%20out.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The way out</em></p>

<p>James may have lost his phone—and his contacts—but I also lost the starfish picture. I had hoped that it ended up on the Cloud, but it was not the case. At home, James checked out a few tricks on the internet but, alas, the phone was pronounced pooched! He phoned Telus and, luckily, only had to add on another $1OO spread out over his payments for his old phone to get a similar new one. </p>

<p>We had a chat about the various ways people we knew have lost cell phones. One person lost their phone in the toilet! Another had to get a professional diver to retrieve theirs from the ocean and it ended up not working anyway! My son goes through a lot of phones too, but he tends to be a screen breaker. We concluded that cell phones are meant to be destroyed, probably because they are carried everywhere. It is one of those unintentional (or maybe intentional?) schemes that keeps the telecommunications industry booming! </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Huson Caves and Little Huson Lake: Stuck in a Labyrinth with Shifting Walls</title>
	  <link>//Huson-Caves</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2018-05-24T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Huson-Caves</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>October 21, 2016</b></p>

<p>Getting ready for our trip to Huson Caves, James and I were both pretty crabby. I was pooped from working at the pizza place Friday night, and James was stuck with virtually all the preparing. The only contribution I could make was to pack my own bag and water the garden. I was trying to water the garden deeply, but it was making James restless. He was eager to get going.</p>

<p>As we were packing up, Chloe was very concerned about being left. She sneaked into the truck when the door was open and refused to leave. When it came time for me to pull her out of the truck, so James could drive it out of the protective shade of the carport and the car in, you could tell there were a lot of thoughts going through her mind, and a lot of emotions.</p>

<p>On the road, we stopped at Hyde Creek for some coffee, aloe vera juice, the Gazette and the Sun. We checked our maps and determined we would have to turn onto the road to Zeballos. When we arrived at the turn, we stopped to read a map by the road, discovering, to our disappointment, there was no campsite at the caves—at least there wasn’t one showing. As it turned out, there was no “official” campsite, but there was a small unofficial one that was an absolute gem!</p>

<p>Seeing a campsite icon at Anutz Lake, we determined we would have to go right and right again—though that turned out to be a gross oversimplification of the facts. Driving down the well gravelled but narrow winding road, we saw a fork that gave us the willies. It brought back memories of our trip to Gooding Cove, where we ended up on a cut-block on top of a mountain with not much room to turn around. We listened to our instincts, which was telling us that this was not the turn we should take. They were 100% right. As it turned out, there were all kinds of roads and forks, but, thankfully, there were also regional district signs pointing the way to Anutz Lake and Huson Caves, though, not one for that first fork—which was probably the most critical one! It all is in keeping with the tradition of BC signage: of not telling you where to go until you’ve already figured out how to get there! We saw a sign that said Anutz picnic site, but we weren’t sure if that also meant it was a campsite. A truck came driving out. Assured by signs of human life, we decided to try it.</p>

<p>We penetrated the forest and followed a very narrow rugged road that seemed to be going to the ends of the Earth. We felt certain we would eventually find a nice hidden secluded place deep in the forest to pitch out tents. Instead, we found a mob! We came upon a giant family reunion, with people, kids and RVs everywhere! There seemed to be more vehicles, people and congestion there than downtown Vancouver! We couldn’t get out of there fast enough! You’d think we would have been happier to meet up with a pack of wolves! </p>

<p>We were back on the road and headed to Huson Caves, not sure what we would do about finding a campsite. As we drove, the road started looking more and more rough, narrow and forgotten. We caught sight of the butt of a big black bear before it disappeared into the shrubs. We finally came upon a pullout with information and direction signs for Huson Caves, which was the trail head. There was nowhere to camp at the trail head, but the park sign indicated a campsite further down. We drove on. The road got very dark, and steep in places. We finally came upon a dead end and a parked truck. We parked ourselves and, seeing water through the leaves, decided to take a little walk into the bushes. James went ahead of me. I later heard him say a very emphatic “Wow!” When I saw what he saw, I saw that he wasn’t kidding! We found ourselves on the shore of a very sunny small lake with a picturesque Swiss-like mountain in the distance. We were contemplating spending just one or two nights there and moving on, but those plans were promptly altered. I said I didn’t care if I sat around all day doing diddlysquat, I wanted to stay here for the whole four days. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/road_thru_the_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Road through the forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/deep_in_the_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Deep in the forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/our_private_paradise.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Our private paradise.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/looking_north.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Looking north.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/radiance.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Radiance.</em></p>

<p>The campsite is small, so it can only hold two, maximum three sets of campers. Hidden behind some bushes was the campsite of a young couple with a terrier and weiner dog. We also had a brief visit from a large crowd of people who just looked around and left. Our neighbours stayed until Monday. We had the beautiful picturesque spot all to ourselves on Tuesday. </p>

<p>We had recently bought a Nikon 3300. After pitching our tents, I went out and checked out what it could do around our campsite, which wasn’t much. I had a lot to learn. We later went out on the kayaks for a short paddle, but we didn’t have our usual amount of energy. Even Chloe seemed too pooped to kayak. Because it was the middle of the day, the water was wavy. We were heading toward other end of lake, but James hinted that it was farther than it looked. I suggested we head back. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_at_the_helm.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe at the helm.</em></p>

<p>On the way back to the campsite, we thought we could go past the logs and access the caves to the north. When I saw James working hard at it, I decided to land and save that battle for another day. I needed to purge my work week out of my head before I could do anything. James paddled around the driftwood for a while. When he came back, he determined that we could paddle there to get to the caves, however far the water lets us go—which, as it turned out—wasn’t very far at all! 
We spent the rest of the evening trying to take photos of the moon and Jupiter in the dark that ended up being just squiggly lines on a black background. I used James’s app to find out what other planets we might be able to see. We found out Mars was by the moon. Neptune and Pluto were on the other side of the mountain, though probably not visible to us anyway. I was falling asleep sitting up. I dragged myself to bed without brushing my teeth and slept like a rock all night…which is a rarity for me these days. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_moon.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The Moon.</em></p>

<p><b>May 22, 2016</b></p>

<p>We dawdled around camp until nearly one o’clock. We headed out on the lake toward the caves. The current lead us to the deepest spots, and we were drifting smoothly into the centre of the lake. The wind was coming from the north: we had to engage our warp drive paddle to get anywhere at all. We weren’t paddling too long when we met up with some logs blocking our path. James was surprised as, when he had kayaked here night before, that area was wide open. That was when we first realized that logs on water tend to move. Nevertheless, we could quite easily push through with our kayaks, getting hung up on a log only a time or two. I tried to take some pictures, but James complained I was going to get the camera wet by using it while in motion. He offered to hold onto my kayak, so I could get my fix of pictures for while. It worked for a bit, but not really. An artsie with a brand new SLR camera: I was a snap-happy maniac! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/heavenly_huson_lake.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Heavenly Huson Lake.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_snap_happy_maniac.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The snap-happy maniac.</em></p>

<p>We peered at what we thought was the entrance to the cave. It was choked up by millions of logs! Even if we had been able to somehow get past the log jam—which was impossible—we would have met up with cliffs, waterfalls, whirlpools, shallow rapids and rocks, rocks and more rocks! We overcame our denial, even though the circumstances were pretty obvious, and finally decided this route was impassable. Nonetheless, some weird part of us wanted to keep going. </p>

<p>We turned around to go back, but that was a problem! I was fiddling with the camera and quite oblivious to my surroundings. James was a bit ahead of me when I heard his expression of dismay. What? I asked, only half interested. “We’re trapped,” he moaned. In the short time that we were there, all the logs that we had passed by got pushed together by the wind after it had changed direction. It had closed the gap we had entered by and we were definitively trapped! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/i_do_believe_we_are_in_a_pickle.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>My dear, I do believe we are in a pickle!</em> </p>

<p>Panic started to set in. There were a lot of logs in our way. It seemed to be more than we had passed to get there. Maybe we could have walked on top of them all the way back to shore, but we would have had to leave our kayaks behind, or we would have had to drag them across the logs trying hard not to trip, fall into the water or damage our kayaks! We headed to a part of the lake that seemed to have less logs, though there were some gigantic ones among them. James pushed a few of the logs out of the way to make a path through the logjam. He warned me to keep close behind him or the driftwood would quickly close up and block me in. We struggled and fought, pushing and pulling on logs from our kayaks. Chloe was getting so distressed by our distress that she kept trying to crawl into my cockpit. Even though we were in the midst of catastrophe, I couldn’t help but reach for my camera several times, which, with fact that we were trapped, was making James even more irritable. What can I say, I am a slave to aesthetics! Finally, he told me to put that @#&amp;*# camera down. We managed to forge ahead, James creating openings in the logs, and I following close behind. Then we came upon a gigantic immovable log that was tightly jammed up at both ends! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_oblivious.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe oblivious.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/move_you_damn_logs.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Move you damn logs!</em></p>

<p>That’s when James got out of the kayak and started jumping on top of the log in frustration (he later confessed to me that he had fun doing that)! While standing on the log, he looked around, picked up a stick and started pushing logs around. He managed to create a temporary opening for Chloe and me. Before I was able to get through, I accidentally bumped James’ empty kayak and caused it to drift away (I’m not much help in a log jam, am I?). He had to run down the log to retrieve it! With his kayak secured, he pushed the last two logs apart with his legs so Chloe and I could pass under. I really, really wanted to grab for the camera, but didn’t dare! I found some mobility by grabbing onto logs and pushing them behind me. I moved myself along in one spot by grabbing onto the short branches and pulling. James got into his kayak and followed. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/now_what.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Now what!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/abandoned_kayak.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Abandoned kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/log_jamb.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Logjam.</em></p>

<p>Back at the campsite, we discovered that the campfire that we thought was out, actually wasn’t! I have to admit, I had lapsed in my vigilance. Because it had burned down and stopped producing flames and smoke, it was easy to do. By the time we came back, it was smoking again. See folks! Just because a campfire looks like its out, 
doesn’t mean it is! All it needed was the heat of the mid day and the wind to bring it back to life. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0Nnu3f8P8bc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>James then asked what we are going to do now. I said we go hiking. 
We ate our kayaking snack, then soaked our fire until we were sure it was completely out. Because we forgot to bring a day pack, we ended up having to use my laptop back pack to carry our hiking supplies. We drove back up the hill to the trail head with the park signs and the outhouses. We studied the map, read some of the info, and were off. I kept taking pictures of everything from moss to old man’s hairs. James was getting very impatient for a normally patient guy. He ended up walking ahead on his own, while I dawdled and clicked away like a woman obsessed. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_campfire_is_out.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The campfire is out!</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/are_you_coming_or_not.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Are you coming or not?</em></p>

<p>It turned out to be a short trail. We found ourselves going down some very steep stairs to a viewing platform overlooking a rocky stream that flowed into a cave. We couldn’t see very far inside it. James jumped over the railings and out of sight. I could not see the outcropping of rock that he landed on, so it looked like he was jumping into the river. James encouraged me to jump on it with Chloe. I said no thanks and passed the camera to him. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/creek_in_the_caves.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Creek in the caves.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/sheltered_waters.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Sheltered waters.</em></p>

<p>James flashed away inside the cave, then, disappeared for a while. Not knowing where he was or what he was doing, I just sat there and hoped for the best. Chloe was crying the whole time he was gone. He finally came back with a couple of pictures that were the money shots. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/inside_the_cave.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Inside the cave.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/james_money_shot.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>James’ money shot.</em></p>

<p>We went back up the stairs and found another set of stairs descending to a below ground oasis. The Huson Caves are part of a karst formation, caves created by gradual weather and erosion that form depressions, underwater rivers and caves. The Huson Caves themselves are carved out of a layer of limestone formed during the Upper Triassic period, over 199 million years ago. The water in a karst formation tends to flow between the layers of bedrock, rather than through joints or cracks, as other types of caves do. The canyon then became a home for vegetation, like lichens, fungi, mosses, ferns and shrubs that like to live in old growth cedar-hemlock rainforests—hence, the oasis effect. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/below_ground_oasis.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Below ground oasis.</em></p>

<p>On our way down, James checked out a dry cave and was tempted to go down a hole. He said he needed a rope to attempt it. I thanked God we didn’t have one! We both bumped our heads a couple of times. I worried about Chloe disappearing into one of the holes, so I attached her leash. </p>

<p>After descending the 300 metres to the bottom of the formation, we found ourselves standing in front of a tranquil pool before the dark mouth of the cave. Rapids cut into the canyon and flowed into to the pool and, eventually, into the cave and away. The pool itself was full of rounded boulders, with a couple of opportunistic trees growing on small rock islands. I went nuts with the camera. I took almost 500 shots at different light levels. Too bad I didn’t know how to use my camera properly at the time, but I managed to get some good shots anyway. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/a_world_above.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>A world above.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/fifty_shades_of_green.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Fifty shades of green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/more_green.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>More green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/moss_and_shrubery.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Moss and shrubbery.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/natural_rock_carvings.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Natural rock carvings.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/not_suitable_for_kayaking.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Not suitable for kayaking.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/oasis_effect.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Oasis effect.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/opportunistic_tree.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Opportunistic tree.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/creek_flowing_into_the_cave.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Creek flowing into the cave.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/layers_of_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Layers of forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/another_world.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Another world.</em></p>

<p>James engaged his inner child and decided he was going to leap over the creek onto a rock. He then crawled up the rock to the other side, disappearing into the darkness of the cave. I was left to wonder and wait. He came back, crawled down the rock face, leapt from the rock in the creek and demanded the camera. I resisted at first, then reluctantly surrendered it. I told him that if he wrecks it he pays for it, even though he was the one who paid for it in the first place. </p>

<p>Like he had springs for feet, James was up the rock face and gone into the darkness. He seemed to be gone for an especially long time. After envisioning how I would call 911 from this deep canyon, I started calling for him. Shortly after, he came hopping and jumping back.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/can_you_find_james.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Can you find James?</em></p>

<p>On our way back up the stairs, James got into a conversation with a hiker, talking about a hole James saw on the way down. The hiker told him where the various branches of the cave go. He showed him a hole to go in, and they crawled through, along with the guys’ wife. I decided to stay back, claiming a touch of claustrophobia, or maybe just being burnt out from taking so many photos and not being willing to crawl and creep around tight spaces on slippery rocks with a finicky Chihuahua. </p>

<p>While James was in the cave, I met our neighbours from our camping spot. They informed us about a decommissioned trail to check out. Instead of going straight back to our vehicle, we hung a left and walked passed a sign that told us not to enter. This is not a move I recommend, as there was a risk of running into things like sinkholes and underground passages…so I didn’t tell you to do this! The trail led to a dirt and rock bridge that had collapsed. Unable to proceed further, we had a good look around. We saw the other side of our lake with the logjam where we were trying to access the caves in our kayaks. We had a good laugh: we were actually thought we could paddle through that! We met a couple of batches of people on the trail and had discussions with them about secret hideaways on Vancouver Island, that is, until they found out we were bloggers and the conversations abruptly came to an end. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/we_thought_we_could_kayak_through_this.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>We thought we could paddle through this!</em></p>

<p>After leaving the caves, James and I later went cutting firewood at the brush piles further up the road. I sat on the truck watching him. He seemed to get carried away and cut more logs than we could ever use. We ended up taking some home at the end of our camping trip and leaving a lot behind for the next set of campers.</p>

<p>After supper, I was taking pictures of the sunset. James hopped in the kayak without saying anything and took off across the lake in the semi dark. He went quite far until I couldn’t see him. I was starting to think of calling 911 again when he eventually emerged out of the evening darkness. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/twilight_shot.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Twilight shot.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/sunset.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Sunset.</em></p>

<p><b>May 23, 2016</b></p>

<p>James got up early, around 8, and I stayed comatose in bed until about 10. We were planning to go on the water early to benefit from the calmness. When I came out of the tent, it was cloudy. James said the waves weren’t going to do anything anyway. We hung around until about 12, walking Chloe, having breakfast and drinking lots of coffee.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/overcast.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Overcast.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_with_reflections.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe with reflections.</em></p>

<p>We paddled along the rocky shore of the lake, exploring cave-like indentations, and an outcropping of rock that looked like a giant horse’s hoof. As I was dawdling behind, preoccupied with taking photos, James took off and hid around the next point. I had no trouble figuring out where he went because, paddling on a still fresh water lake, he left a very noticeable trail of bubbles in his wake. I saw a yellow line on the rocks and asked if this lake has a bit of a tide. James said it was from spring runoff, the line marking the level of the water when it was at its highest. The yellow colour comes from the tree pollen. It reminded me of a carpenter’s chalk line. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/put_the_camera_down.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Put the camera down.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/rock_shaped_like_horse_s_hoof.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Rock shaped like a horses’ hoof.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/kalidescope_effect.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Kaleidoscope effect.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/natures_chalk_line.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Nature’s chalk line.</em></p>

<p>Lo and behold, we found <i>another</i> cabin in the BC wilderness! The water was very deep in that area, so we landed several metres away and walked to it. A few of my steps discovered sink holes, so I had to move fast. Inside the cabin, it looked like the last people there left in a fit, as there were dishes and debris scattered everywhere. When I took pictures, I stepped carefully, worrying about falling through the floor. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_cabin.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The cabin.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/someone_left_in_a_fit.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Someone left in a fit.</em></p>

<p>After I got back in the kayak and waited for James on the water, I heard a gun shot that told us there were people around. We paddled toward the campsite where there was an SUV. By the time we got there, the SUV was gone. Their campfire rim was still warm, but their fire was definitely out. Good show, guy, whoever you are! It later turned out he was someone James worked with. James figured it out by noticing a photo of Huson Lake on Facebook some time later and finding out who took it. </p>

<p>We walked down the river to some rapids, trying to figure out how to make the endless stream effect with the camera. We were still so woefully ignorant about the operation of our camera. We walked toward the beach and saw an odd wood construction: a wood frame facing the lake. We read the inscription on it that said, “See TV.” We sat and watched the “natural” TV program of waves on Little Huson Lake while we ate our snack. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/dreamy_green.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Dreamy green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/see_tv.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>See TV.</em></p>

<p>The wind picked up. We realized we had better head back. I had had my fill of photos, so I took the Eskia (Tigger) this time. I noticed how tippy it was, but also how fast it was. It just slips along. The Manitou (Eeyore) seemed like a tractor by comparison, but it is a tractor we need, for Chloe and the camera box. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_with_reflections.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Shadows and reflections.</em></p>

<p>For our last evening at this special little spot, we had a supper of Greek salad and steak with Cajun spice. We started up a conversation about the camera and how to get certain effects. I asked James if he still wanted to go on a night kayak ride. He said his typical “do you want to?” which means he doesn’t really want to. I then had an idea. Since James had an alone kayak the night before, I thought it was my turn to have an alone kayak in the evening light. He promised to take some pictures of me in the hopes of getting some good ones, since I had been complaining that he takes such bad photos of me. Even though he doesn’t have much to work with, he always seems to get me at a bad angle, in a bad light, or when I’m mussed up or frumpy. If I was dressed up to the nines, probably the last thing he’d think of is to reach for the camera! </p>

<p>Going on the water alone like that, it was like a meditation. For some reason, the clutter that moves around in the brain seems to suddenly disappear. I didn’t &quot;think&quot;, and it was easy. I just listened to the birds and looked around, paddling a few strokes and then drifting. When I meditate, it is quite a discipline. Meditating alone on the kayak, though, came quite naturally. I did do some deliberate thinking though. I imagined what this place looked like before people. There would still be birds singing, but the mountains would be completely covered in trees and there would be no cut blocks or logging roads. There on the lake, I was in a timeless zone. When I came back, James actually took some not bad pictures of me, including the one where I’m sticking out my tongue (oh well, you take what you can get). Clearing one’s head can be highly beneficial in unforeseen ways. There’s nothing like a little pre-historic time travel to rid your brain of busy work week. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/alone_kayak.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Alone kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/raspberries_to_you.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Raspberries to you.</em></p>

<p>On our way back, we stopped in at Nimpkish Lake, just off highway 19, at “the sign with no sign” by a cabin at the side of the road. It was one of the special hideaways that the other hikers informed us about. Because it is a very long, Nimpkish Lake makes a good wind tunnel—not great for kayaking. I’ve read in the Backroad Mapbook for Vancouver Island that it has a few rivers flowing into it, with varying levels of difficulty, that would be suitable for kayaking. Because of the perpetual wind, it is an excellent spot for parasailing and wind surfing—and is well used in that respect. It is very scenic too, making it a good spot for a camera buff. Here are some of the pictures I took while we had a short stop there. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/nimpkish_lake.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Nimpkish Lake</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/blue_on_blue.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Blue on blue.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the-upside-down-stump.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The Upside-down stump.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Hardy Bay and Storeys Beach: The Great Escape</title>
	  <link>//storeys-beach</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-10-01T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//storeys-beach</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>Hardy Bay, March 30, 2016</b></p>

<p>It was March…not exactly kayaking season. In many parts of the country people were still coping with snow and sub-zero temperatures. I was feeling an urgency to do some kayaking as soon as possible, which was a good feeling to heed, as there would be an unexpected turn of events that would turn our lives upside down in August. </p>

<p>Unlike in the summer, I couldn&#39;t go kayaking at any time. Because I worked at the school during the week and had an almost full-time job on the weekends, there weren&#39;t many opportunities for me to take off during the school year. James was a little freerer: he worked a half dozen 2 to 4-week mill shutdowns in the spring, summer and fall, with big breaks in between. I saw spring break coming from afar and set the wheels in motion for a kayaking trip for that time. Interestingly, the gods seemed to collaborate with my intentions. The weather on the North Island is usually quite soggy in March; however, those three days that we ended up going kayaking we had an unusual gift of mid-July type weather. </p>

<p>Things were looking good for a spring break trip, except for one hitch. I had to renew my first aid certificate for my lunch supervisor job at the school, and the course was smack dab in the middle of the spring break week we were planning to go. Also, I had to go back to work at my weekend job on Friday. We might have gone farther afield if not for that; but, as it turned out, it was a blessing. Our first kayaking trip had to be local. We considered Storeys Beach by Fort Rupert about 30 minutes away, but weren&#39;t terribly enthusiastic about it. We ended up discovering that it was a gem of a kayaking site, both &quot;exotic&quot; and suitable for almost all ages. Its funny how we tend to think how something exotic and exciting has to be far away and cost a lot of money to get to. So, if you have kids, maybe a Chihuahua or other kind of pooch and not a lot of time for a high kayaking adventure but want one anyway, try out Storeys Beach. </p>

<p>Another complication was lodgings. Our home (James moved out of his rental and into my place in November) was not too far away. There are no campsites at Storeys Beach, so we figured we had to stay at one in Port Hardy. It was a little weird. We would be camping in a municipal area, and there was still a 30 minute drive to our kayaking spot—and it was only a 45 minute drive from home! I guess we just needed to camp; it had been a long winter. We checked out two campsites, but one was closed. We ended up staying at the Quatse River Campground. Again, we were pleasantly surprised and delighted by this element in our close to home adventure. </p>

<p>We arrived at the Quatse River campground on Tuesday and had our pick of camping sites. We walked around to find the very best one, finding it hard to decide. We settled for a site on the banks of the river. We ended up moving two sites down shortly after when a giant bus-camper from Florida showed up and marred our view. Before the sun went down, I took James on a walk on the Quatse loop walking trail. I lived in Port Hardy in 2009-2010, and I used to spend a lot of time on that trail. I was under a lot of stress, so the Quatse Loop Trail, with its tall and ancient Emily Carrish trees and cut-off-from-the-world feeling, provided me with a sanctuary of peace. I was delighted to share it with someone, especially with James who also tends to like that kind of thing. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/quatze_loop_trail.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze Loop Trail.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/a_quatze_loop_monolith.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze Loop Monolith.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/understory.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Understory.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/ferns.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Ferns.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/mother_tree.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Mother tree.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/old_souls.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Old souls.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/old_mans_hairs.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Old man&#39;s hairs.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/wild_flowers.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Wildflowers.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/bank_of_the_quatze_river.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Bank of the Quatze River.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/back_to_camp.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Back to camp.</em>  </p>

<p>During the day on Wednesday, I did my duty by going to my first aid course at North Island College. After grabbing a quick bite to eat at Mo&#39;s, I met James and Chloe at the prearranged kayak launch point at the end of the sea walk on Hardy Bay. There is a little sign there indicating a kayak launch. I&#39;ve walked by that sign dozens of times and never saw it before: it is interesting how what we see is so selective. I suppose our brains would be overwhelmed if we processed everything we saw. I think this applies to nature: it is such a complex system, I think we have barely begun to know all that is there. The First Nations people from thousands of years ago might have been a lot more aware, knowledgeable and sophisticated than we industrially-oriented &quot;modern&quot; people could begin to fathom. Methinks Mother Nature has been posting a lot of signs in our reality lately, and we have been missing all but a scant few of them. James already had both kayaks on shore and was ready to go. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/daddy_cares.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Daddy cares.</em></p>

<p>Then we wondered where to go.</p>

<p>We thought about going north but, with the wind, the water was sure to be rough where it was open to the Queen Charlotte Strait. We decided to head south toward the Quatze River estuary—the &quot;industrial&quot; area, which, surprisingly, turned out to be a lot of fun. It was a novel switch from our usual remote adventures with no or hardly any people around. We took photos of a big barge loaded with heavy construction equipment, as well as a float plane coming in for a landing overhead. We paddled around the estuary—parts of which are solid ground at other times of the day—easily seeing the sand and rocks under the water and sometimes almost running aground. At low tide, this area becomes a sandbar and a graveyard for dark, spooky, dead driftwood tree creatures. A few of those creatures were still sticking out of the water. We came close to a couple of them to pay our respects. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/hey_baby_paddling_my_way.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Hey baby? Paddling my way?</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/barge_with_crane.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Barge with crane.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/float_plane_overhead.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Float plane overhead.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/mommy_and_chloe.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Mommy and Chloe.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/paying_respects.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Paying respects.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/steely_eyed_captain.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Steely-eyed captain.</em></p>

<p>We found a spot for a picnic on the east shore. As we ate, we were the main attraction for an audience of seals peeking out of the water. On our way back to the launch point, we came across a couple of teenagers pretending to try to push each other off of a very high pier and looking, perilously, like they might succeed. I told them to &quot;be careful&quot; but was totally ignored as they seemed to be having a whale of a time. Instead, I paddled slowly and kept watching them until they looked like they were out of danger.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/quatze_river_estuary.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze River estuary.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/setting_summer_sun.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Setting summer sun.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/creek_bed.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Creek bed.</em> </p>

<p>Coming back into Hardy Bay, we saw a couple of lighthouses, one by the fish plant and close to shore, and one in the middle of the bay. I looked longingly at the lighthouse in the centre of the bay. Even though I hadn&#39;t said a thing about it, James told me that going to the lighthouse wasn&#39;t going to happen this time because it was too windy, the water was too rough and it was too late in the day. Remembering our paddle to the lighthouse on Neroutsos Inlet, I wasn&#39;t going to argue. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/lighthouse_by_the_fish_plant.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Lighthouse by the fish plant.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sunset_landing.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sunset Landing.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sunset_on_hardy_bay.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sunset on Hardy bay.</em></p>

<p>Our eventful day was not over. After kayaking, we went to visit James&#39; son, Dakota, and daughter-in-law, Cassandra, and our new grand-daughter, Gabby, born in December. Back at the campground, we sat around the campfire and marvelled how bright the stars were in the March night sky. We talked about them and wondered what we were looking at. Then, James realized, that there must be an app for that! Sure enough, there was! We discovered the star that puzzled us the most was actually Jupiter. It was then that I realized—for the first time in my life—that the brightest stars that appear first in the night sky are planets. What was actually Jupiter, I used to think was the International Space Station. Before the internet, it seems like we were living in the dark ages!</p>

<p>Since we were camping in March and the nights were long, we ended up using a lot of firewood. It was chilly one too, so an extra comforter was must. After all, we were only a few days out of winter.  </p>

<p><b>Storeys Beach, March 31, 2016</b></p>

<p>We planned our trip around the weather report and it fulfilled itself exactly as predicted: three sunny days in a row with the temperatures in the mid teens! Sometimes the weather guys <i>do</i> get it right! On Friday, when we packed up to leave, the clouds came right back!</p>

<p>Storeys Beach is the shoreline of Beaver Harbour, located between Port Hardy and Fort Rupert on the east side of Vancouver Island. The shallow bay has four islands in the middle of it: Shell Island, Cattle Island, Deer Island and Eagle Island. This area is the ancestral home of Kwakiutl band of the Kwakwaka&#39;wakw First Nation, and was once a happening place, in pre-European terms: plank houses adorned with carvings and family crests housed extended families engaged in seasonal routines of hunting and gathering, as well as periodic dance rituals, dramas and potlatches. With the arrival of Europeans, a trading post was established on the Nahwitti River, north of town. When coal was discovered in 1836, the Hudson&#39;s Bay Company developed a fortified trading post at Beaver Harbour. The hamlet of Fort Rupert got its name from the Hudson&#39;s Bay Company governor, Prince Rupert, Duke of Bavaria. In 1887, a former HBC employee who married a First Nations woman, Mary Ebbets, and had numerous children (political leverage), ended up reclaiming part of the land rights of Fort Rupert back to Kwakuitl residents. Although Storeys Beach seemed quite serene and empty at first; it definitely has the feel of a place that has had a lot going on in the past…for thousands and thousands of years!  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/stories_beach.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Storey&#39;s beach.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/unloading_the_kayaks.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Unloading the kayaks.</em></p>

<p>The night before, we checked the weather and the tide guides to make sure we were not launching during low tide…to avoid a long walk with heavy kayaks on the especially wide beach. High tide was a 6:30 am. We launched around 11:30, right in between high and low tide. We didn&#39;t have to drag the kayaks too far. I launched in Eeyore (the slow steady kayak) and James was in Tigger (the fast bouncy kayak). I had to paddle carefully, because the water was mere centimetres from the bottom of my boat. Just when I thought I was a good way out and could paddle normally, I got stuck on a sand bar! I said to James &quot;I&#39;m stuck!&quot; perhaps sounding as if I expected him to come rescue me. He does tend to rescue me a lot, and I might be getting a little too used to it. Instead of dealing with a problem by &quot;taking the bull by the horns&quot; right away—as has been my way most of my life — I now tend to hesitate to see if someone else will take care of it for me. He snarked, &quot;I guess you are going to have to get out and walk!&quot; I replied, &quot;I know that!&quot; I got out and walked, pulling the kayak with Chloe in it. James snapped a few shots of me walking on water.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/launching.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Launching.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/walking_on_water.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Walking on water.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/still_walking.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Still walking.</em> </p>

<p>Shell Island is a hang out place for all kinds of birds, mostly seagulls, though we did see some rather unfamiliar birds, including Harlequin ducks. When we approached, our arrival caused a kafuffle. Some birds took to flight, and others swam hurriedly away from us. Paddling in between Shell Island and Cattle Island, we saw two immature sea eagles perched on rocks, looking dopey and innert. At first, we thought they were Golden eagles, which is a common mistake. Young eagles look like Golden eagles until they mature and develop the dark brown body feathers and white head feathers. James came in close to snap a photo. The bird didn&#39;t move, seeming to enjoy the notoriety—or he was just too young to know any better. Seals were playing peek-a-boo with us. We drifted through the murky whitish (because of the shells) greenish water between Shell and Cattle Island, surrounded by tiny jumping fish, when we saw what looked like a totem pole and little fountains of water squirting out of the shore. With all the eagles and squirting somethings, we decided a landing at Shell Island was warranted. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/crab_trap_buoy.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Crab trap buoy.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/birdsanctuary.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Bird sanctuary.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/casuing_a_kaffuffle.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Causing a kafuffle.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/birds_take_flight.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Birds take flight.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/harlequin_ducks.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Harlequin ducks.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sign_on_shell_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sign on Shell Island.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/young_eagle.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Young eagle.</em></p>

<p>Shell Island is a photographer&#39;s dream, with black lava boulders contrasting with the white broken shell sand. Add to that the abundance of wildlife. James and I are in the process of shopping for a new camera, bemoaning that we did not yet have it so we could use a telephoto lens on the birds. What also added to the photographic delight was the fact that James was dressed in a black T-shirt and black sun glasses which, with his pale complexion, made him match the island! I took a million pictures. We had a picnic on the white rocky beach, stripped a little, and then laid in the sun like it was the middle of the summer (remember, it was March!). We checked out what we thought was a totem pole, but actually was a sign saying, &quot;Kamsaxtte.&quot; Although I am totally ignorant of what the sign means and the significance of the island to First Nations cultures, it sounds a lot like &quot;namaste&quot; and I wouldn&#39;t doubt it has a similar meaning. I would also venture a guess that Shell Island is a spiritual sanctuary. I don&#39;t need to find this out, as the vibes are everywhere!  If anyone who is reading this knows anything more about the history and significance of the sign and Shell Island, I would appreciate it if you enter your comments at the conversation section at the foot of this post. The squirting somethings we guessed to be barnacles just under the surface of the rocks and sand. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/looks_like_snow.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Looks like snow.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/where_are_we.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Where <i>are</i> we?</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/white_shell_sand.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>White shell sand.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/boulders.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Boulders made from undersea lava deposits.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/island_of_contrasts.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Island of contrast.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/tranquil_pool.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Tranquil pool.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/james_matching_the_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>James matching the island.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/chloe_meet_eagle_eagle_meet_chloe.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Chloe meet Eagle, Eagle meet Chloe.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/chloe_photo_bombing_my_artistic_driftwood_composition.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Chloe photo bombing my artistic driftwood composition.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sea_shell_composition.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sea shell composition.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/two_sun_bathing_beauties.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Two sun bathing beauties.</em></p>

<p>After launching from Shell Island, we went in the direction of Cattle Island, where we would get ourselves into a bit of a pickle, to put it mildly. Ever since we arrived, we had been listening to intermittent flurries of sea lions barking. A fishing skiff seemed to be at the epicentre of it. Sea lions were barking at fish workers who were tossing them fish scraps. 
Fishing skiff.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/seals_playing_peek-a-boo.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Seals playing peek-a-boo.</em></p>

<p>In another area, we saw something weird. It looked like fins and tails swimming in a circle. I moved closer. I realized that if I continued along that trajectory, I&#39;d glide right into the middle of the moving circle, which, in hindsight, would have been disastrous to say the least! James told me to take a wide berth. I went around, but had evidently already agitated the creatures in their ritual, as there was a sudden onslaught of hostile barking. I beat it away from the group, taking a quick look back at the circle. Just as I was turning my head to look, I saw the gigantic head of an enormous light grey seal bull with large black spots and a heavy set of jowls rise out of the water and give me a nasty penetrating look. No need for words! Mind reading between animals and humans definitely exists! When I was halfway around—heading toward Cattle Island the long way—the harem&#39;s barking intensified. We booted it. Chloe was getting scared and kept trying to crawl into my cockpit. Somehow, I managed to hold her back and paddle incredibly fast at the same time! Embedded in the cacophony of barking, we heard what sounded like the roar of a giant monster opening its jaws. When we thought we were far enough away, we relaxed and put down our paddles. As soon as we did that, though, the party of sea lions came rushing after us! They chased us for a couple hundred metres, then suddenly stopped. I think it was more of a threat than anything, as they could have easily caught up to us and done some serious damage. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FUqEjtZ1nIs" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>We did some googling and believe we were dealing with Stellar sea lions. The females can weight as much as 350 kilograms (770 pounds) and measure up to 2 metres (7 feet). The males can weight up to 1120 kilograms (2500 pounds) measure over 3 metres (11 feet). We were being chased by several thousand kilograms of angry sea lions!</p>

<p>Deer Island is owned by the Kwakiutl First Nations (so is Shell Island, but people are allowed to go there for day trips), and is out of bounds. You have formally request permission to go there. Paddling by, we saw a bunch of raw wood constructions and a tarp over a dome shaped frame: tables and possibly a sweat lodge. Paddling around to the north, we ran into an abundance of kelp on the water. I started picking them and dropping them into my cockpit. I had images in my mind of making kelp chips in the same way I make kale chips. As we rounded the island, the kelp appeared in greater and greater abundance. I ended up filling up my cockpit and getting my shorts thoroughly soaked! James was getting impatient with me. He kept ordering me to stop, but I couldn&#39;t help sneaking a few more here and there. Just think, generations of people have probably been collecting seaweed over millennia in this very spot!</p>

<p>As we rounded Deer Island, facing the open water, the ride got rocky. I looked to the east and could see the mainland in the distance, with a whole lot of blue water in between! After our trip down the wilder side of the islands, we came around Eagle Island and landed for another picnic and some sun-bathing. As we relaxed on the pebbly beach, we marvelled at how we had hard time telling it wasn&#39;t July. We were even sun burnt in places. Our inner seasonal time clock was experiencing a lot of confusion. The trouble with feeling like it was the middle of summer is that it gave us the uneasy feeling that fall was just around the corner! It&#39;s was a unsettling thought, especially when we only said goodbye to winter a few days ago. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/eagle_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Eagle Island.</em> </p>

<p>Throughout the day, we kept hearing a repetitive blast that sounded like a cannon. On Eagle Island, the sound seemed a lot closer. We looked and looked, trying to figure where it came from. We then realized that there was a flight path overhead, and that the airport was not too far away from us on shore of Vancouver Island. James figured out the blast was from canons trying to scare birds away from the landing strips. </p>

<p>The next stop on our trip was a return to Shell Island, but there was a large body of choppy water in between. James gave me the lighter kayak because he felt sorry for me, and he took the Manitou. We determined we had to do a serious warp drive paddle across, or the trip would take us all day. I was really going. James later confessed he was having a hard time keeping up with me. </p>

<p>Back at Shell Island, we turned left and headed for shore. We couldn&#39;t see our truck, and didn&#39;t know exactly where to aim. If we would have gone in at the wrong angle, we could have ended up a kilometre or two away from our launch point and we didn&#39;t have enough energy left in our bodies to correct it. We finally recognised a microwave tower that we saw when we left, and oriented ourselves with that. We saw the sea lion&#39;s love-in going on in another part of the bay and gave them a wide berth. The water was, more or less, at the same level it was when we left—we had been paddling and exploring the bay for roughly six hours. This time, though, we didn&#39;t have to walk on water. We determined that we ended up doing a serious 12-kilometre paddle. It was nice to experience a little bit of summer, even if it wasn&#39;t actually summer.  </p>

<p>When we were packing up the truck, I had thrown my seaweed into a clean garbage bag. When we got back to our campsite, I spent the evening rinsing the seaweed in fresh water from the campground tap to remove the slime, then hanging it on a line between two trees to drain and dry a bit. The next day, when we got home, I rigged a line on my balcony so the seaweed could dry further. Before it was completely dry, I made a batch of kelp chips in the same fashion as I make kale chips. Taking about half of my spoils, I cut them up into small squares, drizzled them with olive oil, and salted them just a little—just enough to bring out the flavour. Kelp already has lots of salt to start with. I put them in the oven at a low heat, about 300° Fahrenheit, (about 150° Celsius) until they became thin and crispy but still green. The first few bites were hard to get used to, because it is a slightly different taste from kale chips, but it didn&#39;t take long for me to start liking them. James missed out on the culinary experience because he was working a shut down out of town. With my busy schedule, I ended up neglecting the other half of the kelp on the line. They started to get too dry, so I took them off the line and put them in a pan under a cloth, ready to make kale chips for the next time I had a chance. By the time I got around to making them, they were way too dry and didn&#39;t crisp up in the oven properly. If you make kelp chips, cook them when they are still damp. Determined not let this wonderful nature&#39;s bounty go to waste, I threw it on my garden for fertilizer and slug repellent. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/seaweed_drying.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Seaweed drying.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Starfish Are Having A Party</title>
	  <link>//Starfish-Party</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-07-11T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Starfish-Party</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>October 4, 2015</b></p>

<p>We were getting some beautiful fall weather. The sun was shining, the water was calm, and the environs were accented by fall colours. The urge to go on the water was irresistible, not just for James and me, but for my neighbour across the street, retired school principal and very keen kayaker, Polly Steele. Polly was loading up her kayak in the warm October sun the same time we were. Just like geese, who start their migrations in response to certain cues in the environment, as soon as the sun comes out on a fall day, kayakers head to the water. Polly spends a lot more time on the water than we do. Very often, if you look onto the water on a calm morning and see the tiny shadow of a kayaker, it is probably Polly. It is amazing that there are not more kayakers on the inlet in the mornings. If you are a seriously addicted kayaker, Port Alice is the perfect place to live or own a vacation property, not just because the inlet is sheltered from the waves and winds of the open ocean, but because the water is easily accessible from civilization. If you get the urge to kayak, you can have your butt on the water in no time! You don’t have to load up your vehicle with a bunch of camping gear and drive for hours and hours to find a beautiful quiet place to kayak.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/fall_colours.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Fall colours.</em></p>

<p>We went down to the Marina; Polly arrived shortly after. While James was unloading the kayaks, Polly and I talked about the election. It is funny to think back to that conversation, and how neither one of us had a clue about the big surprise that was due on election night.  </p>

<p>Because she had a fancy dansy kayak rack, Polly unloaded her kayak lickety split and was off on the water and gone while we were still unstrapping ours! I took “Tigger,” the fast bouncy kayak, and James took “Eeyore,” the slow steady kayak. We went around the breakwater, then headed for the Frigon Island group. It was easy going. There was no wind; the water’s surface was like a mirror. Going in between the two islands, a sea lion barked at us. We looked around. We saw him just as he surfaced and then dove into the water. He was huge, at least a couple of metres long! We could tell, by the menacing sound of his barking, that he didn’t like having us around. In spite of his territorial theatrics, he didn’t bother us after that. He was just letting us know how big he was, and that he was keeping an eye on us. </p>

<p>The water was especially clear, as the mill had been down for a while. Although pulp mills have to conform to very strict environmental controls these days, they still have an effect on the water. It is a stark contrast to what the mill was like in the 1980s. People tell me that the air back that was thick with smog and that the water was virtually devoid of aquatic life, with all kinds of strange coloured substances floating in the water. People who protested the mill back then coined the name “Neurosis Inlet” as a way of voicing their objections. Oddly, today, the locals seem to still call it “Neurosis Inlet”, not realizing or not caring for the subtle difference in pronunciation between “Neurosis” and “Neroutsos.”</p>

<p>We noticed an abundance of jelly fish. They came beside our boats, one after another, doing their weird little swim. Either there were a lot of jelly fish, or they were purposefully coming by to check us out. We passed a reef by the islands and saw a multitude of starfish having a starfish party! As we were paddling around the starfish, Polly came by. She and James chatted about how clear the water was, and about the recent abundance of sea lions and whales. I was being obsessive, trying to get the absolute best shots of starfish. I was having a hard time getting a good compositional arrangement to photograph because, as soon as I had a good one, the kayak moved and altered it! I became flustered, trying to paddle to the perfect spot for a photo and then snapping it fast enough, worrying that I might end up dropping the phone in the water. After a while, I snapped photos nearly indiscriminately, hoping that I incidentally got in a few good shots. Eventually, James ordered me to curb my frenzied photography. I complied, simply because I was getting frustrated. Polly took off and went to the south part of the island. James and I went across the inlet to check out a river. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/jellyfish.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Jellyfish.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/a_starfish_party.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>A starfish party!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/james_and_polly.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>James and Polly having a neighbourly chat.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/gimme_that_camera.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Gimme that camera!</em></p>

<p>After eons of coughing out rocks, boulders and wood into the inlet, the small sparkling river created a huge underwater mountain. It made for a wide stretch of shallow water for us to walk in up to our ankles, as well as a habitat for seaweed, sea onion and sea asparagus. With massive pieces of driftwood lying around, the sand bar looked like a graveyard for monster trees from Lord of the Rings. We stopped and took a bunch of pictures on a big snag. Chloe posed for pictures, looking like a hero dog in an animal adventure series. I took a bunch of photos of James hopping on the giant piece of driftwood—which made my knee cringe! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/the_underwater_mountain_top.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>The underwater mountain “top.”</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_the_super.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe the super kayaking dog.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/james_on_the_giant.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>James on the giant piece of driftwood.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/log_with_seaweed.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Log with seaweed.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/sea_onion.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Sea onion.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/a_dog&#x27;s_boat.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>A dog’s boat is her castle.</em> </p>

<p>Back at the kayaks, we walked in shallow water for quite a distance before hopping in. We were contemplating a picnic, but decided on having one on the Frigon Islands instead, as there weren’t any dry comfortable places to sit. James tried to paddle up the river, but, with the tide going out, he wasn’t able to get very far. On the way to the islands, I commented that the water’s surface seemed convex: that shortly after we left shore we seemed to sink down a miniscule amount and go lower as we got closer to the centre of the inlet. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/south_view_from.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>South view from the Frigon Islands.</em></p>

<p>Sitting on our blanket and eating on the sand bridge between the Frigon Islands, a crow protested that he wasn’t invited to our picnic. We threw crackers and grapes at him. Sometimes he ate them right away, other times he carried something off to a hiding spot. We had to throw our givings a good distance. If we didn’t throw them far enough, he wouldn’t come close to get them. 
Casting off for home, we drifted by an Inuksuk on the south island. In the last couple of years, there has been an mysterious invasion of inuksuk’s in Port Alice. They appeared in healthy numbers by the kayak launch, on the islands and on the shores of Neroutsos Inlet. Some would crumble back to the elements, then more would appear. They were the talk of the town for quite a while, as people tried to figure out who their creator was. One day, I discussed this mystery with one of Port Alice’s resident professional photographers, Darrell McIntosh, and he confessed it was he who made them. Since he often makes calendars of his nature photography to sell, I suggested he make one with his inuksuks. He hummed and hawed about it at first, but, eventually, he did it! That was already a couple of years back. </p>

<p>Chloe stared at the inuksuk like it was a real person or animal. She even barked at it! There’s something about Chloe and sculptures! When we were in a car rental agency this last Christmas 2016, she became very distressed by the presence of a carved wooden Santa Claus they had in the front lobby. Talk about the power of art! Even animals can have a sense of it! 
James took a picture of Chloe looking at the Inuksuk. I told him to take a picture of the Inuksuk too, but—tired of all the picture-taking—he protested. When he paddled around the island, he got a change of heart. When I finally caught up to him, he confessed that he ended up taking the picture anyway. I have to thank the gods for that intervention! This story would have been sorely incomplete without it, and James later had to agree. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_staring_at.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe staring at the inuksuk.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/the_inuksuk.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>The inuksuk.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_afraid_of_santa.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe afraid of Santa.</em></p>

<p>And this, folks, is the end of the story for our 2015 kayaking season. By the time I finished writing this post (January 2017), there have been a few changes in Port Alice thanks, I believe, to our town’s various web promotions, including portalicelife.ca, vancouverislandhiddengem.com, and chloethekayakingchihuahua.com. Though this is hardly quantitative, many of the locals have been commenting that there has been more tourist activity in Port Alice. One more concrete sign of this is that the local grocery store, F.P. Foods (now called Port Alice Family Foods) opened its doors from 8 to 8 in the summer! The latest I remember them staying open is 7 pm—and that was when the mill was open! </p>

<p>I think kayaking is a very good way to spend our time here on Earth, and even a good way to enliven our economy to a degree. It’s great physical activity, keeping us healthy and fit—even for us oldies with bad knees! The activity itself doesn’t require oil or gasoline, and doesn’t churn up the water or introduce hazards that affect animal life the way motor boats do. We need some of that oil and gas to make kayaks, but they can last a long time. One kayak can last a lifetime, and maybe even a couple more after that—unlike most cars! Kayaking provides us with more opportunities to interact with our animal and fish friends, promoting more awareness of and empathy for our ecosystem. It’s hard to take care of nature’s creatures if we are not even aware that they are there, and that they have intelligence, personalities, and that they even like to be funny sometimes.</p>

<p>Kayaking also helps us to explore those beautiful idyllic settings that are just around the corner, that we may have lived near all our lives and not really seen or appreciated. Who says you have to spend a bunch of money to fly for hours in a plane to a place considered to be exotic? We have oodles of exotic, peaceful and beautiful bodies of water to visit right here in Canada, some of which rarely see people. Canada has over 30,000 lakes larger than three square kilometres—that’s a lot of places to kayak! Whether they are in the west, the east, the far north or in a municipal area, there is something magical about all of them! Mother Nature is an artist who doesn’t skimp on quality.</p>

<p>Our societies’ focus on buying and selling things has gotten out of hand, and we need to change course. Instead of being addicted to buying stuff that, half the time, we don’t need and that just ends up in the land fill, I think we would be better off spending our money on generating “positive experiences.” We can even base a vibrant economy on such “ephemeral” things. It doesn’t have to be primarily based on the exchange of solid, material objects. </p>

<p>I have a pact with James and my son. We exchange gifts at Christmas, a little reluctantly, but for every other occasion, we celebrate with a nice dinner or a night out. We have to eat or be entertained anyway. We don’t end up with a bunch of junk that we have no place to put. There is a limit to how many gadgets a person can actually use. In fact, in many material-object-based industries, like the fashion industry, products have to be regularly destroyed to keep up demand. </p>

<p>The best thing about kayaking, is that it can be a spiritual experience. We can miss so much of what is going on in “reality,” as the TV slowly and insidiously reconstructs our perspective. Kayaking teaches us about various other “worlds” out there, from the worlds of plants and animals… to the long lost cultures of First Nations people (who have maintained this planet for millennia without bringing it to the brink of destruction)…to that space in the silence of nature that helps us be more creative—and that just might provide us with the solutions to all our problems.  </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
