<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>chloethekayakingchihuahua.com</title>
   
   <link>http://chloethekayakingchihuahua.com</link>
   <description>One small dog discovering the beauty of Vancouver Island.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Debra Lynn</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Drake Island and Quatsino: Ghosts of the Sound</title>
	  <link>//drake-island-quatsino</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2020-05-12T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//drake-island-quatsino</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><i>I’d like to give a special thanks to three people for helping me with this post: Gwen Hansen of the Quatsino Museum and Archives for providing historical information on Ed Frigon; Jane Hutton of the Port Hardy Museum and Archives for allowing me to photograph images of Ed Frigon and his hotel; and, my friend and friendly neighbour, Evelyn Hartford, for providing me with a  photograph of Frigon’s hotel, articles and for being a general all round valuable resource for historical information on the North Island.</i></p>

<p><b>July 19, 2016</b></p>

<p>We wanted to go out on Neroutsos Inlet to Drake Island where the notorious Ed Frigon had his hotel and trading post between 1895 and 1917. We had been talking about the idea for a while. It took some convincing to get James on side for it: he thought our kayaks wouldn’t be big enough to carry all the stuff we needed. We finally concluded it shouldn’t be that hard, since many have paddled all the way around the Island with just their kayaks for carrying supplies…for a good stretch anyway. As it turned out, after paring down a few items, there was plenty of room for what we needed. Sea kayaks are big kayaks.  </p>

<p>Ed Frigon is one of Port Alice’s favourite historical “characters.” The very picturesque islands on Neroutsos Inlet are named after him. Frigon was an entrepreneur, an adventurer and a man with a mind of his own. He also had several wives, though not all at the same time. </p>

<p>Ed or “Ned” Frigon was born in Maurice, Quebec. At the age of 21 he left his family to find riches in the California Gold Rush of 1848-55. He took a boat to Panama, then crossed the isthmus by foot through mud, swamps, tropical heat by day and swarms of mosquitos by night. Making it to the Pacific coast in a little over a week, he took passage on a schooner to San Francisco. Although he managed to find gold, it was never enough to overcome the overinflated living costs in the area. He left the mines in disgust. He worked for a time in the San Francisco Bay area; then, not happy with the warm climate, he headed further up the coast. He eventually landed in Victoria, BC. In 1857, after accumulating a tidy savings, he headed to Hope Island on the north end of Vancouver Island to be a fur-trader.</p>

<p>Frigon was one of the first few white men to live among the local Indigenous population. He appeared to get along well with them; but, from time to time, a few “cultural disparities” would emerge. </p>

<p>The material goods in his store could incite envy in people who knew nothing but living off the land. A small group of unscrupulous men once plotted to kill him and divide his goods among themselves. Forewarned by his Indigenous wife at the time, the night of the planned attack he locked all the doors and windows and slept with several loaded weapons by his bed. It turned out that the locked door was enough to thwart the plan. </p>

<p>The next day Frigon opened his store and behaved as if nothing had happened, but had a message sent to the authorities in Victoria. A few weeks later a gunboat appeared, heading in the direction of Hope Island. Upon landing, the commander of the vessel warned the First Nations community that they would be punished should anything ever happen to Ed Frigon. After seeing many Indigenous communities decimated by the colonists, they considered this a serious threat. Thereafter, Frigon was accompanied by an entourage of Indigenous bodyguards wherever he went, to the point it became a serious encumbrance to him. </p>

<p>Of Ed Frigon’s many wives, most of them were Indigenous. He outlived some, was deserted by others and had to send at least one back to her people. Although Frigon was believed to be monogamous, he had a certain charm with women. One of his wives, who was the jealous type, tried to stab him with a butcher knife while he was in his bed. As she raised the knife to deliver the fatal blow, Frigon grabbed her wrist and said, “Not tonight Marie!” He removed the knife from her hand and threw her out of the house. It was with some regret, as he thought she was a very good housekeeper and “une dame belle.” </p>

<p>Frigon carried on trading on Hope Island until 1889, then built a second trading post at Korprino Harbour. In 1895 he moved to Quiet Cove, (Pamphlet Cove) on Limestone Island (now Drake Island) where he built a store, hospital, steamship stop and hotel with a saloon that had the ‘longest bar north of San Francisco.’ When rumours of prohibition were about, Frigon sold his hotel to the mill in 1917. He retreated to a large property north of Port Alice to live with his last common law wife, Lucy Moon. Lucy Moon had the title of “The Last of the Long Heads”: she was the last member of a group of Indigenous people who bound the heads of their children to elongate them. The hotel was floated down to Port Alice where it became a boarding house for mill workers, called “Jones’ Hotel.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20and%20general%20store.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s hotel and general store</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Young%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Young Ed Frigon</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Middle-aged%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Middle-aged Ed Frigon</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Elderly%20Ed%20Frigon.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Elderly Ed Frigon</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20getting%20floated%20to%20the%20mill.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s hotel getting floated to the mill</em></p>

<p>To get to Drake Island we up launching from Atkin’s Cove, a place we had been to before. To get there you take Neroutsos Main north of Port Alice on the east side of Neroutsos Inlet. Keep going on Neroutsos Main for 12 kilometres. Make sure to keep a careful eye on your odometer—it might be the only way you’ll be able to find the proper turn. About halfway there you will see a fork in the road with a branch that goes up the mountain. Don’t take it. That’s Quarry Main. It won’t take you to Atkin’s Cove, but it will take you up the mountain for an incredible view! Go up too far and you will definitely be needing a four-wheel drive and a strong stomach for driving on high mountain roads! Once you pass a side road on Nertoutsos Main with a wire across it, go a few metres further and turn left along a little “goat trail” that’s just wide enough for a vehicle to pass. Sometimes it is overgrown with shrubs, but sometimes it’s brushed. Drive for about a half a kilometre to a pull-out where you can park. In total, you shouldn’t go over 13 km from Port Alice. Any more than that and you’re lost! Let me remind you that if you go out into the bush, make sure to inform someone where you’re going and when you plan to be back so you don’t have to wait for days or even weeks before someone realizes you are missing. </p>

<p>If you look hard enough, on the south west side of the pull-out, you will see an opening in the shrubs which should be marked with florescent ribbon. That is the trail head. If you walk into the woods to the west, you will start to see water. If you read about our first adventure to Atkin’s Cove from years back, you will see how we got terribly lost! Check out my post, “Atkin’s Cove: Lost and Lost Again!” and have a laugh!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Entrance%20to%20the%20trail%20to%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Entrance to the trail to Atkin’s Cove</em></p>

<p>James and I were originally going to launch at Kokwina Cove (which is a little portage to the east of the goat trail) that is at the edge of the Quatsino Narrows with all its nasty currents. We were going to time the tides to go out just before slack tide. I was apprehensive about the idea but didn’t say anything. Then, out of the blue, James voiced misgivings. I told him that if he’s uncertain, then I’m scared you-know-what-less! We talked about it some more, then concluded there were too many unknowns. We decided to take Atkin’s Cove to Drake Island instead. I said I would be willing to try Kokwina some day, but not with Chloe.</p>

<p>You could also get to Drake Island by launching from Port Alice, but it would be a minimum two-day trip. If you are a strong paddler, you may be able to make it to Drake Island in one day. If not, you could spend the night at Atkin’s Cove. Make sure to time the tides, so they are carrying you in the direction you want to go. Leave early in the morning before daytime heating makes the water on Neroutsos Inlet too choppy. </p>

<p>We dragged our supplies and kayaks down the hill to our launch point. Chloe was excited about getting into a kayak. As soon as I put a couple of blankets in her cockpit, she hopped in and wouldn’t leave!</p>

<p>The camera box only fits comfortably in the tandem Manitou; but, because I was due for surgery and James is so noble, he felt he had to paddle the heavier loaded down kayak. It ended up that I only had James’ phone—that doesn’t have a neck strap—for taking photos. I didn’t have much trouble paddling the larger kayak, but he insisted. It would turn out to be something he would woefully regret!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20hopped%20in%20the%20kayak%20and%20wouldn&#x27;t%20leave.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe hopped in the kayak and wouldn’t leave!</em></p>

<p>After leaving the tranquil calm waters of the cove, we met the rougher waters of Neroutsos Inlet—which were especially rough around the point! We made it around somehow, riding waves that made our kayaks feel like bucking broncos! </p>

<p>As soon as we came around the point to calmer waters, we met a community of Harbour seals—one with a baby—playing peek-a-boo with us. </p>

<p>When we crossed the inlet to the east side of Drake Island, our stomachs started complaining. It was 3 o’clock and we had only had breakfast. We landed briefly for a snack. Although we were on Drake Island, we still had a considerable paddle to get to Pamphlet Cove. As we paddled around the large island, we were getting impatient. We kept saying, “are we there yet?” It took a while, but we finally got there!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Kayaks%20landed%20at%20east%20side%20of%20Drake%20Island.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kayaks landed on the east side of Drake Island</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20inspecting%20the%20cuddy.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe inspecting the cuddy</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/paddling%20in%20the%20kelp.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Paddling in the kelp</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Kayaking%20Chloe%20with%20kelp.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kayaking Chloe with kelp</em></p>

<p>Coming up on the entrance of Pamphlet Cove, we entered a serene, windless, warmer, almost stagnant zone of the Sound. The water was calm, with bits of flotsam and foam floating on top. At the entrance of the cove were a couple of rock protrusions with bonsai-like trees on top. It made me think of a water-bound Japanese garden. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Me%20with%20bonsai-like%20trees.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Me with bonsai-like tree</em></p>

<p>We came across a sign surrounded by foxgloves. It informed us that the foxgloves marked the location of Ed Frigon’s hotel! That was the only sign of the previous human habitation, as the area had been almost completely reclaimed by the forest. </p>

<p>Before landing, we decided to explore the cove in our kayaks. The tide was ebbing out, but there was still enough water left for us to go in quite far. We saw lots of little fish. The cove is apparently a haven from the big fish of the sound. All the racing and roaring of the ocean was blocked out. Our voices and splashes echoed against the trees. James was well ahead of me, looking around and lost in wonderment. Unfortunately, that wonderment would be short-lived…</p>

<p>As I passed the shallow channel between the two sections of the hourglass shaped cove, I found a beautiful arrangement of three large starfish sitting together on some large rocks just below the surface of the rushing water. I snapped pictures like crazy! I was obsessed! I don’t know what it is with me a starfish, but they make me go bonkers! I envisioned making some serious money from the shot! </p>

<p>The current was strong and made it hard to stay still long enough to snap the photos. I kept putting James’ cell phone on my lap as I paddled frenetically. I took tons of pictures but kept wanting that one extra picture! When I started to put the camera away after that last extra, <i>extra</i> shot, as I transferred it from one hand to another, it did a sudden flip—as if someone or something had tried to reach out and grab it—then, plop!, into the water it went! </p>

<p>I screamed! I almost went in headfirst trying to reach for it. I tried to stay at the spot where it fell, so maybe we could somehow find it. I kept calling for James, but he wasn’t coming. I called again a couple of times. He finally showed up.</p>

<p>“What’s up?” he asked. 
I told him I dropped his phone in the water. 
He said, “you’re joking, right?” 
I shook my head in the negative. 
Again, he said, “You are joking?” 
I shook my head again. </p>

<p>We repeated that little interchange a couple of times more until he started to make the paradigm shift and acquire a very startled look. </p>

<p>I told him I was over the spot where it fell. In a frenzy, he got out of his boat in the shallow water, rolled up his shorts up to his hips and walked onto the rocks, frenetically searching and reaching in the water for his phone. </p>

<p>Feeling what we feel, Chloe, in the Manitou, was whining desperately. It took some time, but James finally found the camera. It was standing upright in a space between two rocks—which was why it was so hard to find.</p>

<p>With the phone retrieved, we paddled mournfully to our camping spot. I was slouched in the Eskia, paddling a good distance behind and giving James plenty of space. Needles to say, when we landed, he didn’t help me out of my kayak as he usually does.</p>

<p>After about an hour, James was back to his old self and being very poetic about the whole thing. He said it was bound to happen sooner or later. The very nature of cell phones is that they easily get damaged and lost, simply because they are not wired to a wall.</p>

<p>We landed in the area were Ed Frigon’s old floating wharf used to be. All that was left was a construction of poles covered with barnacles embedded in a very mucky shoreline. Half hidden in the trees was an upside-down boat, weathered, worn, with a couple of gaping holes in the bottom—definitely no longer sea-worthy!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20old%20floating%20warf%20(2).JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s old floating wharf</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Barnacle%20encrusted%20relic.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Barnacle encrusted relic</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/No%20longer%20sea%20worthy.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>No longer seaworthy</em></p>

<p>We walked around the forest looking for places to camp. We found the “Green Throne” built by BC Marine Trails. We prided ourselves in being one of the first few people to use it! We found some flat places with nice soft moss among the trees, which was in the area of the foundation of Frigon’s hotel. We didn’t think it was a good place to have a campfire. There were too many “forest fuels” around. We admired the holly and foxgloves—plants not native to the BC wilderness—that have been growing here for over a century. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Frigon&#x27;s%20foxgloves.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Frigon’s foxgloves</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20site%20of%20Frigon&#x27;s%20hotel%20today.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The site of Frigon’s hotel today</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Ferns.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Ferns</em></p>

<p>Finally, we went back out to our landing point and noticed a mound protruding out of the water. There was a small spot just big enough for our tent. There were also some rocks arranged in a circle, which was probably previously a campfire. We added a few more and it made a good fire ring. There was virtually no danger of starting a forest fire here!</p>

<p>We later found the hidden cache from BC Marine Trails that advised us to avoid having a campfire. We were going to keep our fire a secret, but I am going to go out on a limb and confess to it. The spot where we had it is probably the only safe spot to have one on the whole island. Having a fire anywhere else could surely lead to disaster. We felt, by leaving a fire ring on the rise, it will deter people from having one in a riskier place.</p>

<p>We set up camp and then took a walk in the forest, taking pictures of the foxgloves and trees and picking huckleberries. We didn’t do much for the rest of the evening except eat, roast marshmallows, drink tea and try to dry out James’ phone. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Harmony%20in%20green.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Harmony in green</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Old%20man&#x27;s%20hairs.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Old man’s hairs</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Unusual%20coniferous%20trees.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Unusual coniferous trees</em></p>

<p>We watched the tide creep up slowly over the course of the evening. We kept trying to figure out if our tent would end up submerged. It was to be an especially high tide: 11ft. We were getting anxious, staying up as late as possible to figure out how close it would get. </p>

<p>I was very tired, because I hadn’t slept much the night before, and James was just tired We weren’t willing to wait around until 2 am for the high tide point. It turned out we had miscalculated the tide readings and it would not be as bad as originally expected. We didn’t think it would reach the grass—because grass can’t grow under sea water—but we weren’t sure. We thought it might only go to the sea asparagus, in which case our tent, only on grass, should be fine, though it would have been very close.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Sea%20asparagus%20growing%20up-side-down..JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Sea asparagus growing upside-down</em></p>

<p>We ended up working ourselves into a tizzy. We decided to move the tent to a higher point just to put the issue to rest. It was too bad because the other spot was so nice and soft and grassy. At the higher spot, we had to sleep on rocks and roots! When we got up in the night, James concluded that we probably would’ve been OK down below.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20tent%20on%20nice%20soft%20grass.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our tent on nice soft grass</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20tend%20on%20rocks%20and%20roots.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our tent on rocks and roots</em></p>

<p><b>July 20, 2016</b></p>

<p>The next morning, we were thinking of cancelling our trip to Quatsino. We were late for the flooding tide (this sounds a lot like catching a subway). We decided instead to paddle the last leg of the trip against the ebbing tide at a leisurely pace. We were bound to get there sooner or later. </p>

<p>Video: Chloe helping to pack up the tent
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/It&#x27;s%20a%20kayaking%20dog&#x27;s%20life.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>It’s a kayaking dog’s life</em></p>

<p>We crossed the sound diagonally, seeing many passing speed boats. We saw a shoreline of houses, many of which were boarded up. Quatsino has seen better days and, I think, will see them again in the future once people discover what a paradise this is. </p>

<p>We cut around an island and a small peninsula. Finally, we came up to a lighthouse and then noticed a cove with a wharf, boats and a concentration of houses. We had finally arrived at Quatsino. We saw St. Olaf’s church and wondered if it was the church in Emily Carr’s painting, <i>The Indian Church</i>. It turned out not to be. When she was painting here in 1930, the church was a school. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20Quatsino%20Lighthouse.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The Quatsino Lighthouse</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/View%20of%20St.%20Olaf&#x27;s%20from%20the%20water.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>View of St. Olaf’s Church seen from the water</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/indian_church.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Emily Carr’s painting  <i>The Indian Church</i>, 1929</em></p>

<p>We paddled under the wharf, and, after landing, found ourselves in the company of a community of snakes zipping about hither and thither. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Driftwood%20root%20lodged%20under%20the%20dock.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Driftwood root lodged under the dock</em></p>

<p>Since I had been living in Port Alice, I had never seen Quatsino, but heard of many heard stories about it. I envisioned it as a place with aging hippies, huge gardens and peacocks running about freely. One of the residents there who has peacocks brought a huge bouquet of peacock feathers to the Legion one day. I ended up getting a few of them from the bartender I babysat for. </p>

<p>Until then, I didn’t have a boat to get to Quatsino and check it out myself. When I finally arrived, it didn’t quite live up to my perhaps over-idealized image of it. I was surprised that it looked a little dreary. This may have been because of the cloudy day. A major tragedy did happen there in 2002, where a father murdered his six children and then set his house on fire. Even further back, there was a domestic murder suicide. Perhaps the causes and effects of such events leave subtle signs and suggestions on the face of a village, the same way a person who has suffered a great loss has a permanent look of sadness in their eyes. In spite of that, I see that, one day, maybe 50 or so years from now, Quatsino will be a colourful little village (maybe even with the peacocks roaming freely) that will attract many visitors from around the world. It already does to some extent. Perhaps the Quatsino I was seeing in my mind before was a Quatsino of the future.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/A%20dreary%20day%20in%20otherwise%20quaint%20Quatsino.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>A dreary day in otherwise quaint Quatsino</em></p>

<p>Quatsino is a very different way of life. To get anywhere, you need a boat. The community once had an opportunity to install a road, but they voted against it. Although I tend to think of Port Alice as remote, residents leave Quatsino for Port Alice to do their shopping and have a bit of social life and “culture.” </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Backwoods%20GPS.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Backwoods GPS</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Been%20parked%20here%20a%20while.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Been parked here a while</em></p>

<p>We went straight to the Museum, which looked like the only thing open.  We met the curator, Gwen Hansen. I asked her about Ed Frigon, and she led me to a filing cabinet. I read stuff while she and James conversed. Finally, feeling overwhelmed, I asked if I could get copies of the files. </p>

<p>A bunch of people came in who looked very Scandinavian. A very tall guy with a Scandinavian accent pointed to something on the wall and asked what it was. Gwen said it was a sasquatch comb and everybody laughed. Gwen later told me it was a herring comb, but I was still confused. I had to ask James to enlighten me. As it turns out you sweep the comb in the water, catching herring and then throwing them into your boat.</p>

<p>Chloe suddenly started whining hard. James and Chloe took leave of the museum. It turned out Chloe needed to take a really big poop! We were thankful that she didn’t take a dump in the museum! From then on, we resolved to always listen to Chloe, as she usually whines for a good reason (except when she wants extra treats).</p>

<p>We checked out St. Olaf’s church. James was just going to peek in the windows to see what’s inside. I had a more novel idea: I opened the door! It is amazing that there are still places on this planet that don’t have to be under tight security! We went inside, signed the register and took a few pictures of this tiny simple church that was originally the colony’s first school.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/St.%20Olaf&#x27;s%20Church.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>St. Olaf’s Church</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Inside%20the%20church.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Inside the church</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20in%20the%20church.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe in the church</em></p>

<p>Back at our launch point, we sat and had a snack and took pictures and videos of the snakes. It is amazing that snakes can be so beautiful! And fast! In a place where time moves so slowly, it was odd to see something move like it was late for a very important meeting!</p>

<p>Video: Snakes!
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Chloe%20eager%20to%20get%20in%20a%20kayak.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Chloe eager to get in a kayak</em></p>

<p>For the trip back to Atkin’s Cove, I was back in Tigger and James in Eeyore. We paddled over the sound surprisingly fast. We took only 15 minutes to cross it. The snakes must have given us some of their energy.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/kelp%20bed%20by%20Quatsino.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Kelp bed by Quatsino</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Going%20from%20Quatsino%20to%20Atkin&#x27;s.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Going from Quatsino to Atkin’s</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20point%20before%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The point before Atkin’s Cove</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Sea%20onions%20at%20Atkin&#x27;s%20Cove.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Sea Onions at Atkin’s Cove</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Our%20well%20marked%20trail%20to%20the%20truck.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Our “well marked” trail to the truck</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/Dreamland.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Dreamland</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/truck%20with%20kayaks.edited.jpg" alt="Drake-Island"><em>Truck with kayaks</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post14-drakeisland/The%20way%20out.JPG" alt="Drake-Island"><em>The way out</em></p>

<p>James may have lost his phone—and his contacts—but I also lost the starfish picture. I had hoped that it ended up on the Cloud, but it was not the case. At home, James checked out a few tricks on the internet but, alas, the phone was pronounced pooched! He phoned Telus and, luckily, only had to add on another $1OO spread out over his payments for his old phone to get a similar new one. </p>

<p>We had a chat about the various ways people we knew have lost cell phones. One person lost their phone in the toilet! Another had to get a professional diver to retrieve theirs from the ocean and it ended up not working anyway! My son goes through a lot of phones too, but he tends to be a screen breaker. We concluded that cell phones are meant to be destroyed, probably because they are carried everywhere. It is one of those unintentional (or maybe intentional?) schemes that keeps the telecommunications industry booming! </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Huson Caves and Little Huson Lake: Stuck in a Labyrinth with Shifting Walls</title>
	  <link>//Huson-Caves</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2018-05-24T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Huson-Caves</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>October 21, 2016</b></p>

<p>Getting ready for our trip to Huson Caves, James and I were both pretty crabby. I was pooped from working at the pizza place Friday night, and James was stuck with virtually all the preparing. The only contribution I could make was to pack my own bag and water the garden. I was trying to water the garden deeply, but it was making James restless. He was eager to get going.</p>

<p>As we were packing up, Chloe was very concerned about being left. She sneaked into the truck when the door was open and refused to leave. When it came time for me to pull her out of the truck, so James could drive it out of the protective shade of the carport and the car in, you could tell there were a lot of thoughts going through her mind, and a lot of emotions.</p>

<p>On the road, we stopped at Hyde Creek for some coffee, aloe vera juice, the Gazette and the Sun. We checked our maps and determined we would have to turn onto the road to Zeballos. When we arrived at the turn, we stopped to read a map by the road, discovering, to our disappointment, there was no campsite at the caves—at least there wasn’t one showing. As it turned out, there was no “official” campsite, but there was a small unofficial one that was an absolute gem!</p>

<p>Seeing a campsite icon at Anutz Lake, we determined we would have to go right and right again—though that turned out to be a gross oversimplification of the facts. Driving down the well gravelled but narrow winding road, we saw a fork that gave us the willies. It brought back memories of our trip to Gooding Cove, where we ended up on a cut-block on top of a mountain with not much room to turn around. We listened to our instincts, which was telling us that this was not the turn we should take. They were 100% right. As it turned out, there were all kinds of roads and forks, but, thankfully, there were also regional district signs pointing the way to Anutz Lake and Huson Caves, though, not one for that first fork—which was probably the most critical one! It all is in keeping with the tradition of BC signage: of not telling you where to go until you’ve already figured out how to get there! We saw a sign that said Anutz picnic site, but we weren’t sure if that also meant it was a campsite. A truck came driving out. Assured by signs of human life, we decided to try it.</p>

<p>We penetrated the forest and followed a very narrow rugged road that seemed to be going to the ends of the Earth. We felt certain we would eventually find a nice hidden secluded place deep in the forest to pitch out tents. Instead, we found a mob! We came upon a giant family reunion, with people, kids and RVs everywhere! There seemed to be more vehicles, people and congestion there than downtown Vancouver! We couldn’t get out of there fast enough! You’d think we would have been happier to meet up with a pack of wolves! </p>

<p>We were back on the road and headed to Huson Caves, not sure what we would do about finding a campsite. As we drove, the road started looking more and more rough, narrow and forgotten. We caught sight of the butt of a big black bear before it disappeared into the shrubs. We finally came upon a pullout with information and direction signs for Huson Caves, which was the trail head. There was nowhere to camp at the trail head, but the park sign indicated a campsite further down. We drove on. The road got very dark, and steep in places. We finally came upon a dead end and a parked truck. We parked ourselves and, seeing water through the leaves, decided to take a little walk into the bushes. James went ahead of me. I later heard him say a very emphatic “Wow!” When I saw what he saw, I saw that he wasn’t kidding! We found ourselves on the shore of a very sunny small lake with a picturesque Swiss-like mountain in the distance. We were contemplating spending just one or two nights there and moving on, but those plans were promptly altered. I said I didn’t care if I sat around all day doing diddlysquat, I wanted to stay here for the whole four days. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/road_thru_the_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Road through the forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/deep_in_the_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Deep in the forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/our_private_paradise.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Our private paradise.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/looking_north.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Looking north.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/radiance.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Radiance.</em></p>

<p>The campsite is small, so it can only hold two, maximum three sets of campers. Hidden behind some bushes was the campsite of a young couple with a terrier and weiner dog. We also had a brief visit from a large crowd of people who just looked around and left. Our neighbours stayed until Monday. We had the beautiful picturesque spot all to ourselves on Tuesday. </p>

<p>We had recently bought a Nikon 3300. After pitching our tents, I went out and checked out what it could do around our campsite, which wasn’t much. I had a lot to learn. We later went out on the kayaks for a short paddle, but we didn’t have our usual amount of energy. Even Chloe seemed too pooped to kayak. Because it was the middle of the day, the water was wavy. We were heading toward other end of lake, but James hinted that it was farther than it looked. I suggested we head back. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_at_the_helm.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe at the helm.</em></p>

<p>On the way back to the campsite, we thought we could go past the logs and access the caves to the north. When I saw James working hard at it, I decided to land and save that battle for another day. I needed to purge my work week out of my head before I could do anything. James paddled around the driftwood for a while. When he came back, he determined that we could paddle there to get to the caves, however far the water lets us go—which, as it turned out—wasn’t very far at all! 
We spent the rest of the evening trying to take photos of the moon and Jupiter in the dark that ended up being just squiggly lines on a black background. I used James’s app to find out what other planets we might be able to see. We found out Mars was by the moon. Neptune and Pluto were on the other side of the mountain, though probably not visible to us anyway. I was falling asleep sitting up. I dragged myself to bed without brushing my teeth and slept like a rock all night…which is a rarity for me these days. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_moon.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The Moon.</em></p>

<p><b>May 22, 2016</b></p>

<p>We dawdled around camp until nearly one o’clock. We headed out on the lake toward the caves. The current lead us to the deepest spots, and we were drifting smoothly into the centre of the lake. The wind was coming from the north: we had to engage our warp drive paddle to get anywhere at all. We weren’t paddling too long when we met up with some logs blocking our path. James was surprised as, when he had kayaked here night before, that area was wide open. That was when we first realized that logs on water tend to move. Nevertheless, we could quite easily push through with our kayaks, getting hung up on a log only a time or two. I tried to take some pictures, but James complained I was going to get the camera wet by using it while in motion. He offered to hold onto my kayak, so I could get my fix of pictures for while. It worked for a bit, but not really. An artsie with a brand new SLR camera: I was a snap-happy maniac! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/heavenly_huson_lake.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Heavenly Huson Lake.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_snap_happy_maniac.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The snap-happy maniac.</em></p>

<p>We peered at what we thought was the entrance to the cave. It was choked up by millions of logs! Even if we had been able to somehow get past the log jam—which was impossible—we would have met up with cliffs, waterfalls, whirlpools, shallow rapids and rocks, rocks and more rocks! We overcame our denial, even though the circumstances were pretty obvious, and finally decided this route was impassable. Nonetheless, some weird part of us wanted to keep going. </p>

<p>We turned around to go back, but that was a problem! I was fiddling with the camera and quite oblivious to my surroundings. James was a bit ahead of me when I heard his expression of dismay. What? I asked, only half interested. “We’re trapped,” he moaned. In the short time that we were there, all the logs that we had passed by got pushed together by the wind after it had changed direction. It had closed the gap we had entered by and we were definitively trapped! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/i_do_believe_we_are_in_a_pickle.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>My dear, I do believe we are in a pickle!</em> </p>

<p>Panic started to set in. There were a lot of logs in our way. It seemed to be more than we had passed to get there. Maybe we could have walked on top of them all the way back to shore, but we would have had to leave our kayaks behind, or we would have had to drag them across the logs trying hard not to trip, fall into the water or damage our kayaks! We headed to a part of the lake that seemed to have less logs, though there were some gigantic ones among them. James pushed a few of the logs out of the way to make a path through the logjam. He warned me to keep close behind him or the driftwood would quickly close up and block me in. We struggled and fought, pushing and pulling on logs from our kayaks. Chloe was getting so distressed by our distress that she kept trying to crawl into my cockpit. Even though we were in the midst of catastrophe, I couldn’t help but reach for my camera several times, which, with fact that we were trapped, was making James even more irritable. What can I say, I am a slave to aesthetics! Finally, he told me to put that @#&amp;*# camera down. We managed to forge ahead, James creating openings in the logs, and I following close behind. Then we came upon a gigantic immovable log that was tightly jammed up at both ends! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_oblivious.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe oblivious.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/move_you_damn_logs.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Move you damn logs!</em></p>

<p>That’s when James got out of the kayak and started jumping on top of the log in frustration (he later confessed to me that he had fun doing that)! While standing on the log, he looked around, picked up a stick and started pushing logs around. He managed to create a temporary opening for Chloe and me. Before I was able to get through, I accidentally bumped James’ empty kayak and caused it to drift away (I’m not much help in a log jam, am I?). He had to run down the log to retrieve it! With his kayak secured, he pushed the last two logs apart with his legs so Chloe and I could pass under. I really, really wanted to grab for the camera, but didn’t dare! I found some mobility by grabbing onto logs and pushing them behind me. I moved myself along in one spot by grabbing onto the short branches and pulling. James got into his kayak and followed. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/now_what.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Now what!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/abandoned_kayak.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Abandoned kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/log_jamb.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Logjam.</em></p>

<p>Back at the campsite, we discovered that the campfire that we thought was out, actually wasn’t! I have to admit, I had lapsed in my vigilance. Because it had burned down and stopped producing flames and smoke, it was easy to do. By the time we came back, it was smoking again. See folks! Just because a campfire looks like its out, 
doesn’t mean it is! All it needed was the heat of the mid day and the wind to bring it back to life. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/0Nnu3f8P8bc" frameborder="0"allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>James then asked what we are going to do now. I said we go hiking. 
We ate our kayaking snack, then soaked our fire until we were sure it was completely out. Because we forgot to bring a day pack, we ended up having to use my laptop back pack to carry our hiking supplies. We drove back up the hill to the trail head with the park signs and the outhouses. We studied the map, read some of the info, and were off. I kept taking pictures of everything from moss to old man’s hairs. James was getting very impatient for a normally patient guy. He ended up walking ahead on his own, while I dawdled and clicked away like a woman obsessed. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_campfire_is_out.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The campfire is out!</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/are_you_coming_or_not.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Are you coming or not?</em></p>

<p>It turned out to be a short trail. We found ourselves going down some very steep stairs to a viewing platform overlooking a rocky stream that flowed into a cave. We couldn’t see very far inside it. James jumped over the railings and out of sight. I could not see the outcropping of rock that he landed on, so it looked like he was jumping into the river. James encouraged me to jump on it with Chloe. I said no thanks and passed the camera to him. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/creek_in_the_caves.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Creek in the caves.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/sheltered_waters.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Sheltered waters.</em></p>

<p>James flashed away inside the cave, then, disappeared for a while. Not knowing where he was or what he was doing, I just sat there and hoped for the best. Chloe was crying the whole time he was gone. He finally came back with a couple of pictures that were the money shots. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/inside_the_cave.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Inside the cave.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/james_money_shot.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>James’ money shot.</em></p>

<p>We went back up the stairs and found another set of stairs descending to a below ground oasis. The Huson Caves are part of a karst formation, caves created by gradual weather and erosion that form depressions, underwater rivers and caves. The Huson Caves themselves are carved out of a layer of limestone formed during the Upper Triassic period, over 199 million years ago. The water in a karst formation tends to flow between the layers of bedrock, rather than through joints or cracks, as other types of caves do. The canyon then became a home for vegetation, like lichens, fungi, mosses, ferns and shrubs that like to live in old growth cedar-hemlock rainforests—hence, the oasis effect. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/below_ground_oasis.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Below ground oasis.</em></p>

<p>On our way down, James checked out a dry cave and was tempted to go down a hole. He said he needed a rope to attempt it. I thanked God we didn’t have one! We both bumped our heads a couple of times. I worried about Chloe disappearing into one of the holes, so I attached her leash. </p>

<p>After descending the 300 metres to the bottom of the formation, we found ourselves standing in front of a tranquil pool before the dark mouth of the cave. Rapids cut into the canyon and flowed into to the pool and, eventually, into the cave and away. The pool itself was full of rounded boulders, with a couple of opportunistic trees growing on small rock islands. I went nuts with the camera. I took almost 500 shots at different light levels. Too bad I didn’t know how to use my camera properly at the time, but I managed to get some good shots anyway. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/a_world_above.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>A world above.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/fifty_shades_of_green.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Fifty shades of green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/more_green.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>More green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/moss_and_shrubery.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Moss and shrubbery.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/natural_rock_carvings.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Natural rock carvings.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/not_suitable_for_kayaking.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Not suitable for kayaking.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/oasis_effect.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Oasis effect.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/opportunistic_tree.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Opportunistic tree.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/creek_flowing_into_the_cave.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Creek flowing into the cave.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/layers_of_forest.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Layers of forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/another_world.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Another world.</em></p>

<p>James engaged his inner child and decided he was going to leap over the creek onto a rock. He then crawled up the rock to the other side, disappearing into the darkness of the cave. I was left to wonder and wait. He came back, crawled down the rock face, leapt from the rock in the creek and demanded the camera. I resisted at first, then reluctantly surrendered it. I told him that if he wrecks it he pays for it, even though he was the one who paid for it in the first place. </p>

<p>Like he had springs for feet, James was up the rock face and gone into the darkness. He seemed to be gone for an especially long time. After envisioning how I would call 911 from this deep canyon, I started calling for him. Shortly after, he came hopping and jumping back.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/can_you_find_james.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Can you find James?</em></p>

<p>On our way back up the stairs, James got into a conversation with a hiker, talking about a hole James saw on the way down. The hiker told him where the various branches of the cave go. He showed him a hole to go in, and they crawled through, along with the guys’ wife. I decided to stay back, claiming a touch of claustrophobia, or maybe just being burnt out from taking so many photos and not being willing to crawl and creep around tight spaces on slippery rocks with a finicky Chihuahua. </p>

<p>While James was in the cave, I met our neighbours from our camping spot. They informed us about a decommissioned trail to check out. Instead of going straight back to our vehicle, we hung a left and walked passed a sign that told us not to enter. This is not a move I recommend, as there was a risk of running into things like sinkholes and underground passages…so I didn’t tell you to do this! The trail led to a dirt and rock bridge that had collapsed. Unable to proceed further, we had a good look around. We saw the other side of our lake with the logjam where we were trying to access the caves in our kayaks. We had a good laugh: we were actually thought we could paddle through that! We met a couple of batches of people on the trail and had discussions with them about secret hideaways on Vancouver Island, that is, until they found out we were bloggers and the conversations abruptly came to an end. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/we_thought_we_could_kayak_through_this.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>We thought we could paddle through this!</em></p>

<p>After leaving the caves, James and I later went cutting firewood at the brush piles further up the road. I sat on the truck watching him. He seemed to get carried away and cut more logs than we could ever use. We ended up taking some home at the end of our camping trip and leaving a lot behind for the next set of campers.</p>

<p>After supper, I was taking pictures of the sunset. James hopped in the kayak without saying anything and took off across the lake in the semi dark. He went quite far until I couldn’t see him. I was starting to think of calling 911 again when he eventually emerged out of the evening darkness. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/twilight_shot.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Twilight shot.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/sunset.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Sunset.</em></p>

<p><b>May 23, 2016</b></p>

<p>James got up early, around 8, and I stayed comatose in bed until about 10. We were planning to go on the water early to benefit from the calmness. When I came out of the tent, it was cloudy. James said the waves weren’t going to do anything anyway. We hung around until about 12, walking Chloe, having breakfast and drinking lots of coffee.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/overcast.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Overcast.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_with_reflections.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Chloe with reflections.</em></p>

<p>We paddled along the rocky shore of the lake, exploring cave-like indentations, and an outcropping of rock that looked like a giant horse’s hoof. As I was dawdling behind, preoccupied with taking photos, James took off and hid around the next point. I had no trouble figuring out where he went because, paddling on a still fresh water lake, he left a very noticeable trail of bubbles in his wake. I saw a yellow line on the rocks and asked if this lake has a bit of a tide. James said it was from spring runoff, the line marking the level of the water when it was at its highest. The yellow colour comes from the tree pollen. It reminded me of a carpenter’s chalk line. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/put_the_camera_down.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Put the camera down.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/rock_shaped_like_horse_s_hoof.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Rock shaped like a horses’ hoof.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/kalidescope_effect.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Kaleidoscope effect.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/natures_chalk_line.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Nature’s chalk line.</em></p>

<p>Lo and behold, we found <i>another</i> cabin in the BC wilderness! The water was very deep in that area, so we landed several metres away and walked to it. A few of my steps discovered sink holes, so I had to move fast. Inside the cabin, it looked like the last people there left in a fit, as there were dishes and debris scattered everywhere. When I took pictures, I stepped carefully, worrying about falling through the floor. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the_cabin.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The cabin.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/someone_left_in_a_fit.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Someone left in a fit.</em></p>

<p>After I got back in the kayak and waited for James on the water, I heard a gun shot that told us there were people around. We paddled toward the campsite where there was an SUV. By the time we got there, the SUV was gone. Their campfire rim was still warm, but their fire was definitely out. Good show, guy, whoever you are! It later turned out he was someone James worked with. James figured it out by noticing a photo of Huson Lake on Facebook some time later and finding out who took it. </p>

<p>We walked down the river to some rapids, trying to figure out how to make the endless stream effect with the camera. We were still so woefully ignorant about the operation of our camera. We walked toward the beach and saw an odd wood construction: a wood frame facing the lake. We read the inscription on it that said, “See TV.” We sat and watched the “natural” TV program of waves on Little Huson Lake while we ate our snack. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/dreamy_green.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Dreamy green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/see_tv.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>See TV.</em></p>

<p>The wind picked up. We realized we had better head back. I had had my fill of photos, so I took the Eskia (Tigger) this time. I noticed how tippy it was, but also how fast it was. It just slips along. The Manitou (Eeyore) seemed like a tractor by comparison, but it is a tractor we need, for Chloe and the camera box. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/chloe_with_reflections.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Shadows and reflections.</em></p>

<p>For our last evening at this special little spot, we had a supper of Greek salad and steak with Cajun spice. We started up a conversation about the camera and how to get certain effects. I asked James if he still wanted to go on a night kayak ride. He said his typical “do you want to?” which means he doesn’t really want to. I then had an idea. Since James had an alone kayak the night before, I thought it was my turn to have an alone kayak in the evening light. He promised to take some pictures of me in the hopes of getting some good ones, since I had been complaining that he takes such bad photos of me. Even though he doesn’t have much to work with, he always seems to get me at a bad angle, in a bad light, or when I’m mussed up or frumpy. If I was dressed up to the nines, probably the last thing he’d think of is to reach for the camera! </p>

<p>Going on the water alone like that, it was like a meditation. For some reason, the clutter that moves around in the brain seems to suddenly disappear. I didn’t &quot;think&quot;, and it was easy. I just listened to the birds and looked around, paddling a few strokes and then drifting. When I meditate, it is quite a discipline. Meditating alone on the kayak, though, came quite naturally. I did do some deliberate thinking though. I imagined what this place looked like before people. There would still be birds singing, but the mountains would be completely covered in trees and there would be no cut blocks or logging roads. There on the lake, I was in a timeless zone. When I came back, James actually took some not bad pictures of me, including the one where I’m sticking out my tongue (oh well, you take what you can get). Clearing one’s head can be highly beneficial in unforeseen ways. There’s nothing like a little pre-historic time travel to rid your brain of busy work week. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/alone_kayak.edited.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Alone kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/raspberries_to_you.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Raspberries to you.</em></p>

<p>On our way back, we stopped in at Nimpkish Lake, just off highway 19, at “the sign with no sign” by a cabin at the side of the road. It was one of the special hideaways that the other hikers informed us about. Because it is a very long, Nimpkish Lake makes a good wind tunnel—not great for kayaking. I’ve read in the Backroad Mapbook for Vancouver Island that it has a few rivers flowing into it, with varying levels of difficulty, that would be suitable for kayaking. Because of the perpetual wind, it is an excellent spot for parasailing and wind surfing—and is well used in that respect. It is very scenic too, making it a good spot for a camera buff. Here are some of the pictures I took while we had a short stop there. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/nimpkish_lake.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Nimpkish Lake</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/blue_on_blue.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>Blue on blue.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post13-husoncaves/the-upside-down-stump.jpg" alt="Huson Caves"><em>The Upside-down stump.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Hardy Bay and Storeys Beach: The Great Escape</title>
	  <link>//storeys-beach</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-10-01T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//storeys-beach</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>Hardy Bay, March 30, 2016</b></p>

<p>It was March…not exactly kayaking season. In many parts of the country people were still coping with snow and sub-zero temperatures. I was feeling an urgency to do some kayaking as soon as possible, which was a good feeling to heed, as there would be an unexpected turn of events that would turn our lives upside down in August. </p>

<p>Unlike in the summer, I couldn&#39;t go kayaking at any time. Because I worked at the school during the week and had an almost full-time job on the weekends, there weren&#39;t many opportunities for me to take off during the school year. James was a little freerer: he worked a half dozen 2 to 4-week mill shutdowns in the spring, summer and fall, with big breaks in between. I saw spring break coming from afar and set the wheels in motion for a kayaking trip for that time. Interestingly, the gods seemed to collaborate with my intentions. The weather on the North Island is usually quite soggy in March; however, those three days that we ended up going kayaking we had an unusual gift of mid-July type weather. </p>

<p>Things were looking good for a spring break trip, except for one hitch. I had to renew my first aid certificate for my lunch supervisor job at the school, and the course was smack dab in the middle of the spring break week we were planning to go. Also, I had to go back to work at my weekend job on Friday. We might have gone farther afield if not for that; but, as it turned out, it was a blessing. Our first kayaking trip had to be local. We considered Storeys Beach by Fort Rupert about 30 minutes away, but weren&#39;t terribly enthusiastic about it. We ended up discovering that it was a gem of a kayaking site, both &quot;exotic&quot; and suitable for almost all ages. Its funny how we tend to think how something exotic and exciting has to be far away and cost a lot of money to get to. So, if you have kids, maybe a Chihuahua or other kind of pooch and not a lot of time for a high kayaking adventure but want one anyway, try out Storeys Beach. </p>

<p>Another complication was lodgings. Our home (James moved out of his rental and into my place in November) was not too far away. There are no campsites at Storeys Beach, so we figured we had to stay at one in Port Hardy. It was a little weird. We would be camping in a municipal area, and there was still a 30 minute drive to our kayaking spot—and it was only a 45 minute drive from home! I guess we just needed to camp; it had been a long winter. We checked out two campsites, but one was closed. We ended up staying at the Quatse River Campground. Again, we were pleasantly surprised and delighted by this element in our close to home adventure. </p>

<p>We arrived at the Quatse River campground on Tuesday and had our pick of camping sites. We walked around to find the very best one, finding it hard to decide. We settled for a site on the banks of the river. We ended up moving two sites down shortly after when a giant bus-camper from Florida showed up and marred our view. Before the sun went down, I took James on a walk on the Quatse loop walking trail. I lived in Port Hardy in 2009-2010, and I used to spend a lot of time on that trail. I was under a lot of stress, so the Quatse Loop Trail, with its tall and ancient Emily Carrish trees and cut-off-from-the-world feeling, provided me with a sanctuary of peace. I was delighted to share it with someone, especially with James who also tends to like that kind of thing. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/quatze_loop_trail.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze Loop Trail.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/a_quatze_loop_monolith.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze Loop Monolith.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/understory.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Understory.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/ferns.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Ferns.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/mother_tree.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Mother tree.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/old_souls.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Old souls.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/old_mans_hairs.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Old man&#39;s hairs.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/wild_flowers.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Wildflowers.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/bank_of_the_quatze_river.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Bank of the Quatze River.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/back_to_camp.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Back to camp.</em>  </p>

<p>During the day on Wednesday, I did my duty by going to my first aid course at North Island College. After grabbing a quick bite to eat at Mo&#39;s, I met James and Chloe at the prearranged kayak launch point at the end of the sea walk on Hardy Bay. There is a little sign there indicating a kayak launch. I&#39;ve walked by that sign dozens of times and never saw it before: it is interesting how what we see is so selective. I suppose our brains would be overwhelmed if we processed everything we saw. I think this applies to nature: it is such a complex system, I think we have barely begun to know all that is there. The First Nations people from thousands of years ago might have been a lot more aware, knowledgeable and sophisticated than we industrially-oriented &quot;modern&quot; people could begin to fathom. Methinks Mother Nature has been posting a lot of signs in our reality lately, and we have been missing all but a scant few of them. James already had both kayaks on shore and was ready to go. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/daddy_cares.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Daddy cares.</em></p>

<p>Then we wondered where to go.</p>

<p>We thought about going north but, with the wind, the water was sure to be rough where it was open to the Queen Charlotte Strait. We decided to head south toward the Quatze River estuary—the &quot;industrial&quot; area, which, surprisingly, turned out to be a lot of fun. It was a novel switch from our usual remote adventures with no or hardly any people around. We took photos of a big barge loaded with heavy construction equipment, as well as a float plane coming in for a landing overhead. We paddled around the estuary—parts of which are solid ground at other times of the day—easily seeing the sand and rocks under the water and sometimes almost running aground. At low tide, this area becomes a sandbar and a graveyard for dark, spooky, dead driftwood tree creatures. A few of those creatures were still sticking out of the water. We came close to a couple of them to pay our respects. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/hey_baby_paddling_my_way.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Hey baby? Paddling my way?</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/barge_with_crane.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Barge with crane.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/float_plane_overhead.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Float plane overhead.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/mommy_and_chloe.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Mommy and Chloe.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/paying_respects.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Paying respects.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/steely_eyed_captain.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Steely-eyed captain.</em></p>

<p>We found a spot for a picnic on the east shore. As we ate, we were the main attraction for an audience of seals peeking out of the water. On our way back to the launch point, we came across a couple of teenagers pretending to try to push each other off of a very high pier and looking, perilously, like they might succeed. I told them to &quot;be careful&quot; but was totally ignored as they seemed to be having a whale of a time. Instead, I paddled slowly and kept watching them until they looked like they were out of danger.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/quatze_river_estuary.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Quatze River estuary.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/setting_summer_sun.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Setting summer sun.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/creek_bed.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Creek bed.</em> </p>

<p>Coming back into Hardy Bay, we saw a couple of lighthouses, one by the fish plant and close to shore, and one in the middle of the bay. I looked longingly at the lighthouse in the centre of the bay. Even though I hadn&#39;t said a thing about it, James told me that going to the lighthouse wasn&#39;t going to happen this time because it was too windy, the water was too rough and it was too late in the day. Remembering our paddle to the lighthouse on Neroutsos Inlet, I wasn&#39;t going to argue. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/lighthouse_by_the_fish_plant.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Lighthouse by the fish plant.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sunset_landing.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sunset Landing.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sunset_on_hardy_bay.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sunset on Hardy bay.</em></p>

<p>Our eventful day was not over. After kayaking, we went to visit James&#39; son, Dakota, and daughter-in-law, Cassandra, and our new grand-daughter, Gabby, born in December. Back at the campground, we sat around the campfire and marvelled how bright the stars were in the March night sky. We talked about them and wondered what we were looking at. Then, James realized, that there must be an app for that! Sure enough, there was! We discovered the star that puzzled us the most was actually Jupiter. It was then that I realized—for the first time in my life—that the brightest stars that appear first in the night sky are planets. What was actually Jupiter, I used to think was the International Space Station. Before the internet, it seems like we were living in the dark ages!</p>

<p>Since we were camping in March and the nights were long, we ended up using a lot of firewood. It was chilly one too, so an extra comforter was must. After all, we were only a few days out of winter.  </p>

<p><b>Storeys Beach, March 31, 2016</b></p>

<p>We planned our trip around the weather report and it fulfilled itself exactly as predicted: three sunny days in a row with the temperatures in the mid teens! Sometimes the weather guys <i>do</i> get it right! On Friday, when we packed up to leave, the clouds came right back!</p>

<p>Storeys Beach is the shoreline of Beaver Harbour, located between Port Hardy and Fort Rupert on the east side of Vancouver Island. The shallow bay has four islands in the middle of it: Shell Island, Cattle Island, Deer Island and Eagle Island. This area is the ancestral home of Kwakiutl band of the Kwakwaka&#39;wakw First Nation, and was once a happening place, in pre-European terms: plank houses adorned with carvings and family crests housed extended families engaged in seasonal routines of hunting and gathering, as well as periodic dance rituals, dramas and potlatches. With the arrival of Europeans, a trading post was established on the Nahwitti River, north of town. When coal was discovered in 1836, the Hudson&#39;s Bay Company developed a fortified trading post at Beaver Harbour. The hamlet of Fort Rupert got its name from the Hudson&#39;s Bay Company governor, Prince Rupert, Duke of Bavaria. In 1887, a former HBC employee who married a First Nations woman, Mary Ebbets, and had numerous children (political leverage), ended up reclaiming part of the land rights of Fort Rupert back to Kwakuitl residents. Although Storeys Beach seemed quite serene and empty at first; it definitely has the feel of a place that has had a lot going on in the past…for thousands and thousands of years!  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/stories_beach.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Storey&#39;s beach.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/unloading_the_kayaks.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Unloading the kayaks.</em></p>

<p>The night before, we checked the weather and the tide guides to make sure we were not launching during low tide…to avoid a long walk with heavy kayaks on the especially wide beach. High tide was a 6:30 am. We launched around 11:30, right in between high and low tide. We didn&#39;t have to drag the kayaks too far. I launched in Eeyore (the slow steady kayak) and James was in Tigger (the fast bouncy kayak). I had to paddle carefully, because the water was mere centimetres from the bottom of my boat. Just when I thought I was a good way out and could paddle normally, I got stuck on a sand bar! I said to James &quot;I&#39;m stuck!&quot; perhaps sounding as if I expected him to come rescue me. He does tend to rescue me a lot, and I might be getting a little too used to it. Instead of dealing with a problem by &quot;taking the bull by the horns&quot; right away—as has been my way most of my life — I now tend to hesitate to see if someone else will take care of it for me. He snarked, &quot;I guess you are going to have to get out and walk!&quot; I replied, &quot;I know that!&quot; I got out and walked, pulling the kayak with Chloe in it. James snapped a few shots of me walking on water.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/launching.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Launching.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/walking_on_water.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Walking on water.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/still_walking.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Still walking.</em> </p>

<p>Shell Island is a hang out place for all kinds of birds, mostly seagulls, though we did see some rather unfamiliar birds, including Harlequin ducks. When we approached, our arrival caused a kafuffle. Some birds took to flight, and others swam hurriedly away from us. Paddling in between Shell Island and Cattle Island, we saw two immature sea eagles perched on rocks, looking dopey and innert. At first, we thought they were Golden eagles, which is a common mistake. Young eagles look like Golden eagles until they mature and develop the dark brown body feathers and white head feathers. James came in close to snap a photo. The bird didn&#39;t move, seeming to enjoy the notoriety—or he was just too young to know any better. Seals were playing peek-a-boo with us. We drifted through the murky whitish (because of the shells) greenish water between Shell and Cattle Island, surrounded by tiny jumping fish, when we saw what looked like a totem pole and little fountains of water squirting out of the shore. With all the eagles and squirting somethings, we decided a landing at Shell Island was warranted. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/crab_trap_buoy.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Crab trap buoy.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/birdsanctuary.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Bird sanctuary.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/casuing_a_kaffuffle.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Causing a kafuffle.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/birds_take_flight.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Birds take flight.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/harlequin_ducks.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Harlequin ducks.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sign_on_shell_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sign on Shell Island.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/young_eagle.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Young eagle.</em></p>

<p>Shell Island is a photographer&#39;s dream, with black lava boulders contrasting with the white broken shell sand. Add to that the abundance of wildlife. James and I are in the process of shopping for a new camera, bemoaning that we did not yet have it so we could use a telephoto lens on the birds. What also added to the photographic delight was the fact that James was dressed in a black T-shirt and black sun glasses which, with his pale complexion, made him match the island! I took a million pictures. We had a picnic on the white rocky beach, stripped a little, and then laid in the sun like it was the middle of the summer (remember, it was March!). We checked out what we thought was a totem pole, but actually was a sign saying, &quot;Kamsaxtte.&quot; Although I am totally ignorant of what the sign means and the significance of the island to First Nations cultures, it sounds a lot like &quot;namaste&quot; and I wouldn&#39;t doubt it has a similar meaning. I would also venture a guess that Shell Island is a spiritual sanctuary. I don&#39;t need to find this out, as the vibes are everywhere!  If anyone who is reading this knows anything more about the history and significance of the sign and Shell Island, I would appreciate it if you enter your comments at the conversation section at the foot of this post. The squirting somethings we guessed to be barnacles just under the surface of the rocks and sand. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/looks_like_snow.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Looks like snow.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/where_are_we.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Where <i>are</i> we?</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/white_shell_sand.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>White shell sand.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/boulders.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Boulders made from undersea lava deposits.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/island_of_contrasts.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Island of contrast.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/tranquil_pool.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Tranquil pool.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/james_matching_the_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>James matching the island.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/chloe_meet_eagle_eagle_meet_chloe.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Chloe meet Eagle, Eagle meet Chloe.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/chloe_photo_bombing_my_artistic_driftwood_composition.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Chloe photo bombing my artistic driftwood composition.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/sea_shell_composition.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Sea shell composition.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/two_sun_bathing_beauties.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Two sun bathing beauties.</em></p>

<p>After launching from Shell Island, we went in the direction of Cattle Island, where we would get ourselves into a bit of a pickle, to put it mildly. Ever since we arrived, we had been listening to intermittent flurries of sea lions barking. A fishing skiff seemed to be at the epicentre of it. Sea lions were barking at fish workers who were tossing them fish scraps. 
Fishing skiff.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/seals_playing_peek-a-boo.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Seals playing peek-a-boo.</em></p>

<p>In another area, we saw something weird. It looked like fins and tails swimming in a circle. I moved closer. I realized that if I continued along that trajectory, I&#39;d glide right into the middle of the moving circle, which, in hindsight, would have been disastrous to say the least! James told me to take a wide berth. I went around, but had evidently already agitated the creatures in their ritual, as there was a sudden onslaught of hostile barking. I beat it away from the group, taking a quick look back at the circle. Just as I was turning my head to look, I saw the gigantic head of an enormous light grey seal bull with large black spots and a heavy set of jowls rise out of the water and give me a nasty penetrating look. No need for words! Mind reading between animals and humans definitely exists! When I was halfway around—heading toward Cattle Island the long way—the harem&#39;s barking intensified. We booted it. Chloe was getting scared and kept trying to crawl into my cockpit. Somehow, I managed to hold her back and paddle incredibly fast at the same time! Embedded in the cacophony of barking, we heard what sounded like the roar of a giant monster opening its jaws. When we thought we were far enough away, we relaxed and put down our paddles. As soon as we did that, though, the party of sea lions came rushing after us! They chased us for a couple hundred metres, then suddenly stopped. I think it was more of a threat than anything, as they could have easily caught up to us and done some serious damage. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/FUqEjtZ1nIs" frameborder="0"allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>We did some googling and believe we were dealing with Stellar sea lions. The females can weight as much as 350 kilograms (770 pounds) and measure up to 2 metres (7 feet). The males can weight up to 1120 kilograms (2500 pounds) measure over 3 metres (11 feet). We were being chased by several thousand kilograms of angry sea lions!</p>

<p>Deer Island is owned by the Kwakiutl First Nations (so is Shell Island, but people are allowed to go there for day trips), and is out of bounds. You have formally request permission to go there. Paddling by, we saw a bunch of raw wood constructions and a tarp over a dome shaped frame: tables and possibly a sweat lodge. Paddling around to the north, we ran into an abundance of kelp on the water. I started picking them and dropping them into my cockpit. I had images in my mind of making kelp chips in the same way I make kale chips. As we rounded the island, the kelp appeared in greater and greater abundance. I ended up filling up my cockpit and getting my shorts thoroughly soaked! James was getting impatient with me. He kept ordering me to stop, but I couldn&#39;t help sneaking a few more here and there. Just think, generations of people have probably been collecting seaweed over millennia in this very spot!</p>

<p>As we rounded Deer Island, facing the open water, the ride got rocky. I looked to the east and could see the mainland in the distance, with a whole lot of blue water in between! After our trip down the wilder side of the islands, we came around Eagle Island and landed for another picnic and some sun-bathing. As we relaxed on the pebbly beach, we marvelled at how we had hard time telling it wasn&#39;t July. We were even sun burnt in places. Our inner seasonal time clock was experiencing a lot of confusion. The trouble with feeling like it was the middle of summer is that it gave us the uneasy feeling that fall was just around the corner! It&#39;s was a unsettling thought, especially when we only said goodbye to winter a few days ago. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/eagle_island.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Eagle Island.</em> </p>

<p>Throughout the day, we kept hearing a repetitive blast that sounded like a cannon. On Eagle Island, the sound seemed a lot closer. We looked and looked, trying to figure where it came from. We then realized that there was a flight path overhead, and that the airport was not too far away from us on shore of Vancouver Island. James figured out the blast was from canons trying to scare birds away from the landing strips. </p>

<p>The next stop on our trip was a return to Shell Island, but there was a large body of choppy water in between. James gave me the lighter kayak because he felt sorry for me, and he took the Manitou. We determined we had to do a serious warp drive paddle across, or the trip would take us all day. I was really going. James later confessed he was having a hard time keeping up with me. </p>

<p>Back at Shell Island, we turned left and headed for shore. We couldn&#39;t see our truck, and didn&#39;t know exactly where to aim. If we would have gone in at the wrong angle, we could have ended up a kilometre or two away from our launch point and we didn&#39;t have enough energy left in our bodies to correct it. We finally recognised a microwave tower that we saw when we left, and oriented ourselves with that. We saw the sea lion&#39;s love-in going on in another part of the bay and gave them a wide berth. The water was, more or less, at the same level it was when we left—we had been paddling and exploring the bay for roughly six hours. This time, though, we didn&#39;t have to walk on water. We determined that we ended up doing a serious 12-kilometre paddle. It was nice to experience a little bit of summer, even if it wasn&#39;t actually summer.  </p>

<p>When we were packing up the truck, I had thrown my seaweed into a clean garbage bag. When we got back to our campsite, I spent the evening rinsing the seaweed in fresh water from the campground tap to remove the slime, then hanging it on a line between two trees to drain and dry a bit. The next day, when we got home, I rigged a line on my balcony so the seaweed could dry further. Before it was completely dry, I made a batch of kelp chips in the same fashion as I make kale chips. Taking about half of my spoils, I cut them up into small squares, drizzled them with olive oil, and salted them just a little—just enough to bring out the flavour. Kelp already has lots of salt to start with. I put them in the oven at a low heat, about 300° Fahrenheit, (about 150° Celsius) until they became thin and crispy but still green. The first few bites were hard to get used to, because it is a slightly different taste from kale chips, but it didn&#39;t take long for me to start liking them. James missed out on the culinary experience because he was working a shut down out of town. With my busy schedule, I ended up neglecting the other half of the kelp on the line. They started to get too dry, so I took them off the line and put them in a pan under a cloth, ready to make kale chips for the next time I had a chance. By the time I got around to making them, they were way too dry and didn&#39;t crisp up in the oven properly. If you make kelp chips, cook them when they are still damp. Determined not let this wonderful nature&#39;s bounty go to waste, I threw it on my garden for fertilizer and slug repellent. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post12-storeysbeach/seaweed_drying.jpg" alt="The Great Escape"><em>Seaweed drying.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Starfish Are Having A Party</title>
	  <link>//Starfish-Party</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-07-11T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Starfish-Party</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>October 4, 2015</b></p>

<p>We were getting some beautiful fall weather. The sun was shining, the water was calm, and the environs were accented by fall colours. The urge to go on the water was irresistible, not just for James and me, but for my neighbour across the street, retired school principal and very keen kayaker, Polly Steele. Polly was loading up her kayak in the warm October sun the same time we were. Just like geese, who start their migrations in response to certain cues in the environment, as soon as the sun comes out on a fall day, kayakers head to the water. Polly spends a lot more time on the water than we do. Very often, if you look onto the water on a calm morning and see the tiny shadow of a kayaker, it is probably Polly. It is amazing that there are not more kayakers on the inlet in the mornings. If you are a seriously addicted kayaker, Port Alice is the perfect place to live or own a vacation property, not just because the inlet is sheltered from the waves and winds of the open ocean, but because the water is easily accessible from civilization. If you get the urge to kayak, you can have your butt on the water in no time! You don’t have to load up your vehicle with a bunch of camping gear and drive for hours and hours to find a beautiful quiet place to kayak.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/fall_colours.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Fall colours.</em></p>

<p>We went down to the Marina; Polly arrived shortly after. While James was unloading the kayaks, Polly and I talked about the election. It is funny to think back to that conversation, and how neither one of us had a clue about the big surprise that was due on election night.  </p>

<p>Because she had a fancy dansy kayak rack, Polly unloaded her kayak lickety split and was off on the water and gone while we were still unstrapping ours! I took “Tigger,” the fast bouncy kayak, and James took “Eeyore,” the slow steady kayak. We went around the breakwater, then headed for the Frigon Island group. It was easy going. There was no wind; the water’s surface was like a mirror. Going in between the two islands, a sea lion barked at us. We looked around. We saw him just as he surfaced and then dove into the water. He was huge, at least a couple of metres long! We could tell, by the menacing sound of his barking, that he didn’t like having us around. In spite of his territorial theatrics, he didn’t bother us after that. He was just letting us know how big he was, and that he was keeping an eye on us. </p>

<p>The water was especially clear, as the mill had been down for a while. Although pulp mills have to conform to very strict environmental controls these days, they still have an effect on the water. It is a stark contrast to what the mill was like in the 1980s. People tell me that the air back that was thick with smog and that the water was virtually devoid of aquatic life, with all kinds of strange coloured substances floating in the water. People who protested the mill back then coined the name “Neurosis Inlet” as a way of voicing their objections. Oddly, today, the locals seem to still call it “Neurosis Inlet”, not realizing or not caring for the subtle difference in pronunciation between “Neurosis” and “Neroutsos.”</p>

<p>We noticed an abundance of jelly fish. They came beside our boats, one after another, doing their weird little swim. Either there were a lot of jelly fish, or they were purposefully coming by to check us out. We passed a reef by the islands and saw a multitude of starfish having a starfish party! As we were paddling around the starfish, Polly came by. She and James chatted about how clear the water was, and about the recent abundance of sea lions and whales. I was being obsessive, trying to get the absolute best shots of starfish. I was having a hard time getting a good compositional arrangement to photograph because, as soon as I had a good one, the kayak moved and altered it! I became flustered, trying to paddle to the perfect spot for a photo and then snapping it fast enough, worrying that I might end up dropping the phone in the water. After a while, I snapped photos nearly indiscriminately, hoping that I incidentally got in a few good shots. Eventually, James ordered me to curb my frenzied photography. I complied, simply because I was getting frustrated. Polly took off and went to the south part of the island. James and I went across the inlet to check out a river. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/jellyfish.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Jellyfish.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/a_starfish_party.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>A starfish party!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/james_and_polly.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>James and Polly having a neighbourly chat.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/gimme_that_camera.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Gimme that camera!</em></p>

<p>After eons of coughing out rocks, boulders and wood into the inlet, the small sparkling river created a huge underwater mountain. It made for a wide stretch of shallow water for us to walk in up to our ankles, as well as a habitat for seaweed, sea onion and sea asparagus. With massive pieces of driftwood lying around, the sand bar looked like a graveyard for monster trees from Lord of the Rings. We stopped and took a bunch of pictures on a big snag. Chloe posed for pictures, looking like a hero dog in an animal adventure series. I took a bunch of photos of James hopping on the giant piece of driftwood—which made my knee cringe! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/the_underwater_mountain_top.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>The underwater mountain “top.”</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_the_super.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe the super kayaking dog.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/james_on_the_giant.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>James on the giant piece of driftwood.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/log_with_seaweed.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Log with seaweed.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/sea_onion.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Sea onion.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/a_dog&#x27;s_boat.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>A dog’s boat is her castle.</em> </p>

<p>Back at the kayaks, we walked in shallow water for quite a distance before hopping in. We were contemplating a picnic, but decided on having one on the Frigon Islands instead, as there weren’t any dry comfortable places to sit. James tried to paddle up the river, but, with the tide going out, he wasn’t able to get very far. On the way to the islands, I commented that the water’s surface seemed convex: that shortly after we left shore we seemed to sink down a miniscule amount and go lower as we got closer to the centre of the inlet. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/south_view_from.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>South view from the Frigon Islands.</em></p>

<p>Sitting on our blanket and eating on the sand bridge between the Frigon Islands, a crow protested that he wasn’t invited to our picnic. We threw crackers and grapes at him. Sometimes he ate them right away, other times he carried something off to a hiding spot. We had to throw our givings a good distance. If we didn’t throw them far enough, he wouldn’t come close to get them. 
Casting off for home, we drifted by an Inuksuk on the south island. In the last couple of years, there has been an mysterious invasion of inuksuk’s in Port Alice. They appeared in healthy numbers by the kayak launch, on the islands and on the shores of Neroutsos Inlet. Some would crumble back to the elements, then more would appear. They were the talk of the town for quite a while, as people tried to figure out who their creator was. One day, I discussed this mystery with one of Port Alice’s resident professional photographers, Darrell McIntosh, and he confessed it was he who made them. Since he often makes calendars of his nature photography to sell, I suggested he make one with his inuksuks. He hummed and hawed about it at first, but, eventually, he did it! That was already a couple of years back. </p>

<p>Chloe stared at the inuksuk like it was a real person or animal. She even barked at it! There’s something about Chloe and sculptures! When we were in a car rental agency this last Christmas 2016, she became very distressed by the presence of a carved wooden Santa Claus they had in the front lobby. Talk about the power of art! Even animals can have a sense of it! 
James took a picture of Chloe looking at the Inuksuk. I told him to take a picture of the Inuksuk too, but—tired of all the picture-taking—he protested. When he paddled around the island, he got a change of heart. When I finally caught up to him, he confessed that he ended up taking the picture anyway. I have to thank the gods for that intervention! This story would have been sorely incomplete without it, and James later had to agree. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_staring_at.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe staring at the inuksuk.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/the_inuksuk.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>The inuksuk.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post11-starfishparty/chloe_afraid_of_santa.jpg" alt="The Starfish Party"><em>Chloe afraid of Santa.</em></p>

<p>And this, folks, is the end of the story for our 2015 kayaking season. By the time I finished writing this post (January 2017), there have been a few changes in Port Alice thanks, I believe, to our town’s various web promotions, including portalicelife.ca, vancouverislandhiddengem.com, and chloethekayakingchihuahua.com. Though this is hardly quantitative, many of the locals have been commenting that there has been more tourist activity in Port Alice. One more concrete sign of this is that the local grocery store, F.P. Foods (now called Port Alice Family Foods) opened its doors from 8 to 8 in the summer! The latest I remember them staying open is 7 pm—and that was when the mill was open! </p>

<p>I think kayaking is a very good way to spend our time here on Earth, and even a good way to enliven our economy to a degree. It’s great physical activity, keeping us healthy and fit—even for us oldies with bad knees! The activity itself doesn’t require oil or gasoline, and doesn’t churn up the water or introduce hazards that affect animal life the way motor boats do. We need some of that oil and gas to make kayaks, but they can last a long time. One kayak can last a lifetime, and maybe even a couple more after that—unlike most cars! Kayaking provides us with more opportunities to interact with our animal and fish friends, promoting more awareness of and empathy for our ecosystem. It’s hard to take care of nature’s creatures if we are not even aware that they are there, and that they have intelligence, personalities, and that they even like to be funny sometimes.</p>

<p>Kayaking also helps us to explore those beautiful idyllic settings that are just around the corner, that we may have lived near all our lives and not really seen or appreciated. Who says you have to spend a bunch of money to fly for hours in a plane to a place considered to be exotic? We have oodles of exotic, peaceful and beautiful bodies of water to visit right here in Canada, some of which rarely see people. Canada has over 30,000 lakes larger than three square kilometres—that’s a lot of places to kayak! Whether they are in the west, the east, the far north or in a municipal area, there is something magical about all of them! Mother Nature is an artist who doesn’t skimp on quality.</p>

<p>Our societies’ focus on buying and selling things has gotten out of hand, and we need to change course. Instead of being addicted to buying stuff that, half the time, we don’t need and that just ends up in the land fill, I think we would be better off spending our money on generating “positive experiences.” We can even base a vibrant economy on such “ephemeral” things. It doesn’t have to be primarily based on the exchange of solid, material objects. </p>

<p>I have a pact with James and my son. We exchange gifts at Christmas, a little reluctantly, but for every other occasion, we celebrate with a nice dinner or a night out. We have to eat or be entertained anyway. We don’t end up with a bunch of junk that we have no place to put. There is a limit to how many gadgets a person can actually use. In fact, in many material-object-based industries, like the fashion industry, products have to be regularly destroyed to keep up demand. </p>

<p>The best thing about kayaking, is that it can be a spiritual experience. We can miss so much of what is going on in “reality,” as the TV slowly and insidiously reconstructs our perspective. Kayaking teaches us about various other “worlds” out there, from the worlds of plants and animals… to the long lost cultures of First Nations people (who have maintained this planet for millennia without bringing it to the brink of destruction)…to that space in the silence of nature that helps us be more creative—and that just might provide us with the solutions to all our problems.  </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>A Rupert Inlet Snippet</title>
	  <link>//A-Rupert-Inlet-Snippet</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-05-14T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//A-Rupert-Inlet-Snippet</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>September 3, 2015</b></p>

<p>James and I often go out to Rupert Inlet to camp with his son, Dakota, and daughter-in-law, Cassandra, and a lot of their friends and neighbours. The land is owned by Western Forest Products, and people get to camp there by their good graces. The sites are undeveloped, but there are the necessary couple of outhouses for sanitation, and the view is amazing! The time spent there is taken up by catching prawns and crab, digging for clams, picking berries and sea asparagus, cooking, eating, drinking and socializing around the fire…the usual North Island weekend warrior kind of stuff. It doesn’t make for much of a story; or, it makes for too much of a story…so I won’t bother delving into it. I will simply cut down my workload and share some of our photos. On this trip James brought his daughter Tyra and her dog Sweetie up from Campbell River. One afternoon James, Tyra, Sweetie, Chloe and I broke away from the party and went kayaking out onto the inlet. On the way back, we kayaked up Rupert Creek, passing under the bridge and winding through the forest until we could go no further. Coming back around the estuary, Tyra noticed a house in the bush and wanted to check it out. Being adventurous and curious people, we obliged her and found quite a surprise indeed! It was an abandoned house, slowly destructing over the years and pregnant with hidden stories.</p>

<p>To get to Rupert Arm, turn left from Highway 19 at the Port Alice turnoff to Highway 30, “The Port Alice Road.” Follow it for 10.6 kilometres, until you reach a gravel road crossing the pavement, and take a right onto Hardy Main. Follow the gravel road until it loops around. It should only take a few minutes go get there. Be careful to stay on the main road. There are at least a half dozen possible wrong turns you could take that could lead you heck knows where! You will pass the fork in the road that leads to Varney Bay to your left, so stay right. After the loop, you will start noticing the inlet through the trees and several driveways going to the shore. One is private property and the other ones lead to camping spots. When you see the outhouses, the main road veers away. You need to get off the road before it does. Take the left fork by the outhouses and it will lead you to the last camping site, which is the one we usually camp at. Keep in mind, they tend to fill up on weekends, especially long weekends in the summer, so get there early, go there during the week, or have an alternative in mind in case it’s full. Maybe James, Chloe and I will see your there someday! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/tyra_and_sweetie.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Tyra and Sweetie.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/texting_on_the_kayak.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Texting on the kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/a_happy_dad.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>A happy dad.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/captain_chloe_on.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Captain Chloe on the bridge.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/house_in_the.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>House in the trees.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/checking_things_out.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Checking things out.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/leaning_with_the.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Leaning with the years. *
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/that_last_party.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"></em>That last party must have been a doozie.*
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/winding_stairway_to.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Winding stairway to nowhere.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/chloe_and_sweetie.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Chloe and Sweetie investigating.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/barbie_a_casualty.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Barbie a casualty.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/ferns_growing_on.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Ferns growing on the roof.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/harmony_in_green.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>Harmony in green.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post10-arupertinletsnippet/view_of_rupert.jpg" alt="A Rupert Inlet Snippet"><em>View of Rupert Inlet.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Neroutsos Inlet: When the Ocean Sneezes…!</title>
	  <link>//Whale-Sitting</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-05-02T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Whale-Sitting</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>August 10, 2015</b></p>

<p>Because I had to work and wasn’t available for kayaking, James decided to paddle the inlet on his own. Chloe stayed at home. James would end up having plenty of company anyway. He launched at the transfer station around noon. Not a good time to launch—and he would pay for it later! It was a bit cloudy, so the water was calm. With the tide flooding into the inlet, he paddled easily south toward the marina and the Frigon and Walk Out Islands. James was contemplating visiting his friend and old work buddy, Russell Inglis, who lives on the other side of the inlet, when suddenly, in the quiet of the cloudy day, he heard a sound that made him think that the ocean had sneezed! </p>

<p>Startled, he looked around for the source of the explosive sound. About 200 to 300 metres away from him, a whale had surfaced and was putting on a good show. It did some shallow dives, breached up, arched its tail and then went into a deep dive, not coming up for 4 or 5 minutes! It was a very surreal experience, out on the ocean with another animal the size of an airplane! When writing up this post, I asked James if he felt a sense of connection with the whale. He put down his cell phone and developed a quizzical expression. After a few seconds of silence, he answered, “I guess so. It was just him and me on the water.” James took some pictures, but they were taken after the breaching and didn’t do justice to the whole experience.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post9-whalesitting/the_whale.jpg" alt="Whale Sitting"><em>The whale.</em></p>

<p>I find it curious how there are so many videos of kayakers encountering whales without incident. Sometimes they even come within a hair’s breath of the kayak, without even rocking the boat. It is amazing that such massive creatures can be so careful and exacting in their movements, demonstrating a basic respect for diminutive creatures like us—as well as a certain playfulness. Like the seals and the sea lions, they like to tease and flirt. </p>

<p>James carried on to Russell’s place. First his dog came out to meet him, then Russell came to check out the commotion. Russell is an always jovial guy with a a very off-handed sense of humour and permanent devilish gleam in his eye. His property is an acreage on the underpopulated side of the inlet. His family gets many of their needs met from the land, having gardens, chickens, goats and access to prime fishing from the inlet. Even though they live in a fairly remote secluded place, it doesn’t prevent them from going out and about. When the family goes to the Legion Thursday nights for darts league, they often go by boat!  The whole family, including the in-laws, are all dart sharks and usually go home with prize money from tournaments quite consistently! I got paired up with Russell in a doubles tournament once and we won first prize! See, that’s how good of a dart player he is: that he can be paired up with a greenhorn like me and win! I wasn’t doing too badly that night, though, and got in some lucky shots at the right time that helped keep us out in front. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post9-whalesitting/russell_inglis.jpg" alt="Whale Sitting"><em>Russell Inglis.</em></p>

<p>Russell gave James a tour of the property. He showed him his sawmill, an old jeep that he was working on, and some of the things left by his father that he was planning to fix and sell. He introduced James to the goats and chickens, showed him a little greenhouse that he built, then showed him his son’s place a little further up the hill that was close to the finishing stages of construction. They then went into the house for a coffee and a beer. Like every conversation in town as of late, after talk about family and acquaintances, there is discussion about whether or not the mill will reopen. The visit was topped off by a trip in Russell’s skiff to his special fishing spot where they pulled up a large steel and very heavy crab trap full of crabs. Bringing the crabs back to the dock, Russell put some in a live well and processed a couple for James to put in his little kayaking cooler for the trip back.  </p>

<p>After leaving Russell’s little North Island oasis, James Paddled directly across the inlet. He received another greeting from his buddy, the whale, hearing a blow hole on the west side of the inlet, in the direction of the mill. By this time, it was getting sunny. The wind was picking up and blowing in his face. Paddling was getting a lot harder. His arms were getting tired, so he took a break in a little bay near Walk Out Island.  As soon as he left the protection of the Frigon Islands, the wind intensified. He contemplated pulling into the marina and walking back to the truck on the other side of town. In the end, he decided he was due for a work out, and he <i>definitely</i> got one! For about three kilometres he paddled with all his might, not getting very far very fast. He thinks he was paddling 6 or 7 knots, and going back 3. For those of you who are land lubbers, a knot is equivalent to almost two kilometres per hour. At the last little bit, he had to crank up the intensity to be able to get anywhere at all. Needless to say, he was happy to see his landing spot. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post9-whalesitting/port_alice_pulpmill.jpg" alt="Whale Sitting"><em>The Port Alice Pulp Mill.</em></p>

<p>Sitting on the shore, he took some time to recoup his strength and evaluate how many parts of his body were sore…but the wind wasn’t done with him yet! To add insult to injury, he had to wrestle with the wind as he struggled to mount the kayak on top of the truck all by himself. </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Wild West Coast and the Rogue Wave Rodeo</title>
	  <link>//gooding-cove</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-12T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//gooding-cove</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>August 4, 2015</b></p>

<p>Gooding Cove turned out to be our “adventure of misadventure”—and the misadventures were on straight out of the gate! On our way to the Wild West Coast, we followed Marine drive around the south end of Neroutsos inlet. Because I was so busy with my several part time jobs, I had to leave the research of how to get there all to James. I was blissfully tuned out as he was navigating. He followed the instructions in the BC Coast Explorer, telling us to follow Cayuse Main. We took a turn on Cayuse Main, driving for quite a while on a very undeveloped road, until, after coming up on a couple of fallen trees, James said a despondent “something’s wrong.” I was inclined to start chopping, but, as I later learned, the road to the Wild West Coast was a well enough travelled road that it should have been clear. We put our heads together and studied the book and the maps and figured out the <i>BC Coast Explorer</i> probably had a typo. We turned around and went back to Marine Drive. We followed it until it “became” Teeta Main (no turns taken) and just continued on. We then felt we were on the right track. </p>

<p>So, if you’re going the Wild West Coast, do not take Cayuse Main! It would probably lead you there eventually, but I wouldn’t recommend it unless you happen to be driving a bull dozer! Just follow Marine Drive until it <i>becomes</i> Teeta Main. After that, follow the rest of the instructions in the <i>BC Coast Explorer</i>. As we were driving along Teeta Main, looking for the switchback that was supposed to be 25 km from Port Alice, checking out this side road and that side road and wondering if that was it, what did we come across but a great…big…LOGGING TRUCK! James turned very white! He shifted the truck into reverse and goosed it! Luckily, the logging truck had been slowing down to make a turn from a side road onto Teeta Main, and he was able to stop in time. It was obviously a little bit sooner than he expected, as his cab bucked up and down harshly from the abrupt deceleration. Realizing the logging truck had stopped, James shifted the truck into drive and goosed ahead! As we made our getaway, he informed me that our bacon was probably saved by the other pick up trucks that had passed us earlier, warning the logging truck drivers over the two way radios about a couple of yahoos with kayaks. </p>

<p>I have mentioned this before, but I will mention it again: if you don’t have the foolhardiness to travel on logging roads while the logging trucks are working, avoid travel between 6 am and 6 pm on weekdays. There are many stories around the Island of people who were seriously injured and even killed meeting up with a logging truck. Because logging trucks have the right of way, they are not even liable if they run into you. Some roads are not too bad, such as this one to Gooding Cove and Side Bay, as they are quite wide and have enough room to let two vehicles pass—in most places at least! It helps that James is familiar with logging roads, but I’m going to push for travel after 6 pm from now on, when feasible. If you come from a place where logging roads are a remote concept, you should travel during the safe hours, or better yet, hire a local to guide you. The village office/tourist information centre can give you some good leads. There is talk in Port Alice about having bus tours to Side Bay and Gooding Cove, but the idea is still in the “contemplative” stages at this time.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/forestdirectionsigns.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Forest Direction Signs.</em></p>

<p>You might notice that on one of the signs in this photo, it says there is logging activity seven days a week. I’m not sure what to say about that, as there was a much greater preponderance of signs saying there is activity only on weekdays. Also, there is a mantra going around Port Alice that says “loggers keep banking hours.” In our travels, we haven’t seen any activity on weekends. I do know, that on the road to Link River, gravel trucks travel seven days a week and we need be careful about that. I’d say that travel on the weekends is generally safe, but, as with everything in life, there might be exceptions. Keep your eyes peeled at all times anyway. </p>

<p>We finally came across the switchback as described in <i>BC Coast Explorer</i>, and were heading up on K500, then on K main over the mountain pass. From K Main, we went on I main, then J main. As we got closer to the Wild West Coast, there were bold red and white hand painted signs pointing the way to Side Bay and Gooding Cove (I guess if you managed to make it this far, you finally earned the right to know where you’re going) so we were able to put down our books and maps. The road was pretty good in some places, and it even became a two lane highway in one stretch. It turned out to be a nice drive for a while. All the forks in the road had direction signs…except for one…and that was a problem! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/chloe_having_a_scratch.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Chloe having a scratch while James adjusts the straps.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/mountain_fireweed.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Mountain pass with fireweed.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/mountain_pass_pine.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Mountain pass with pine trees.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/road_show.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Let’s get this show on the road.</em></p>

<p>After we passed LeMare Lake we came across a fork in the road with a sign post that didn’t have a sign. We pondered and debated which one to take. We took the road to the right, thinking that the cove would be just on the other side of the ridge. It <i>definitely</i> turned out to be the road less travelled….to our chagrin! As we were driving, it struck me that it seemed like we were going up, but we couldn’t tell for sure because the trees were masking our surroundings. I started turning to a Nervous Nellie, complaining that this road was giving me a bad feeling. We debated and debated, but kept wondering what was behind the next rise. We drove up one rise only to find another one, which lead to another debate about whether or not we should take it. By the time we were certain we were on the wrong path, we were greeted by a spectacular panoramic view of the Quatsino Sound! </p>

<p>We found ourselves on a mountain cut block and quite nearly at the very top! We stopped at a little pull-out (emphasis on the “little”) because I really had to get out. My Nervous Nellie jitters turned into a full blown panic attack. I got out of the truck and didn’t care if I had to walk all the way down! Even so, I still grabbed the camera and took numerous shots of the incredible view! I couldn’t conceive how anyone could turn around on that narrow road with not much of a pull out, but somehow James did it! When I got back to Port Alice, I told one of my bosses, Rhetta Vesna at the Ozzieland Campground, about this. She informed me that she and her husband, Ozzie, ended up doing the very same thing back in the day…except, they didn’t just have a measly little pick up truck…they had a truck and trailer! Somehow they lived to tell about it! Rhetta says that’s probably why she has heart trouble today!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/quatsino_sound.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>View of Quatsino Sound.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/ozzieland.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Rhetta and Ozzie: would anyone like to buy a campground? They would really like to retire!</em></p>

<p>At the bottom, we took the other fork, crossed the bridge over Lamere River and passed by a rock slide that gave us cause to pause. On Restless Main, we passed Harvey Cove, stopping a couple times to take pictures. Arriving at Gooding Cove, we met a couple of campers and had a chat with them before setting up. They warned us not to drive on the sandy beach with our 2-wheel drive. They suggested instead that we camp on a ledge at the side of the cove that was close to the road. To camp on the beach would have meant too much walking with our heavy gear, so we agreed that the ledge was the solution. We mentioned we were bloggers and got quite a reaction. They suddenly got horrified looks on their faces and begged us to not tell anyone about this place. How’s <i>that</i> an endorsement for you! I figure if only a handful of people know about places like this, they may end up getting used for some less than aesthetic purpose. The more people that know about places like Gooding Cove, the more likely they will be preserved and protected. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/rock_slide.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Rock slide that gave us cause to pause.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/harvey_cove.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Scene by Harvey Cove.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/goodingcove.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Gooding Cove.</em></p>

<p>After setting up camp, we went for a walk along the beach. We contemplated going for a paddle, but we were too burnt out from the trip. We spent the night sitting around the campfire, watching the flames and not saying very much. Perhaps we were clearing our minds in preparation for the next day’s misadventures. </p>

<p><b>August 5, 2015</b></p>

<p>It rained all night. Luckily, it was a fairly light rain. James got up in a frenzy in the middle of the night. Our tent had become the location of a new mini lake! We had a tarp under the tent (as well as over), but part of it was extending past the tent, catching water and causing it to flow down the slight slope and straight under our air mattress!  After James went out and made some adjustments to our tarps, we fell back to sleep. We woke up again around 8 am to the sound of raindrops hitting our tarp and waves crashing down below. </p>

<p>We opened the tent to find a miserable day out there, but it was only drizzling, not pouring. We contemplated what we should do, even considering going back home. We certainly felt frustrated enough to do so. The whole discussion was resolved by us falling gently back to sleep. When we got up at about 10:30, James opened the tent and peeked outside and proclaimed a couple of spots of blue sky. We felt hopeful. We took our time getting up, starting a campfire in the drizzle. The clouds seemed to anchor themselves just over the cove and the sun stayed out at sea. After a while, the clouds started to shuffle back and forth over the shore, causing the weather over us to alternate between drizzle and sunshine. I did my forest fire lookout weather forecasting and determined we had a short window of opportunity. I was a bit rushed, feeling we had to go soon or we would be going home unkayaked, but James wanted to deal with our wet clothes and the water problem in our tent. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/tent_view.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>The view from our tent.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/below_tent.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>The view below our tent.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/anchor_clouds.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Clouds anchored over the cove.</em></p>

<p>We lassoed a couple of saplings to make a clothes line. When I went into the tent to clean it out, it felt like a sauna. I removed all the clothes, putting the wettest ones on the line to half dry in the drizzle. We put our semi dry stuff and critical sleeping bags in the truck, so at least they wouldn’t get wetter. I lifted out the air mattress, finding a significant body of water. I took out the mattress and flipped it over so it could dry out in the occasional bits of sunshine. After soaking up what I could with a towel, I lifted the tarp off of the window in the back of the tent to create some air flow. I tied open the front entrance and left the tent to dry out…somewhat. </p>

<p>James and I quibbled over the campfire again. We put the bucket of water we had on it, but it was still smoking. I wanted to put another bucket on it, but he accused me of being over the top with this fire thing. He then told me to get the bucket myself. So I did. I found the wash water from last night and put that on the fire, but it was still smouldering. I went down the long way around the rocks to get more water. As I was getting my water, I looked up at James sitting on the camp chairs, and he didn’t look too happy. As I came back up the hill, he started walking down to the beach with the stuff for our kayaking trip, still very disgruntled. </p>

<p>After I satisfied myself that the fire was sufficiently out, I met him at the kayaks. There was one more fire that needed to be put out. James eventually apologized for getting mad at me. I told him, that I wouldn’t feel very comfortable out there kayaking knowing that the fire wasn’t completely out. Since he’s a pipe fitter, I told him it would be like him fixing a pipe and leaving a very small leak. He seemed to connect with the metaphor. Although the air above ground was wet on this day, the ground underneath, with all the dried leaves and other organic matter that is the “fuel” for a forest fire, was very dry. The rain was only wetting the ground’s surface and not sinking in very far. I could quite literally “feel” the dryness beneath me. I might have seemed “over the top” because the weather was so miserable. After eighteen seasons of taking weather calculations and seeing how they affect fire behaviour, I wasn’t fooled by the light rain. We had been having a long dry summer: it would take several days of heavy rain to bring the hazard down to safe levels. Even then, you should still be vigilant about putting out your campfires. As I explained in my Link River post, fires have ways of burning in low hazard, over a long cold snowy winter, and even underground for a hundred years or more!</p>

<p>It seemed to be a rough start to the day all over. Dozy and uncoordinated, we carried the kayaks down to the shore to about the middle. We had Chloe in the kayak and were sort of lined up to launch—except I wasn’t in it yet. As I was trying to push the kayak onto the water and hop in, a big wave came in and landed on Chloe! She had such a look of ultimate betrayal in her face! I thought she was going to hate us forever! We both felt like terrible parents! Chloe’s blankets were soaked, and she was soaked! I picked her up in my arms and cuddled and consoled her a while in some dry blankets while we tried to figure out what to do next. We considered everything, from giving up to going to the quieter part of the cove. We thought about switching kayaks but, in the end, James decided to go in the water a little and pull me out. He probably shouldn’t have been in the front of my kayak.  When it came time for me to paddle like a demon, I accidentally smacked him in the head with my paddle (take that for not letting me put out my campfire!) Alas alack, Chloe and I made it out past the breakers without getting soaked. I apologized profusely for smacking James, but he didn’t look like he was in too much pain because he was laughing. 
On the water, I couldn’t find my pedals. We had to paddle to a quieter part of the cove and get me adjusted (something we should have done before we launched). The big differential between the highs and the lows of the water level was giving me a bad case of turn-backitis; but, as soon as we were on the water, James was in charge and we were going. Sounding very professorial, he instructed me to avoid certain rocks, larger swells and breakers. Because it seemed like he knew what he was doing, I followed faithfully. At the mouth of the cove, paddling on the open ocean, we saw a wave farther out that was a huge fan of water splashing up 3 metres or more! The rocks the helped produce it were hiding stealthfully just below the surface of the water! I hate to think what would have happened to us if we were anywhere near there! We navigated between the spot with the scary wave and the rocks with the breakers, going up and down, up and down on the big swells. Finally, James paddled out ahead to check things out around the point and I stayed back. After he had a good look, he waved at me to follow. Swallowing my prairie chicken fear, and strongly resisting the temptation to go straight back to the shore, I did as he ordered. He told me to go slow and take my time. </p>

<p>After a short stretch on rocky open ocean, we soon found ourselves in a tranquil cove with plenty of rock formations and islands. Staying close to shore, we snapped pictures and reveled in the beauty of the rocks, the islands and the marine life. James was looking for a cabin that was built by a friend of his that was supposed to be somewhere there. We saw a cabin, but it turned out to be someone else’s. Before heading there, we took the roundabout route, paddling between the rocks and islands. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/tranquil_cove.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>The tranquil cove.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/photo_cameo.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>A photographic cameo effect.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/smoothpaddling.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Smooth paddling.</em></p>

<p>Passing over calm waters between two rocks in between two islands, I felt my kayak suddenly rise up! I screeched at James, but it wasn’t enough warning. I rose about a metre into the air, but managed to avoid a splashing! Instead, James, who was little ahead of me, got swamped! It was a rogue wave! I remembered that when I paddled up to the rocks and looked out at the ocean, I could see no sign of waves for at least a kilometre! That mischievous wave had sneaked into the cove incognito, suddenly appearing under us the very moment we were passing between the two innocuous rocks. One is inclined to thing there was some kind of intelligence at work here! Thankfully, Chloe didn’t get swamped a second time, as she was in the Manitou with me. James, on the other hand, had to pull out the bilge pump. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/beware_rocks.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Beware of those rocks ahead!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/flat_water.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Don’t let this flat water fool you!</em></p>

<p>On the way to the cabin, we said hello to Mr. Jellyfish and took some pictures. At the cabin, we delighted in using a real outhouse! We saw a folding chair sitting under a bunch of fishing floats hanging in the trees. The cabin looked nice on the outside, but it was very bare bones on the inside. The walls were made of unpainted particle board and it had few furnishings, essentially a big shelf full of cots. We found a guest book that had been written in extensively, possibly over the space of decades. I didn’t spend too much time reading, but noticed one passage where the guests had to contend with rats. Because it was cool and dreary inside, we went outside to have our snack. We walked around the beach and checked out the rocks. We found wild strawberries growing high up on a couple of large rocks on shore, their tiny habitat being high enough to be safe from the tides and waves.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/mr_jellyfish.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Hello Mr. Jellyfish!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/selfie.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>A selfie.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/cabin.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>The cabin.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/fishing_float.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Fishing float decorations.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/old_soul.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>An old soul.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/ded_jelly.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Deceased jellyfish.</em></p>

<p>We left the cabin and paddled to the point to check out Restless Bight to the south. James went out ahead of me to scout but, seeing high winds and a lot of breakers, he called off the attempt. On our way back, a large seal or sea lion had some fun with the tourists. He did a flip out of the water behind us, causing a noisy splash and making us jump. 
That rogue wave must have seriously spooked James. As we were going back around the point back to Gooding Cove, he was ahead and I was well behind. I was taking my time, because he told me to do that before. He started complaining about my slow pace, so I geared into my warp drive paddle. We rounded the point, riding high swells and keeping our eyes on the breakers further out to sea. Perhaps James realized we could easily be hit by a rogue wave again; but, on the open ocean, it would have been a lot more devastating! It was probably only the luck of the draw that we didn’t. The water was turbulent probably because of the stormy weather. On a calm sunny or generally overcast day, the trip might not be so risky. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/serendipitous_forest.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>A serendipitous forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/wild_west_coast.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Wild West Coast woman.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/swell.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Approaching a swell.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/queasy_ocean.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>Are you getting that queasy open ocean feeling?</em></p>

<p>I was glad when the point was behind us, but we still had to ride high swells all the way back to the shore. We decided to go far to the right on the beach that was more protected. The waves weren’t that bad by then though, and we probably could have landed in the centre. We walked back, looking for a walking stick for me because my knee was bugging me. As we were sitting on a log and looking at the bay and our kayaks, it occurred to me that we should name our kayaks. Calling them by their product name was a little too formal. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/pooped_puppy.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>A pooped puppy.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/gooding_cove_view.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>View from Gooding Cove.</em></p>

<p>We got a fire going again—which was really hard because it was so wet (I wonder whose fault that is!)—and cooked up all our remaining meat, including steak and pork chops. We sat by our campfire watching it burn and listening to the crashing of the waves. I so love doing nothing sometimes!</p>

<p><b>August 6, 2015</b></p>

<p>It was dry in the morning, but we kept sleeping in our tents. As I was laying there, I contemplated the naming of our kayaks. I thought about naming the Eskia “Donovan Bailey” or “Andre Degrasse” because it was the fast one. Because the Manitou sounded like Manitoba, I thought about naming it after Winnipeg, as like in Winnie the Poo. Then I thought about the characters in Winnie the Poo. I thought, because the Manitou was the slower steady kayak, it should be named “Eeyore.” Then it occurred to me that we should name the Eskia “Tigger,” because it was the fast bouncy kayak. James had a laugh and seemed to agree. From then on, our kayaks were named Eeyore and Tigger. It is probably very apropos, since I’m a children’s author, and James is a children’s author’s boyfriend, who, by the way, is also a remarkably kid friendly person. We don’t have too many disagreements on how to deal with children (like we do about putting out campfires). </p>

<p>By the time we were out of our tent, it was raining steadily. James went to get the kayaks to put them on the truck. I stayed back and dismantled the tent. Even though we hadn’t started a fire that morning, when James wasn’t looking, I dumped some water on our campfire pit. Even though it didn’t look like it was burning and it was raining lightly, the fire pit hissed like a pit of snakes! Even <i>I</i> was surprised by this! That fire looked dead, but it was full on alive! </p>

<p>As we were packing up, our neighbours left and some new campers came by. We were worried that my two-wheel drive would not be able to make it up the road in the rain. We asked the new possible campers to look out for us. It was a good thing, as it turned out they were just about to leave. I got out of the truck to lighten the load. James made it up, giving a happy toot when he made it to the top. Otherwise, we might have been stuck there a few days!  </p>

<p>We were planning to go to Side Bay for at least a quick look, but, because of the rain, we felt an urgency to get back. James left the final decision to me and I decided against. James later said it was a good thing, because, if we had gone there, we would have been coming back late at night, which, on long lonely logging roads, is not a pleasant notion—especially if we suddenly find ourselves on the top of a mountain with nowhere to turn around! </p>

<p>Driving back, we kept hearing a strange noise. I thought it was my differential (I forgot I used to have problems with it). After stopping a few times, we finally figured out it was because I didn’t twist the straps that hold the kayaks and it was causing “harmonic vibration.” In fact, I tried to make them especially flat and straight because I thought it was more aesthetic…silly artsie me! Alas alack, it wasn’t my differential! After fixing the straps by giving them a few twists, we continued on the slow long two and a half hour journey in the rain along logging roads J, I and K. Every once in a while, we had to stop to adjust our foam pads that kept falling out of place, as well as have a listen for the rumble of logging trucks in the distance. </p>

<p>Going over the mountain pass we took to get there, we found it much scarier than the trip the other way. There were no guard rails and we had a full on view of the very steep drop! Going up we were oblivious, as that scene was behind us. We inched along. I had to look away to avoid a panic attack. James was very cool, but I could tell he wasn’t at ease about it either. </p>

<p>Relieved to be past the scary part, we stopped at an overgrown campsite just below the pass and took pictures of the mill across the inlet. It’s funny how the mill, such a massive complex that is such a big part of people’s lives in Port Alice, looks so miniature in the expanse of nature! It makes you realize how the entity that created nature has a lot more resources and a lot more influence in the larger scheme of things. As we drove along Marine Drive, it was interesting to watch it change from a rough forestry road to a municipal paved road lined with signs, houses and pruned and trimmed lawns and shrubs. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/picnic_table.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>A picnic table that has seen better days.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post7-gooding/pulp_mill.jpg" alt="Gooding Cove"><em>The Port Alice pulp mill.</em></p>

<p>I went to my place and had a good nap, my cats sleeping on top and beside me. They quite evidently missed me as much as I missed them. Later, I cleaned myself up a little and went down the hill to James’ place to have some grub. </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Cluxewe Resort: The Big Gamble</title>
	  <link>//Cluxewe</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-01-22T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Cluxewe</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>July 7, 2015</b></p>

<p>James wanted to take his daughter kayaking, but we realized we couldn’t go anywhere too remote. We opted for Cluxewe Resort, just a turn and a short drive off Highway 19. If you are travelling from the south, it is 12.2 kilometres north of Port McNeill, and then a turn to the right. There is a big Cluxewe Resort sign at the turn off, so it is hard to miss. </p>

<p>I stayed with the cats the night before and got a lot of cleaning and garden watering done. I watered everything: the flowers in front, the pots, and the vegetable garden. I even left the hose on mist for a good long time in strategic places like the zucchini planter, the blueberries, the rhubarb, etc. Except between the hours of 12 and 4, I was watering all day and well into the night with the misting hose. You’d think I was living in the desert instead of the rainforest! It’s getting to be that way, little by little. It was a good thing I put down some grass clipping mulch to hold in the moisture. I left the balcony for the morning, did my house-sitting job and then went down to James’ place. We hit the road, James in my truck with the two kayaks, and I in the Camry with his daughter, Tyra, and her friend in the back connected to their media devices. As we drove along, I met a very slow logging truck, a bear (which the girls didn’t see because they were in that other “media dimension”) and a mama deer and her two babies. The baby Bambis hooves were proportionally larger than their growing bodies. Running away from the car they were leaping awkwardly, looking not quite as graceful as Mama. I couldn’t help but think they looked like kids trying to move fast in their mother’s oversized high heel shoes.  </p>

<p>We went to the campsite we reserved but we weren’t happy with it. It was narrow, with not much greenery and lots of traffic driving by to the islet. James took the bike and went on a tour around half the campsite. When he returned, we took the car to the islet and checked out some other camping spots. We really liked 54, but wrote down some other numbers just in case. When we got to the office, we found out 54 was reserved starting tomorrow until September! We ended up in 100, just across from 54. When we were unloading at site 100, I wasn’t much help, as I had trouble sleeping the night before. I did my usual duty, and set up the tent and the air mattress. Once that was done, I collapsed onto the air mattress and slept for a good part of the afternoon. 
James woke me up and put the end of Chloe’s leash in my hand so he and the girls could go kayaking. Though I was barely awake, I noticed that the particular sound of the waves meant they were getting rough. I got up and had a couple of iced teas in my folding chair with Chloe on my lap, struggling to get myself fully awake. When I finally got up to go to the bathroom, James was coming down the road. He told me their trip was cut short by the waves (tell me something I didn’t know!). They had some trouble coming in with the surf and Tyra ended up getting splashed. At first Tyra wanted to go to the lighthouse, but James vetoed it. They said they had fun bobbing up and down, but they didn’t feel like kayaking for very long. It seems like the girls had fun, but got bored with kayaking pretty quickly. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/tyra.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Tyra</em></p>

<p>In the evening, we grilled steaks on the BBQ because there was a fire ban. I complained that we did not have lemon juice and olive oil for the grilled vegis. I’m very persnickety about following recipes to the letter. James often makes fun of me because I won’t go “outside the box” when I cook. I often answer back that I go “outside the box” in just about every other aspect of my life, so I’m allowed. I went toward the office to see if there was a store, but there was only a restaurant. James offered me some olive oil based margarine and butter and I took it, but we couldn’t find a substitute for lemon juice. I was having a crisis! I was so bothered by not having lemon juice, I ended up going to Port McNeill the next day to get it and a few other things.  </p>

<p>James and I went for a bike ride around the campsite, then followed a path into the woods that lead us to the river, a huge pile of water worn rocks and a trail on the beach. We parked our bikes and sat on a log for a while, watching the scenery and musing. We went walking along the beach for as long as my knee could stand it. I thought of Hawaii and how it is very much like this, exotic, but just a lot warmer. James expressed a wistful desire to go to Hawaii someday. I wasn’t interested in Hawaii at first, because I thought it was probably too touristy. When I got there though, after spending a winter in China and Hong Kong, I was actually impressed. I stayed there a couple of months in ‘83, living in a Philipino lady’s apartment with a Swiss roommate and a whole lot of cockroaches. One of those cockroaches was nearly the size of my hand and had sneaked into my bikini bottoms when they were hanging to dry on the closet pole. It gave me quite the scare when I gathered my stuff for a day of snorkeling at Hanauma Bay!
With no campfire to sit around because of the fire ban, I asked the girls if they would be interested in playing poker. They didn’t know how, so I offered to teach them. I first taught them the hands, from lowest to highest, then we played a few practice rounds. We then we had a rousing game well into the night, our table lit with several battery-operated lanterns. </p>

<p>After we finished the game, James and I retired to our tent. As soon as we were in, the girls pulled the poker chips out again and started playing between themselves. While James and I were reading by flashlight, we had to shout out the answer to the occasional poker related question. </p>

<p><b>July 8, 2015</b></p>

<p>We got up around 10, expecting the girls to follow suit not long after…but no such luck. In fact, when we came back from our kayaking trip that day, they were still asleep! I forgot what teenagers were like! 
The other times we kayaked, Chloe whined a lot on the water. This time, however, she whined to get <i>into</i> the kayak! She didn’t whine at all when we were on the water! She is probably so used to kayaking now, that she would probably feel lost without it. It would be much harder for her to stay home alone all day with only a couple of visits from a dog-sitter. Even though she is well into middle age, she is very much a baby at heart and has to go everywhere with Mommy and Daddy! </p>

<p>Following the tide going out, James and I kayaked close to shore in the direction of the estuary. We paddled in the fog, feeling calm, and not inclined to paddle too hard. The estuary water was very shallow. We realized we weren’t going to get too far in at low tide. We decided instead to paddle into the fog, staying close to the shore so as not to get lost and inadvertently paddle out to sea. It’s quite a mystical experience, paddling in the fog. It felt like we were in a bubble, and it was so quiet. We came across a reef of rocks and realized we had to go around. We ran into a kelp bed and a community of rocks encrusted with barnacles. We spent some time paddling around them, snapping pictures of rocks, barnacles and each other.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/islet.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>The islet.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/paddling_in_fog.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Paddling in the fog.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/paddling_rocks.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Paddling around the rocks.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/mist_apparition.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Apparition in the mist.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/kelp_1.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Kelp bed 1</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/kelp_2.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Kelp bed 2</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/barnacles.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Barnacles.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/mom_n_chloe.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Mommy and Chloe.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/duel.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>It’s a duel!</em></p>

<p>Seeing a lot of driftwood on the shore, James and I debated what it was all about. James thought they were man made structures and I disagreed. We paddled there to see who was right, and it turned out James was. Someone had piled driftwood into crude shelters. We landed to check things out. Chloe was excited about the structures, hopping around and energetically sniffing in and around them. We walked down the beach, noticing deer, wolf and even Chihuahua tracks in the sand! We commented that Chloe has gotten a lot stronger and healthier since she started kayaking (even though she doesn’t paddle) and is in much better spirits these days. She gets more exercise, and a lot more varied and interesting things to sniff. We determined that we definitely have to camp here some day. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/dw_shelter_1.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Driftwood shelter 1.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/dw_shelter_2.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Driftwood shelter 2.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/dw_fort.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Driftwood fortress.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/sniff.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Lots to sniff.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/in_shelter.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Inside a shelter.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/whale_sculp.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Whale sculpture.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/dw_little_dog.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Driftwood beach and little dog.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/animal_tracks.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Animal tracks in the sand.</em></p>

<p>James mentioned that we should have brought a snack and should always bring a snack. We thought we were only going to go to the estuary, but it didn’t turn out that way. We admitted we always end up going a lot further than we expect. It was resolved from that day forward that we will always bring a snack when we kayak, no matter where we think we are going. It’s a big deal, because it is very hard to paddle hungry.<br>
On the return trip, we found that the ebbing tide had changed the scenery. There were more rocks than before. The rocky reefs were bigger too, forcing us take longer detours into the centre of the bay. We met two other kayakers on the water—which is a first for us. You would think there would be more kayaking traffic on the North Island in general, but there isn’t. We exchanged our delight in seeing other kayakers. We asked them if they could suggest some good kayaking spots.  Many that they had suggested we had already been to. They also suggested that the south end of Nimpkish Lake and Huson Caves were a must. We eventually did go to Huson Caves in 2016, and the verdict is a definite “yes.” At Nimpkish Lake, however, though the scenery was stunningly beautiful and I was able to take some great photographs, it is not a good place for kayaking. It is a very long lake, making it a wind tunnel with plenty of rough water. Nimpkish Lake is more of hangout for windsurfers and parasailers. It is also good place to camp on the beach. 
Our campsite appeared out of the fog sooner than expected. The fog and the calm water made us lose our sense of time. The shoreline was much longer than it was when we left it, which probably also helped to shorten the trip. We were having a struggle carrying our kayaks up the now significantly larger shore. We thought to alternate carrying them, but, in the end we gave up and decided to leave them where they were, halfway up the shore, as the tide would probably not reach them before the next time we went kayaking. </p>

<p>We had a much needed quick lunch of smokies because we were <i>really</i> hungry! After lunch, James took the girls kayaking while I stayed behind with Chloe and wrote my reflections on my laptop until I got sleepy and had to have a nap. They were not gone too long. When the bunch came back, James told me of some of the unusual ideas they had. Tyra said she wanted to jump in the water and swim! She also kept bugging him about the lighthouse, which he considered out of the question. Then they said they were getting too hot and wanted to come in. I don’t think our 10 or 12 kilometre treks would be these girls’ cup of tea!  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/reflections.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Writing my reflections with Chloe.</em></p>

<p>James and I went out on the kayaks again at around 6 pm, when the estuary was at high tide. The fog had cleared and the water was fairly calm, with a few breakers at the shore. Even though we were only planning to do the estuary, we still packed a lunch as per our previous pact. Just as we got to the beach, James got a funny look in his eye. He looked around at the water, turned to me and said, “How ‘bout we try it?” At first, I didn’t understand what he was talking about. “Try what?” I asked. He didn’t answer me right away, as if he was expecting me to read his mind. It turned out he was meaning paddling to the lighthouse! I was taken aback, as he had been telling me and the girls all weekend that the lighthouse was off limits. I realized that it would be somewhat of a trepidatious paddle, but said a hesitant “OK.” I am a sucker for lighthouses! It would turn out to be a lot more than we bargained for! </p>

<p>We had a clumsy launch. I tried to go out onto the water on my own and ended up getting splashed. I had taken out the rim around my cockpit when I set myself inside and, in the hesitation, got my splashes. I jumped out and James fixed my cockpit.  He told me to jump in quickly, and then he gave me a push out onto the water. We met with huge swells that lifted us way up and brought us way down at regular intervals. It felt a little like being on a ferris wheel. James seemed to be keeping his cool, but I was freakin’. It was especially scary on the Eskia, because it was a much lighter craft. We paddled steady, carefully— no speeding or sudden moves. It was not just water, it was ocean, very deep and full of powerful currents in this narrow passage called the Broughton Strait, and I was one tip away from being in it! Getting capsized in this water would be very dangerous indeed—there is no telling where the currents would take us! I set aside my apprehension and just kept my mind on getting to the lighthouse. We were going at a moderate speed and only took a half an hour to get across, but it seemed like it took much much longer! When we got close to the lighthouse, we were salivating for that solid shoreline! </p>

<p>Grabbing James’ camera right away, I snapped shots of the lighthouse and the view around. In the back of my mind I was still thinking about the journey back and if I had the stomach for it, but I was savouring my time there. I got James to take several pictures of me with the lighthouse in the background. As he was taking one, he accidentally snapped a selfie and Chloe just happened to join in!  The pictures of me didn’t turn out so well, but that selfie turned out to be a gem! No one came to greet us from the buildings, but we couldn’t be too sure there was no one there. We just stayed on the shoreline, presuming it would be trespassing if we went up to the buildings. Shorelines are public domain. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/lighthouse.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>The lighthouse.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/north_lighthouse.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>North of the lighthouse.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/photo.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>The photograph.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/clutsy_photo.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>The clutsy photographers.</em></p>

<p>As we had lunch, I noticed waves curling around a point. We later took a video of it, and a few photos of a big stump. Looking to the mountain range to the west, we saw a mountain top that had a shape of an indigenous chief laying on his back. It reminded me of a peak at Ironstone Lookout that the residents of Crowsnest Pass coined “Mt. Mulrooney” that looks very much like an exaggerated profile of our 18th prime minister. I also thought of the ape face at Raspberry Ridge, in Kananaskis Country by Turner Valley. When the sun is at a certain position in the sky on a sunny mid-summer day, it casts shadows on the Continental Divide producing the face of a giant ape. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/strait.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>The Broughton Strait.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/dw_root.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Driftwood root.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post8-cluxewe/chief.jpg" alt="Cluxewe"><em>Indigenous chief.</em>
<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/FaBe6N9kZrs" frameborder="0"allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p>For the trip back to the campsite, we switched kayaks. James gave me a lecture about points, that we should avoid them because they have dangerous currents. A fishing boat was passing by and James told me we had to stay back and let it pass. After it passed, he instructed me to steer straight into the waves, in case they might end up being rollers. They ended up being not that bad. I was feeling better in the Manitou because it was much more stable in the water. Chloe poked her nose out the cockpit in the beginning and sniffed, then hid herself in the cuddy for the rest of the voyage. I instinctively tried to make a B-line for the campsite, but it turned out to be the wrong plan. James actually started complaining vociferously—which is unusual for him. Because of the wind and the tide still coming in, he told me to point myself toward the estuary, which was north, even though we were trying to go <i>west</i>, to the campsite. Even though we were paddling like crazy to the north, we never passed the line between the campsite and the lighthouse! We just gradually drifted sideways, getting closer and closer to the campsite! It was an odd experience to say the least. Under these conditions, if I had been leading the way, we would have ended up further south in Port McNeill! It is amazing that tides, wind and currents can make such a difference!</p>

<p>As we got closer to shore, James devised a plan for landing. We were to head north of the campsite a bit and then drift into shore at a south-westerly angle, getting a boost from the waves. He ordered me to ride the waves and then start back paddling when I catch a surf. I’m not sure if I really understood his instructions at the time, but somehow, I seemed to have instinctively done the right thing. Mind you, I spent some time in Hawaii riding surfs, so maybe that experience came in handy. I jumped out quickly and hardly got splashed at all. </p>

<p>We were greeted by some onlookers who had watched our landing and were intrigued by our kayaking Chihuahua—especially 3 little boys in shark helmets. When I took Chloe out of the kayak, she seemed to be stuck in my arms, not wanting to be let down. I had to carry the kayak while holding her. I put Chloe on a log to socialize with the boys, while James and I answered grown ups questions about what it was like to kayak with a Chihuahua. When Chloe was done with the PR, she faced both James and me, then looked to me to pick her up. James commented, “You want mommy.” I guess when one has been through a harrowing experience, it’s mommy that they need! Once we were done tying up the kayaks, James emphatically told me he was done kayaking for the day. Later he confessed to me that that trip gave him cause to pause, which says a lot! He doesn’t get scared easily, let alone admit it! We considered kayaking the estuary later that evening, but we were unable to get up the gumption. </p>

<p>That night, after I drove to Port McNeill to get (compulsively) needed ingredients and a few treats like chips and pop, we grilled vegetables on our propane grill. James had the left over steak. To the girls, who seemed to not need food, I gave some cheese and crackers and cucumbers that they barely picked at. They had been playing poker most of the day and wanted us to join them. After we had supper, made coffee and cleaned up, we played poker by the music from the girls’ cell phones until we started yawning. The winner of the all in hand was Tyra’s friend, even though Tyra and James tended to be the winners most of the time. Late at night, we marvelled at the brightness of the stars and how many would could see. We could easily discern the band of the Milky Way. </p>

<p><b>July 9, 2015</b></p>

<p>James and I planned to get up for 8 am to take the high tide into the estuary. We woke up at 7 am, discussing it and checking the tide guide, but fell back into our beds and slept some more. At about 8, I again asked James if he wanted to get up to do the estuary, but he brushed me off saying he wanted to sleep. Later he was angry at himself for not getting up. James ended up getting up around 10:30 and I, 11:30. As we had our breakfast and packed up the vehicles, he kept beating himself up for not getting up in time to paddle the estuary. </p>

<p>You win some. You lose some. </p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Varney Bay: Time Travel and Other Illusions</title>
	  <link>//varney-bay</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-12-02T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//varney-bay</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>June 27, 2015</b></p>

<p>We agreed to get up at 7 am so we could get to Rupert Arm and Varney Bay at around 11 am for the high tide.  We wanted to take advantage of the tide, to let it carry us easily toward Varney Bay.  I slept at my place to give the cats some company before our long time away, and James stayed at his.  Leah, our regular cat sitter, was away, so I had to ask my neighbour, Cathy Anderson, to cat sit for me.  I didn’t want to ask Cathy to cat sit for me unless I absolutely needed it, as she won’t accept payment.  Cathy does a lot of volunteer work in Port Alice.  She has done so much volunteer work over the years that she can’t even remember it all; but, presently, she volunteers at the Port Alice Recycle Centre, The Legion, the Thrift Shop and at the school.  She will even help out whenever someone has a personal or health crisis!  In fact, she has even won the Governor General’s Award for volunteerism in 1988!   I call her the “Guardian Angel of Port Alice,” as she plays a major role in keeping the community going.  As payment for her good deeds, every summer I give her some elephant garlic from my garden.  She loves to get her garlic!  When I give it to her, she has such a beaming look on her face, you’d think I was giving her a bag full of money!  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/cathy.jpg" alt="Cathy"><em>Cathy Anderson.</em></p>

<p>After I had my bath, I called James.  He was already up for a while packing up the truck.  He had put both kayaks on the truck, the Manitou in the back and the Eskia on the roof.  When I saw it, I thought my truck looked like a Christmas tree!  We were leaving the Camry behind this time.  James had charted out our route very carefully in the hope that we wouldn’t get lost.  He even suggested we stop at the side of the road once to check the map and, lo and behold, all cross roads were properly taken!  </p>

<p>To get to Varney Bay, turn left from Highway 19 at the Port Alice turnoff to Highway 30, “The Port Alice Road.”  Follow it for 10.6 kilometres, until you reach a gravel road crossing the pavement, and take a right onto Hardy Main.  Follow the gravel road for 4.5 kilometres until you reach a “Y” in the road.  Be careful to stay on the main road, until the “Y.”  There is at least a half dozen possible wrong turns you could take that could lead you to nowhere, or worse than nowhere!  When you see a sign saying “Varney Main,” take a left.  After travelling 1.5 kilometres, take Varney Main West and continue on Varney Main West for 5 kilometres.  To get to the log dump campsite, take a right.</p>

<p>At the present time (fall 2016), the log dump is deactivated as a campsite, and we’re not sure why.  It might be because the site is considered unsanitary because of a lack of outhouses.  While that campsite is closed, the only way to get to Varney Bay is to paddle there from Coal Harbour, on the east side of Holberg Inlet.  If you take that route, just make sure you don’t accidentally turn into the Quatsino Narrows thinking it is Varney Bay, or you could be in a real pickle!  You can also paddle there from the campsite at the south end of Rupert Arm, but it will be a very long paddle.  I just hope the powers that be will see the light and find some way to reopen that campsite lickety split!  Among paddling sites on the North Island, Varney Bay is a real gem.  </p>

<p>We knew we were driving into the log dump at Rupert Arm—our launch point for Varney Bay—when we saw logs.  To our surprise, however, we also saw a bunch of trailers and fifth wheels and a pack of friendly pouches.  We talked to a couple of the campers standing on a giant protruding driftwood log jutting out high above the water in front of a boat.  They told us that they were trying to make a makeshift dock with some wood they brought, but the plan was thwarted by the arrival of the log boom.  They said they were trying to get on their boat using the protruding driftwood and a ladder.  I couldn’t envision what they were trying to do, as it was looking rather impossible and pretty dangerous.  Perhaps it was a good thing the log boom was there, or they might have ended up needing an ambulance.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/rupertinlet.jpg" alt="Rupert Inlet"><em>Rupert Inlet.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/thelogboom.jpg" alt="The log boom"><em>The log boom.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/protrudingdriftwood.jpg" alt="Protruding driftwood"><em>Protruding driftwood.</em></p>

<p>We first intended to get on the kayaks right away.  Since this seemed to be a busy place, we decided to put up our tent to mark our spot in case someone else came.  We then hopped in the kayaks and were off with a favourable tide and wind.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/chloegettingherlifejacketon.jpg" alt="Chloe getting her jacket on"><em>Chloe getting her jacket on.</em></p>

<p>With the tide and the wind going the same direction we were, it was a deceptively easy trip!  Coming back turned out to be a different thing altogether!  We paddled past the log boom and into the big water between Rupert Arm and Holberg Inlet.  James pointed out an island to me that was supposed to be in front of the Quatsino Narrows and talked again about riding the waves through the Narrows someday.  </p>

<p>At first we couldn’t find Varney Bay, as the entrance was camouflaged by the surrounding scenery.  We kept paddling and eventually the huge bay made its appearance.  We were getting hot under the cloudless sky.  Skirting around an island, we found a spot to land so we could cool Chloe down and have a bathroom break.  The water where we docked was shallow for a good distance into the bay.  After having a drink from our supply of liquids, we waded into the water to cool ourselves to just above our ankles.  We then carried Chloe out into the shallow water for a few metres and let her swim back to shore on her own.  I was surprised how such a round dog with skinny little legs could swim so well!   </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/varneybay.jpg" alt="Varney Bay"><em>Varney bay.</em>
<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Vu-tLJROPtY" frameborder="0"allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p>Like many places around here, Varney Bay is named after a North Island pioneer.  Lord Henry Varney left England and arrived in the Quatsino settlement on the steam ship, Mischief, in 1896, with his engraved calling card that identified him as the ‘the Queen’s Messenger’…which is a little curious.  As I read through the <i>Quatisino Chronicle</i>, my main source of historical information on this area to date, I saw no record of him delivering any messages directly from the Queen.  Perhaps he saw himself as a vehicle of Commonwealth indoctrination.  He and his wife, Ethel, took up a 137 acre homestead at the mouth of the Marble River (probably not far from the very spot we were cooling ourselves down) and raised their nine children.  There was a boarded up fairly modern house on the shores of Varney Bay, just a little south of us—a sign of a good location for a homestead.  Lord Varney home schooled his children with the Bible and harsh lessons in frugality.  When he would send a couple of his children out to hunt—by themselves out amongst the bears and the cougars—he would only allow them a couple of shells and they had to come home with dinner.  He sounds like quite a character, our <i>Lord of this Neck of the Woods!</i></p>

<p>Back in the kayaks, we were having some doubts about finding this Marble River estuary.  We were told there were rock faces and caves, but, at that point, nothing of a sort seemed to be anywhere near.  The surrounding scenery seemed to be a bit too close to the ground to be hiding a canyon.  We soldiered on.  We noticed a patch of green on the water and were wondering what it was all about.  We noticed a current off to the side of the algae and followed it.  Until the bay, the tide was carrying us along.  As soon as we turned into Varney Bay, the tide was against us, as it, as well as all the other water around, was then flowing toward the Narrows.  Adding to that, we had to paddle against the outflow of the Marble River.  The arduousness of the paddle slowed down time for us.  The water was very shallow in places, and we had to navigate around big rocks.  James ended up crashing into one, giving out a yelp!  Luckily, there was no hole in the kayak!  </p>

<p>Going around a bend in the river brought us into the shadowy world we were looking for.  Rock facades appeared out of the vegetation.  The river became mysteriously cool, dark and calm.  A few wedges of bright sunlight illuminated small sections of the shadowy estuary.  Where the light touched the water, it cast rippling reflections onto the rock walls.  The odd tree reached down and out, trying to catch the limited bits of sun.  For lack of flat ground, the ferns grew sideways on the cliffs.  Dripping water made tinkly sounds as it hit the water, then echoed.  Here and there, huge spaces were gouged out of the rocks just above the water surface—the handiwork of some intense spring runoff.  The musty smell of the forest was intensified by the enclosure.  Chloe’s eyed were deliriously wide as her nose stretched far out of her cockpit.  It turned out we weren’t alone.  We heard a big splash!  We discovered we were sharing this hideaway with a seal who seemed to get a kick out of scaring us.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/kayakingintheshadows.jpg" alt="Kayaking in the shadows"><em>Kayaking in the shadows.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/rockface.jpg" alt="Rock face"><em>Rock face.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/emeraldhues.jpg" alt="Emerald hues"><em>Emerald hues.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/cave.jpg" alt="Caves"><em>Caves.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/ripplingreflectionsonrockwalls.jpg" alt="Rippling reflections on rock walls"><em>Rippling reflections on rock walls.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/erodedrockface.jpg" alt="Eroded rock face"><em>Eroded rock face.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/rockfacesgougedoutbyspringrunoff.jpg" alt="Rock faces gouged out by spring runoff"><em>Rock faces gouged out by spring runoff.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/chloestretchinghernoseoutofthecockpit.jpg" alt="Chloe stretching her nose out of the cockpit"><em>Chloe stretching her nose out of the cockpit.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/averticalforest.jpg" alt="A vertical forest"><em>A vertical forest.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/theviewup.jpg" alt="The view up"><em>The view up.</em></p>

<p>We came upon some rapids, but passable ones.  Without hesitation or even asking if I was willing, James just trudged on through, making it look easy.  When it was my turn, I discovered it was not so easy.  I had lifted my rudder and tried to go through, but was pushed back down sideways.   I ended up having to back up.  I put my rudder down and made another run for it, paddling harder than ever.  It felt like I was climbing a mountain!  James sat safely on the other side, watching and grinning.   I think he was thinking I wasn’t going to make it through, but I did!  When I made it to calm water he cheered and said, “Aren’t proud of yourself for having done that?”  I didn’t see it as that much of an accomplishment, just something that had to be done.  Besides I was a farm girl: I was used to dealing with difficult physical limitations without all the fanfare. </p>

<p>We went around a couple of bends and then came to a sharp turn in the river with rapids, a cave, and a swirling current.  We weren’t going to be able to get past the rapids, so we decided to make a stop.  The shore was steep.  It was a complicated maneuver to land.  James got off first with ease, but I was still pretty iffy getting out of the boat (you can take the girl out of the prairie, but not the prairie out of the girl).  He held the boat and I grabbed a rock and pulled myself out like a sack of potatoes.  We tied the kayaks very securely to a small tree on the rocks.  If we lost the kayaks, it would be difficult and dangerous to retrieve them in this environment.  James kept thinking we should portage and go up further, but we ended up just staying there for no particular reason.  Later, when he googled it at home, he figured out Bear Falls might have been not far from there.  We walked around on the water-rounded rocks under a sun shining down hot and hard.  We were in our own little private oasis, notwithstanding the odd cougar or bear hanging out behind the bushes (occasionally, I honked my bicycle bear horn for security).  Not expecting to run into anyone else, we had our picnic and did some sun-bathing—swim suits optional.  James, Mr. Fast Twitch Muscle Stunt-man Sprinter Guy and Glutton for Punishment, of course, had to jump in the water for some hooting and hollering.  He tried to swim to the next bend, but couldn’t see much.  When he swam back he kept challenging me to get in the water.  I opted instead to sit in the water and watch the water flow by.  We spent a leisurely afternoon in our oasis, until the shadows moved over our picnic spot and it was time to head back. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/rapids.jpg" alt="Rapids"><em>Rapids.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/caveoverswirlingcurrent.jpg" alt="Cave over swirling current"><em>Cave over swirling current.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/treesaboveouroasis.jpg" alt="Trees above our oasis"><em>Trees above our oasis.</em></p>

<p>The trip down river seemed so much shorter than the trip up.  Since we didn’t have to fight the current and the tide, we spent much more time looking around.  When we got back to the estuary, the water was much lower and we had to navigate carefully around the rocks.  Where before there was smooth water, we found rapids—but they were easy to handle because we were travelling with the flow of the river.  At the mouth of the estuary, we took a left turn and checked out a little cove, switching boats because the seat of the Eskia was digging into my back.  It was hot so we opted to take the shadow route back on the west side of Varney Bay, especially for Chloe’s sake.  </p>

<p>On our way back to Rupert Inlet, we were fighting the tide and the wind.  Our seemingly minutes long journey going down this route turned into a trip that took possibly hours!  After we battled to pass one point of land, we discovered another and then another, all of which seemed to take forever to get to!  I had no idea there were so many points between the camp and the estuary!  Finally, we had to take a break and get our land legs back, landing on a shadowy shore full of barnacles.  It was cold and clammy, and Chloe had a hard time walking on the barnacles.  We didn’t stay there more than a few minutes, but I needed to feel ground under my feet to be able to paddle the rest of the way. 
Getting back to camp, James got out of his kayak, dragged mine up the shore and then helped me out.  I walked slowly to the tent, and, in spite of the intense heat inside it, collapsed on the air mattress and immediately fell asleep.  James came sometime later and became comatose too.  </p>

<p>Coming out of my nap, I heard to the grunting and groaning of a tugboat taking logs away.  I got up to take pictures.  By the evening, the log 
boom was gone. We started a fire, visited a bit with our human and doggie neighbours and took numerous pictures of the sunset over Rupert Inlet. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/tugboatatwork.jpg" alt="Tugboat at work"><em>Tugbot at work.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/pastelsunset.jpg" alt="Pastel sunset"><em>Pastel sunset.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/rococosunset.jpg" alt="Rococo sunset"><em>Rococo sunset.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/harmonyinredandblue.jpg" alt="Harmony in red and blue"><em>Harmony in red and blue.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/sunsetwithvirga.jpg" alt="Sunset with virga"><em>Sunset with virga.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/goldensunset.jpg" alt="Golden sunset"><em>Golden sunset.</em></p>

<p><b>June 28, 2015</b>,</p>

<p>After the magnificent trip down the estuary, we were expecting a low-key day.  It didn’t turn out that way.  Somehow, James, Chloe and I seem to have a real knack for finding adventure.  We first contemplated just lazing around all morning.  With the water very still and the coming of slack tide around noon, we got lured into cutting across the Rupert Arm Inlet to visit the old Utah Mine site.  We talked about my need for a hat and sunglasses.  I tried to put a pair of James’s sunglasses over mine, but it didn’t work.  I took my glasses off and put on the sunglasses alone.  I was surprised that there didn’t seem to be much difference in my vision. As near sighted people get older, their vision improves.  I put my prescription glasses in the dry bag and just used the sunglasses.  It wasn’t a fashion statement, but it worked.  I opted to go without a hat, as none of James’ hats fit my head (hats rarely do) and I have plenty of hair for protection anyway.<br>
While we were getting ready, Chloe waited dutifully by the kayaks across the roadway.  She now gets eager to go on a kayak ride like she does a car ride!  Even though she seemed to look forward to the ride, she did nothing but whine all the way across.  We eventually figured out she was probably too hot, and that we would have to keep wetting her down.  We arrived at the north end of the mine and paddled in, out and around the maze of logs and machinery, feeling like kids in an adult sized playground.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/chloeeagertokayak.jpg" alt="Chloe eager to kayak"><em>Chloe eager to kayak.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/utahmineoreconveyer.jpg" alt="Utah mine ore conveyer"><em>Utah mine ore conveyer.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/utahminedockingpier.jpg" alt="Utah mine docking pier"><em>Utah mine docking pier.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/hidaddy.jpg" alt="Hi Daddy!"><em>Hi Daddy!</em></p>

<p>Paddling south of the mine, we came upon the artificial cove created to fill the old copper mine site when it was closed nearly 20 years ago.  James, the Campbell River native, said it took a long time to fill up.  My research tells me it took from May 15th to August 15th in 1996 to be exact.  When the mine site was finally filled, it was sealed off from the cove.  It was then left to nature—in a very big way as we would soon find out!  As we paddled deeper into the man-made cove, we were both looking at a spot with a cliff and tall dark and spooky looking pine trees.  A gigantic eagle soared from tree to tree, looking not the least bit intimidated by our presence.   We were actually intimidated by his, because of Chloe.  An eagle could easily pick up a dog like Chloe.  When I first went to a mountain lookout, I had my then 10-year old son with me and I was told, to my amazement, an eagle would be able to pick him up!  It seems hard to believe, was probably unlikely (especially since I always kept him close by) but was very possible!  James and I have seen footage on TV of an eagle flying while dangling a mountain goat from its claws!    </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/theeagle.jpg" alt="The eagle"><em>The eagle.</em></p>

<p>We came up to a spot near the end of the cove with a flat sandy beach under some old twisted pines.  As we approached we peered into a small clearing in the bushes and thought we saw a deer.  It was certainly the size of a deer.  It seemed to move like a deer.  It was definitely the colour of a deer.  I shouted to James to look.  He also thought it was a deer.  Then, the creature turned in a way that was very <i>undeerlike</i>.  Even without my glasses I could see that it was definitely not a deer, as its tail was way too long and bushy!  I yelled “It’s a wolf!”  The wolf gave us perturbed look, then walked off on his incredibly long legs.  </p>

<p>After the caves at the Marble River Estuary, we weren’t expecting much excitement.  We got some anyway.</p>

<p>Sometime after this kayaking trip, I took the ferry to Vancouver.  To entertain the passengers, there was a biologist on board giving a talk about sea otters.  To get the talk going, she asked members of the audience if they had had any wildlife sightings.  People mentioned seeing bears, whales, sea lions, sea otters, eagles, and so on.  I then piped up with “wolf.”  The biologist looked at me, surprised, and then said, “I’m jealous.”  You know you’ve had a rare animal sighting when you can make a biologist envious! </p>

<p>Finding a place to land a good distance from the spot where we saw the wolf, we had a snack on shore and marvelled at what we had just experienced.  James and I then switched kayaks for the trek back across Rupert Arm.  We paddled alongside the shore to a far point and then decided to make the mad dash across the inlet.  James had the more stable kayak and didn’t even use a rudder.  I had the more slippery one.  We debated about which point to head into the crossing.  I wanted to go further south and then let the wind, waves and tide carry us down the shore to the campsite.  James wanted to cut diagonally across.  I tried to do what he wanted but found my kayak not cooperating with my intentions.  My rudder was pushed all the way down, but somehow, I was only managing to go straight across the inlet instead of diagonally.  It may have been that way because I was getting knocked around going parallel with the waves.  Turning perpendicular into the waves gave me some stability.  “Boy are you stubborn!” James said as he followed me straight across.  Yes, I’m stubborn, I proudly admit it, but I only draw on that stubbornness when absolutely necessary or for something very important.  I wasn’t trying to be stubborn this time.  I was also getting frustrated with the roughness of the waves and wanted the uneasy crossing to be over as soon as possible, so I did some sprinting.  I was surprised how paddling a certain way and expending a lot of effort turned my kayak into a speed machine. It was easier to do on the Eskia too, because it was the lighter swifter boat.  </p>

<p>We had a complicated difficult docking at low tide.  James landed first and took out Chloe and all his stuff, then lifted his kayak by himself out of the water.  I paddled around to keep from being swept north by the wind and the waves until it was my turn to dock.  James held down my kayak so I could lift myself out with relative ease.  For nearly 40 years of my life, I have virtually survived by my own means and in some pretty rough conditions!  Now, I have a partner who worries about me getting in and out of a kayak!  Like I said before, I will enjoy this situation before he sees the light!  </p>

<p>We dragged the kayaks onto the grass, sat down and drank some fake beer and then; after creating as much air circulation as possible inside the tent by opening windows, we did some reading on our air mattresses and had a nap.  </p>

<p>For the rest of the night we sat around our fire, eating smokies, watching the flames and admiring the sunset at its various stages. James was doing some sorting with our camping gear, so I decided to go to the docking area.  I sat on the rocks, meditating and watching the sunset, thinking back to my days at Round Hill Tower in Lac La Biche in the 1980s when I would, after a day in the fire tower, sometimes go down to the lake at Mile 27 in my little Honda Civic (you’d be amazed how that little city car managed in the bush!) and do this very thing.  I tried to capture that feeling again, of being alone in my own little bubble—which is quite different from my life now.  James can’t seem to figure out why I don’t seem to get “lonely” when he goes a way to work for a couple of weeks or month.  I frequently have to remind him that it has been like I’ve been on the TV series <i>Alone</i> for 4 to 6 months at a time for 18 years of my life!  </p>

<p>I sometimes miss being alone.  I miss being able to hear my own thoughts.  I can get tired of the endless distractions of civilized life: the scheduling, the commuting, the multi tasking and the playing phone tag.  Curious things can happen in solitude.  Once you get adjusted to the idea of being alone, you start to notice more things around you.  You notice the wildflower you might not have seen if you were conversing with someone.  You notice all the markings of a caterpillar and its unique way of moving.  You start to see all the diversity in nature: that it’s not just trees and grass, but a huge plethora of vegetation competing and cooperating for the same space.  Not only that, but you may discover, like I did, that plants can “talk.”  Very often I will go out to my garden and sit on my lawn chair with no preconceived plan or intention.  As I sit there, “taking it all in,” I notice thoughts that creep into my brain that seem to be the quiet voices of the plants trying to communicate their needs to me.  They will say things to me like, “Hey lady, we need pruning, or hilling, or watering right now.”  Although one can say it is all still my own thoughts, sometimes I can come up with ideas that I never thought of before, or ideas I haven’t thought about in a while, even decades. You might say that is just creativity, but what, really, is creativity?  It might be just a nebulous name for some entity we can’t understand yet. I think the First Nations people have come closer to giving that entity a more distinct form in the shape of “spirits” of animals, the land, the sky and the water.  </p>

<p>In solitude, you discover that the animals have temperaments, and that you can mentally connect with them, even share a bit of good humour.  Although you don’t share a language, you can get a lot of information from their body language, their gestures and the look in their eyes.  When you can connect with another creature in this way, it can sometimes make you feel that language is redundant. </p>

<p>In solitude, you realize clouds are not just clouds, and that there is a complex interplay going in the skies too. You become more aware of the moon, the stars and the planets.  You can look out in the southwest sky and see Mars hanging there, looking so clear and orange and immediate, that it feels like you’re peeking into your next-door neighbour’s yard!  Not only that, but removing people and distraction allows more things to come up from within.  The vacuum of solitude leaves more room for ideas to come up from the imagination, which is how I got into writing in the first place.  </p>

<p>Lately, I’ve developed a special “thinking technique.”  I just ask my brain for an idea or a solution to a problem, release it, and, sometime later, usually when I’m quiet and away from distractions, the answer comes to me as if delivered by another force.  I’ve come to recognise a force in my brain that is possibly <i>not</i> my brain.  A while back, I disconnected my cable TV and discovered, to my surprise, I was not bored at all!  On the contrary, I found myself bombarded with ideas and solutions to problems like crazy!  For those of you suffering from writer’s block, just get away from the crowds, shut off all the media, be still, and your writer’s block will probably be dislodged!  The cable TV is connected again; but, I limit how much I watch it.  After my experience without TV, I notice now, that when I watch it, I feel a little like a zombie, or like I’m being hypnotized, and I find it a little disturbing.  </p>

<p>Living in solitude also leaves room for things to come up from the subconscious mind—some of it scary, some of it delightful.  You have the time to think about certain assumptions that were false and misleading, and analyze your own responses to others and others’ responses to you.  You get less reactionary and more contemplative (simply because there is no one around to react to!).  I found I became more aware of my dreams, and at times felt I was getting special messages delivered to me through my dreams—something I might not have noticed while maintaining a “busy” life.  </p>

<p>I’ve come to understand the forest as not just a bunch of trees, animals and vegetation, but as a spiritual entity.  Even though there may be bears and cougars around that could eat me, there is something about that spiritual entity that is deeply comforting!  When I’m alone, I don’t really feel alone at all; in fact, quite the contrary.  I become friends with my surroundings, as well as my inner life, my psychic reality and possibly alternate creative realities.  I tend to feel alone in places like downtown Vancouver with its many attention grabbers that take me away from my inner self.  It’s a good thing I’m living in Port Alice—the next best thing to living in a lookout—and that I have a partner who likes sitting in the bush and watching time go by as much as I do.  If I was forced to live in the city again year round, I would probably loose all my marbles!  I would have to press the rescue button on the proverbial satellite phone and beg to be dropped somewhere in the middle of nowhere!  </p>

<p>In some indigenous cultures, young people have to perform a rite of passage by travelling into the forest or the dessert all alone with only a few tools.  It seems like a cruel thing to do; however, if you survive the trip, it can give you an inner strength and awareness that is invaluable!  Perhaps experiences of solitude are relevant for all cultures, and could have an effect of curbing crime, depression and relationship dysfunction.  </p>

<p>James came up to me a little cautiously.  He asked me for permission to join me and permission was granted.  We threw stones in the water.  As our ripples merged, it created a glittery effect on the water that seemed to go on and on—long after the ripples were done being ripples. We sat quietly, enjoying the light and colour, until Venus dropped down from a sheet of middle cloud, then Jupiter.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/venusandjupiter.jpg" alt="Venus and Jupiter"><em>Venus and Jupiter.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/inkysunset.jpg" alt="Inky sunset"><em>Inky sunset.</em></p>

<p><b>June 29, 2015</b></p>

<p>Our neighbours moved out, leaving their smouldering fire as if they thought it would somehow put itself out!  I was shocked, especially when a forest officer drove into the campsite a couple of days before to remind us to put out our campfires and that a fire ban was imminent!  As the campfire culprit drove away, he stopped and generously handed us some of his catch of prawns and crab.  Thanks for the fish, but not for nearly burning down our forests!   With slightly stunned looks, we graciously accepted the offering.  We decided to shift camp and use his fire for our crab and prawn feast.  We put Chloe on a folding camp chair with an umbrella to block out the sun.  James made a bit of garlic butter for the prawns and fried them up.  We boiled up the crab and sat breaking them and munching on them for quite some time.  It wasn’t just <i>eating</i>, it was <i>playing</i> too.  James said you could tell the meat was fresh because it was plump—no shrinkage.  We doused the fire completely and took a picture of it for old time’s sake.  We partially loaded up the truck, but left the tent up because our comforter was drying on top of it.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/seafoodfeast.jpg" alt="Seafood feast"><em>Seafood feast.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/chloegettingsomeshade.jpg" alt="Chloe getting some shade"><em>Chloe getting some shade.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/thefireisout.jpg" alt="The fire is out!"><em>The fire is out!</em></p>

<p>Before going back home, we opted for a “short quick trip” across the inlet, which turned out to be a lot more than that.  Because of the heat, we rigged up an umbrella on the boat so Chloe could have some shade.  It produced a lot of laughs.  We headed for what we thought was an island.  We paddled straight and steady.  After reaching the other side, we saw a couple of quiet coves with clear greenish water.  Just when we were about to land, the water started churning up.  I got panicky and insisted we go straight back.  James said, “Hold on a minute here, I’m not going anywhere without my snack!” so we docked at the cove.  James gets lots of “snack attacks”; in fact, he is a virtually non-stop eating machine!  It’s a mystery why he stays so slim!  I am beginning to think that peoples’ metabolisms are as unique and varied as their personalities.    </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/chloekayakingwithanumbrella.jpg" alt="Chloe kayaking with an umbrella"><em>Chloe kayaking with an umbrella.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/nowdowelooksillyorwhat.jpg" alt="Now do we look silly or what!"><em>Now do we look silly or what!</em></p>

<p>We found a nice log to sit on in front of a massive tree stump.  We watched the waves churn about as we ate!  We were especially vigilant about keeping Chloe on the leash, after seeing Mr. Wolf and Mr. Eagle yesterday.  I took pictures of a giant stump and the sea asparagus on the shore.  If you’re ever a contestant on the TV series <i>Alone</i>, you can get your vitamins from sea asparagus.  They are OK to eat raw.  They are salty and a bit crunchy, reminding me of potato chips.  You can also use them to make stir fries, and even pickles.  I made a batch of sea asparagus pickles and found them to be quite tasty, though James hasn’t been willing to brave them so far.  Oh well, all the more for me!  The interesting thing about making stuff from foraged food is that it is hard to eat in the beginning, simply because it is so unfamiliar.  Once you make the paradigm shift, you can never go back!  Something similar bought in the store just doesn’t have the character and richness as something made with foraged or home grown food.  For recipes for sea asparagus pickles and stir fries, check out Google.  I found a good pickle recipe at <i>www.westcoastseaweed.com.</i></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/driftwoodstump.jpg" alt="Driftwood stump"><em>Driftwood stump.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/seaasparagus.jpg" alt="Sea asparagus"><em>Sea asparagus.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/seaasparaguspickles.jpg" alt="Sea asparagus pickles"><em>Sea asparagus pickles.</em></p>

<p>Between watching <i>Alone</i>, and doing my own research, I am amazed at the amount of available food there is in nature.  I’ve even seen hungry <i>Alone</i> contestants walk past stuff they could have made a hardy meal out of!  You need to know what you’re are doing though, as, in my estimation, about half the stuff that is out in nature is poisonous.  It is amazing that animals know what’s safe and what’s not without access to the internet!  They have <i>another</i> internet that they use.  Maybe some day we humans might have full access to <i>that</i> internet…and then maybe we can clean up the mess we are making of our planet!   </p>

<p>When we were done eating, all our cameras out of power, we put them in the dry bag.  We realized that Chloe’s umbrella was going to have to be packed up because it would be a hindrance going back through the rough water.  Luckily the waves were perpendicular to our direction, so we could cut straight through them to prevent tipping.  We were definitely dealing with the “time moving more slowly” effect.  We bounced a lot and got splashed a few times.  Maintaining a faster steady pace on the rough water was wearing me out.  At the end, James got a second wind and sprinted.  I had no hopes of beating him, but I was determined to keep up with him.  When he turned back to look, he was surprised to find me not far behind.  I said I knew he’d be surprised.  </p>

<p>After we landed I found a blanket and lay there immobile for quite some time.  James came over and gave me a sympathy cuddle and continued to pack up the truck.  I joked that he can load up the truck and I’ll supervise and make sure he’s doing a good job. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/mytrucklookinglikeachristmastree.jpg" alt="My truck looking like a Christmas tree!"><em>My truck looking like a Christmas tree!</em>.
<img src="/assets/images/post6-varney/theroadtocivilization.jpg" alt="Road to civilization"><em>Road to civilization.</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>"Friggen" Islands and "Neurosis" Inlet</title>
	  <link>//frigon-islands</link>
	  <author>Debra Lynn</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-10T17:15:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//frigon-islands</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><b>June 21, 2015</b></p>

<p>We were discussing the various possibilities for kayaking, and wanted to leave some of the best stuff for a visit from James’s daughter and/or my son. On this day we settled on few hours of kayaking on Neroutsos Inlet, which included the Frigon Islands and the lighthouse.</p>

<p>Some of you might be wondering about the names of our inlet and the islands in them. Yes, “Neroutsos” does sound a lot like the psychological disorder and Frigon sounds like a substitute swear word. Back in the seventies, when the mill dumped pollution into the inlet indiscriminately (before they seriously cleaned up their act because of new government regulations), people who were opposed to it would call it, “Neurosis Inlet.” Well, the name “neurosis” seems to have stuck. When I came here in 2010, practically anyone I’ve talked to has pronounced the name like the psychological disorder. If you look closely at the name “Neroutsos” and follow the rules of English pronunciation, it should sound a little different. It doesn’t flow smoothly off the tongue, however, which is probably why people tend to default to “neurosis.”</p>

<p>The name “Neroutsos” actually has a very honourable origin. It was the name of a hardy and heroic big wig and pioneer in the development of navigation in western coastal waters, Captain Cyril Demitrius Neroutsos. Born into a wealthy shipping family in 1868 in Bowden, Cheshire, England, his considerable metal was soon tested when he became an orphan at age 13. With barely any time to grieve his circumstances, he set out on the high seas as an officer cadet. In addition to trade excursions around the globe, he ended up participating in the New Zealand to London clipper ship races around the Cape. By the time he reached 18, he had sailed around the world four times! With the arrival of steam, Neroutsos acquired his papers for deep sea master and signed on with the <i>British India Steam Navigation Company</i>. This brought him to Seattle during the Klondike Gold Rush where he became marine superintendent for the <i>Frank Waterhouse Company</i>. In 1901, he switched over to the <i>Canadian Pacific Navigation Company</i>; and, because of his qualification as a lieutenant Commander in the <i>Royal Naval Reserve</i>, he was promoted from marine superintendent to Manager of the costal fleet.  Although his knowledge of the deep seas was impeccable, he signed on as a mate on the <i> S.S. Islander</i> in order to gain more familiarity with coastal waters. While he was asleep in his quarters, the ship struck an iceberg off the shores of Alaska and sank in 20 minutes. As soon as the ship struck, Neroutsos went knocking on cabin doors, waking up passengers and assisting people onto the deck. The last man off the deck before the ship disappeared into the sea, he continued his heroic feats in the water. A strong swimmer and apparently impervious to the frigid Alaska water (I can’t even handle the water down here in the middle of the summer!) he helped save a man with an injured leg by lifting him onto a door from the wreckage. Incredibly, he stayed afloat in the water until help arrived! When he was found, Neroutsos was hypothermic, but holding an unconscious girl on his shoulders who survived because of his efforts. There were many causalties from the sinking. Neroutsos was the only executive officer to survive.</p>

<p>Despite this legendary account, Neroutsos is remembered because he was able to make sweeping advancements in coastal navigation in a single lifetime, keeping people as safe as possible in the relatively uncharted waters of the New World. </p>

<p>Ed Frigon, after whom our islands are named, was another unbeatable North Island pioneer. Hailing from Maurice Quebec, he set out to make it big in the California Gold Rush of the 1850s. When things did not go his way there, he set his compass for a life of adventure in the Pacific Northwest. After working a few years in Victoria to save money, he chartered a sealing schooner for Hope Island (Bull Harbour) in 1857. He spent 32 years running a fur trading post for local First Nations and passing sealing and whaling ships. In 1895, he moved to Limestone Island, now called Drake Island, in the Quatsino area. This is the island that we saw on our paddle from Atkin’s Cove. It is interesting to think that this lonely looking uninhabited island was once a happening place! In Quiet Cove (now called Pamphlet Cove), in the middle of the Island, Frigon opened a trading post, a floating wharf and a three storey hotel with fourteen rooms and a saloon! The hotel ran for 8 years before it was shut down mainly because of prohibition in 1917. An elderly Ed Frigon then moved to a large homestead north of Port Alice to spend his remaining days with his late in life love interest First Nations woman and “Last of the Longheads,” Lucy Moon, who was about 50 years his junior. </p>

<p>Frigon was only 5’2”, but he was strong as an ox, with a personality to suit. A true pioneer, he chose to live in a remote part of the world where there were very few white people, and probably not a single Francophone! Not only did he survive life in the wilderness, he found a way to make a living. He gave commerce on the North Island a serious jump start in the process. He was so much the heartbeat of commercial life of the community that his influence continued even after he passed away. A general store in Quatsino that opened shortly after his death was named after him. Lucy Moon remained living on Frigon’s property, and, after teaming up with Nip Wong, worked Frigon’s land and supplied Port Alice with fresh produce for many years. Frigon’s hotel was floated down to the old Port Alice townsite and renamed “Jones’s Hotel” and used for housing mill workers. It was also used as a community dance hall that was probably the starting point of many Port Alice romances. The hotel was finally destroyed in the mid-1960s, along with the rest of the buildings of Old Port Alice, when the town site was moved to Rumble Beach. Probably every transaction that happens and every child that is born on the North Island since is, in some way, touched by the ghost of Ed Frigon. </p>

<p>We were getting pretty fast at loading and unloading the kayaks. We launched at low tide at the Marina, but not at the boat dock because I think you have to pay. We passed boats and a pole coated with mussels going up to the highest tide level. We were heading in the direction of the Frigon Islands. We passed around the north side, seeing the rocks encrusted with barnacles and plant life in a variety of hues. When you launch at low tide, you get to see everything that lives under the water part time! When we came around the other side, we found a small cove with a pebbly beach. We decided this was to be the place for our snack when we were ready. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/palice_marine_1.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Port Alice Marina 1.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/palice_marine_2.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Port Alice Marina 2.</em> 
<img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/pole_mussels.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Pole with Mussels.</em></p>

<p>We contemplated visiting some friends who lived across the inlet. We had started out quite late (we slept in), so we had missed the best part of the day for paddling on calm waters. We headed in that direction, but chickened out part way there. We were suspecting the waves would get choppy soon from the inflow winds. For those of you who don’t know what inflow winds are (I just learned this recently), they are produced when the mid-day heat from the inlet rises up and creates a gap for cooler winds to come rushing in from the ocean. When the winds come rushing down the inlet, not only does it create wind resistance, it makes for higher waves, and, depending what is happening with the tides and the currents, it can make for complicated boating in general. Neroutsos Inlet is a great place for low key kayaking, what I like to call “Chihuahua kayaking”— or family kayaking, as it is sheltered from the rough waters of the ocean by mountain ranges. It is not like some places around Tofino that have breakers and high waves which are good for surfing and more acrobatic kayaking. On the inlet, you only have to work around the inflow winds; but, even then, they are only a bit challenging. You will get a good example of this later in this account. Generally speaking, to get calm easy kayaking, you should do it in the morning. Unfortunately, James and I are not morning people, but we’re working on it. </p>

<p>I didn’t want to do the trip across the inlet either because we still hadn’t found a proper life jacket for Chloe. James recently went to Campbell River to get her a life jacket and take care of some other business. When he put it on Chloe, she didn’t look too comfortable. He had been looking for a life jacket for her for a while with little luck. Chloe is a small dog who is big around the middle. Most small dog vests tend to be too small and medium sized vests fit her around the middle, but nowhere else. We thought the tabs at the front of this latest one might be too bothersome for her small head. James said he saw one that would be better at Bosley’s, but they didn’t have her size. We decided to return the life jacket he bought and keep looking for a better one. This is not easy for us, as we live two and half hours from “civilization.” Shopping on the North Island hasn’t improved much since Ed Frigon’s time.  </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/lifejacket.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>The not too comfortable lifejacket.</em></p>

<p>As we paddled around we saw a prawning boat and waited until it passed us. We were respecting the laws of the water: little boats yield to big boats. We then had a little fun bouncing up and down on the wake waves. Later there came a tremendously large sailboat with the sails down. We estimated its value at about a million. When we launched from the marina, we saw two boats that we estimated at 200 and 300 thousand. Such capitalists we are! We appreciate a boat’s beauty by its possible price tag! You have to admit that the price tag has a definite bearing on aesthetics! It just happens to be one aspect of appreciating something than most people can relate to. I mentioned to James that I thought this inlet should be full of such boats, as well as kayaks and canoes and such. I think Port Alice is a mini Monaco that has not been discovered yet.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/mini-monnaco.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>A burgeoning mini Monaco.</em></p>

<p>The water wasn’t very choppy, but we suspected it would be soon. By the time we headed back to the Island, it was past noon and we were hungry. As we landed, the tide was low so there was plenty of ground to walk on. We realized that high tide would leave only a narrow grassy patch between the two islands. It might even be completely submersed in a super high tide. There were remnants of a campfire right on that ridge. We contemplated how it would be fun to spend the night here, looking at the “bright lights” of Port Alice while sitting around a campfire. There is beauty to be found in human constructions, as well as Nature’s. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/jamesmefrigon.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>James and me on the Frigon Islands.</em></p>

<p>We sat down and had our lunch of hummus and rice crackers, cheese and blue berries. The crows on the Islands made quite a racket for quite some time, enough to start getting on our nerves. I’m not sure what the issue was, whether they felt we intruding on their territory or if they were excited about possible left overs and handouts. These crows were very different from the crows in Port Alice. The crows at the school, in particular, gather on the roof of the school at recess time, waiting in a row and quietly watching as the kids as they drop all kinds of goodies and crumbs on the ground. When the class bell rings they know it is <i>their</i> lunch time! These crows on the Frigon Islands were a little more “wild.” Their cawing was loud and hostile sounding. They did settle down eventually, though. I guess it was a different “tribe” of crows, with different customs and practices. </p>

<p>On the island, Chloe engaged herself in the doggie business of sniffing around for “doggie emails” and sending a few herself.  Animals have their own version of the internet based on scent! After our snack, James, Chloe and I went searching for trails. The North part of the island was quite forbidding: it was tightly closed in with very thick trees and Salal. We found what looked like a trail opening on the south end of the island. We pushed through the Salal to find somewhat of a clearing that would be reasonably good for pitching a tent. We followed the very overgrown but still faintly discernible trail to the south end of the island and found a lookout perch with a rough hewnbench, another remnant of a campfire and one heck of a view! We could see some island lumps sticking out of the water. The view of the inlet was a high one, and we felt like we were on top of the world! It would be wonderful to sit and stare at it in front of a campfire around twilight and then watch the stars at night without fear of running into predators. Looking up from the lookout perch, we saw a weather worn old snag with all the crows sitting on it, by this time settled down. I took some nice shots of them, but most had flown away before I was able to get a really good one. I then took some nice shots of the view. We sat for quite some time in the sun and enjoyed the view. Chloe made herself comfortable under the bench in the shade. It was hot! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/doggie_biz.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Chloe checking her inbox.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/island_lumps.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Island lumps.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/bench.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>The rough hewn bench.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/cove_entrance.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Cove entrance.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/2010_landslide.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>View of 2010 landslide.</em></p>

<p>Instead of going back into the brush, we went around the rocks down to the cove and back to our landing spot. When we got back there, we discovered that the crows had cleared away our left-over crackers!  No wonder they settled down! We went walking around the north side of the island looking for a trail in a few places but we were forced to turn back. </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/crows.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>The crows.</em></p>

<p>There was a lot of sea asparagus on the island. James and I quibbled on how to pick them. I tried to pick them individually and he just pulled them up by the handfuls. I told him to be more selective, and just pick the nice bright green juicy looking ones. It also gives the plant a greater chance of surviving. James joked that he was fired. I said “Yeh, you are!” but he just kept on picking, though he did start to be more selective. I mentioned I could consult my Chinese cookbooks and make a stir fry with them with Chinese mushrooms, fresh mushrooms and maybe black beans. We started picking them where there was more shade, as that was where they seemed to be the greenest and juiciest. We picked a Ziploc container full and then some, which was too bad, because we ended up forgetting them and not realizing it until we got all the way back home. </p>

<p>Worried that the tide might take our boats away, James had tied them to a big piece of driftwood. When we arrived, the kayaks were sitting on rocks. By the time we were getting ready to leave, they were floating and James had to pull them in. As I was waiting for James to load up, I slowly paddled out to the mouth of the little cove and was peek-a-booed by a seal! Its head was just above the water and it was staring at me with a child-like curiosity for some moments before it ducked out of sight. I could definitely get a “vibe” from this seal. Just like I can get a good idea of what someone is thinking by their facial expression and body language, I felt a short merging of minds with this seal. It turns out, seeing us humans is as much of a novelty as seeing them is for us! </p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/where_mom.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Where&#39;s Mommy?</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/theres_mommy.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Oh, There&#39;s Mommy!</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/artist_at_work.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Artist at work.</em></p>

<p>James was taking a while packing up and, used to him being so efficient and thorough, I didn’t worry about the sea asparagus that I left a little too far from our gear. We paddled around the south of the islands between the out-cropping of rocks, running into some kind of swimming grey fluffy water birds. Then, it was on to the lighthouse!</p>

<p>Having been a lookout, I have quite an affinity for lighthouses. I was determined to get there sometime and it looked like this was the day. We probably should have gone there first, because, by the time we were on our way there, it was well into the afternoon and the water was starting to get rough. We probably should have gone to the lighthouse first, <i>then</i> the islands. The water got rougher as we got closer to the lighthouse. I absolutely wanted a nice picture of the lighthouse, but my phone camera-- James’s old Galaxy 3--was out of battery. There was only James’ brand new Samsung Galaxy Note 4 that he just bought a few days ago in Campbell River that still had battery life—but he had it in his boat! Because the water was so rough and the current kept pushing us all about, we were having trouble getting coordinated. We were reluctant to pass the brand new phone from one kayak to the other for fear it would end up on the bottom of the inlet!  Having a couple of art degrees, I’m pretty persnickety about how to take photos. I went to the place to show James where I wanted the picture to be taken from, but, after doing a little fiddling and looking away, the current had pushed me metres away from the desired position! I was also scared of getting too close to the lighthouse, for fear of crashing into it and losing my balance. It was a lot like being on a conveyor belt, with a large immobile jagged object at one end of it! Alas, I was unsuccessful at getting my message across. James took several photos, but they were not centred like I wanted them and probably not taken from the place that I wanted them taken. He suggested we could crop it.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/lighthouse.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>The lighthouse.</em>
<img src="/assets/images/post5-friggon/frenzy_lighthouse.jpg" alt="Friggon Islands"><em>Frenzy around the lighthouse.</em></p>

<p>Between our battles with the current and the increasing choppiness of the water, we suddenly sensed an urgency to head to shore and abandon this business of getting a well-framed photograph. We were especially nervous since Chloe did not have her life jacket yet. We were bumping up and down on the waves, which was kind of fun albeit a little nerve wracking. We tried to head to shore but didn’t seem to be getting anywhere at all! We were aiming to head north to Jeune Landing and it was proving elusive as the current kept pushing us away from it. Finally, frustrated, I was determined to get out of this rough water. I said to James “race ya!” and engaged my paddling warp drive in the hopes of actually getting somewhere. It worked and the shore finally came in sight. James wasn’t too far behind me. We arrived at the shore, a bit south of Jeune Landing. The waves were still just as high as they were in the middle of the inlet and the current was still pushing us south. That short trip would have demanded a lot of power and we were just about spent! We gave up going to Jeune Landing and followed the shore back to the marina. We likely got ourselves on TV when we paddled by the Brooks Bay Cable weather camera. We complained how tired we were the whole way back, paddling slowly and meekly like we were a couple of 120-year olds (I was inclined to say 90 year olds, but I suspect that there are some 90 year olds out there who could seriously out paddle us!). Even Chloe was looking tired, though she didn’t have to paddle. She had emerged from her fleece and was sitting up, hot and panting, with her unusually big tongue hanging way out. We brought our two kayaks together and poured some water into her little red bowl so she could have a drink. </p>

<p>As is evidenced by our experience that day, boating can be pretty complicated. Between currents, tides, weather and the position of the sun, not to mention whatever may be under the water like reefs, whales and icebergs, you have to know what is going to happen in the water at any particular time and where exactly it will happen. Just think, our Captain Neroutsos had to have a good grasp of all these factors for the <i>entire west coast</i>—not to mention the fact that he knew this stuff for all the oceans around the world—and in a time before GPS and Google maps! It’s hard even to imagine! The guy definitely deserves to have an inlet named after him!  Both Neroutsos and Frigon very much deserved their honours, as they both seemed larger than life. Now, after researching these two men, when I say “Frigon Islands on Neroutsos Inlet,” I no longer say it with a bit of a snigger, but with reverence. </p>

<p>Once we were on shore, we discovered we were more tired than we originally thought. My body felt like lead. We were even too pooped to wash down the kayaks. For the rest of the day we were virtually useless, doing minimal domestic routine like zombies, afflicted with something that only a good night’s sleep could remedy. </p>

<p>I would like to say a special thanks to Evelyn Hartford at the Port Alice Tourist Information centre for providing me with historical information for this and future blog entries. A lot of the history of Port Alice cannot easily be found in mainstream information sources. Thankfully, people like her are indispensable for keeping this information preserved and bringing awareness to that fact before it is forever lost to the passage of time.</p>

<p><i>I&#39;d like to thank Gwen Hansen at the Quatsino Museum for providingme with information on Ed Frigon for this and future posts. I hopes she&#39;s right, and that someone makes a movie about &quot;Old Ned&quot; someday.</i></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
